<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of Spain being a new description of that country and people, and of the sea ports along the Mediterranean : of Ceuta, Tangier, &amp;c. / written by a French gentleman, who was in disguise aboard the English fleet, with an account of the most remarkable transactions of that fleet : to which is added, a large preface concerning the establishment of the Spanish crown, on the Duke of Anjou.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 257 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 115 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A226C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13796</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077434</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077434</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75204)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2261:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of Spain being a new description of that country and people, and of the sea ports along the Mediterranean : of Ceuta, Tangier, &amp;c. / written by a French gentleman, who was in disguise aboard the English fleet, with an account of the most remarkable transactions of that fleet : to which is added, a large preface concerning the establishment of the Spanish crown, on the Duke of Anjou.</title>
                  <author>R.</author>
                  <author>Lewis, E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 192 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Wilde ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within double line border.</note>
                  <note>Letters signed: R.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: E. Lewis.</note>
                  <note>Pages 91,110 incorrectly numbered 61, 104 respectively.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spain --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151495:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151495:2"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF SPAIN: BEING A New Deſcription of that COUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRY and PEOPLE; And of the <hi>SEA PORTS</hi> along the <hi>Mediterranean:</hi> Of <hi>Ceuta, Tangier,</hi> &amp;c. Written by a <hi>French</hi> Gentleman, who was in diſguiſe Aboard the <hi>Engliſh Fleet:</hi> With an Account of the moſt Remarkable Tranſactions of that <hi>Fleet.</hi> To which is added, A Large Preface concerning the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Crown, on the DUKE of <hi>ANJOU.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Wilde,</hi> at the <hi>Elephant</hi> at <hi>Charing-Croſs,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151495:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151495:3"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt Noble PRINCE HENRY DUKE of <hi>NORFOLK,</hi> Earl <hi>Marſhal</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> One of His Majeſtys moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privy Council, Knight of the moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Order of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE following Letters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſome general remarks of what happen'd in the <hi>Engliſh
<pb facs="tcp:151495:4"/>
Fleet,</hi> that was ſent to the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean</hi> toward the letter end of the laſt War; with ſome obſervations of the poſture and diſpoſition of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nation as it then ſtood. The Account is not ſo particular as it might have been, I wiſh ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more had been ſaid of the Hiſtory and Politicks of that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that it might have been more ſeaſonable for this preſent juncture, when the eyes of all the World are pointed to that Empire: But to make amends for that Omiſſion, I take every thing in it to be very juſtly deſcrib'd, moſt of it having occur'd to my own experience, and to the Knowledge of all the Curious in that Voyage: And as I can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Account to be juſt, ſo there is little or nothing ſaid that ever has been mention'd by any other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:151495:4"/>I have form'd it into a Book for your Graces peruſal, and am happy that I can lay it at your feet in a time when your confinement at home by a troubleſome pain, and ſometimes your want of Company gives you leiſure to read it over: And tho' I know your Graces Palate to be exceeding Nice in all ſorts of reading, yet I am not more diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd at that, than I am animated with your Goodneſs and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p>The opportunities I have had of your Converſation were very fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to me: by them I had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of being known to your Grace; By them I have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at ſome of the Politeſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes that I have met with, and by them I have, of conſequence, refin'd my own Capacity; and I can't chuſe but ſay, I was aſtoniſht
<pb facs="tcp:151495:5"/>
to hear the firſt Peer of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Nobility has been of late years leſs Curious of theſe finer Studies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> talk ſo well. My next thought was, (may my Lord par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me) that if the Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> were ſtript of all his Titles, and cou'd come upon the Square to converſe with ſuch as me, there is not a Man on earth whoſe Society I ſhou'd ſo much covet: But in the pleaſure of that thought I forgot my diſtance, not conſidering that Nature, as well as the ſcituation of your Birth, had put ſo great a Bar betwixt you and me, that like the Sun, you can't be look'd at, but with the Clouds between. My Lord, I was born with an antipathy to flattery, and I hope, I have ſaid nothing that can be ſo underſtood; I'm ſure I wou'd avoid it if I knew where it look'd like it, but in your
<pb facs="tcp:151495:5"/>
Graces Character, 'twould be hard to ſay too much, and it is the World's unhappineſs not to know you as well as I do.</p>
            <p>I am at a loſs, My Lord, how to acknowledge the Honours I have already receiv'd, and nothing but your Permiſſion cou'd make me ſin again by laying this trifle under your Patronage: but when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the Curioſity your Grace has for Books, and the particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries you made of the Country here mention'd, I thought I had a fair occaſion of putting your Name before this, which I hope will give you ſome ſatisfaction: I wiſh it were in my Power to cover ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better than this Imperfect Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with your Illuſtrious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, but 'tis the Debtor's curſe to be always in Arrears, and I don't know how to offer your Grace any
<pb facs="tcp:151495:6"/>
thing that will not want a bluſh to hide it: But your Grace is often exercis'd in Acts of Clemency, and 'tis but the habit of your Goodneſs to Pardon. The Contemplation of that Vertue gives me unſpeakable pleaſure, therefore with the greater aſſurance I addreſs this Book, and with profound humility remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt Dutiful Servant, <hi>E. LEWIS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:151495:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THis Year will be famous in Chronicle for the Death of the two greatest Monarchs in <hi>Europe,</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> and of one who might have been as great as either, the Duke of <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> whoſe ſhort life has been as much lamented, as that of any young Prince who was ever born with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne: But for the firſt that I Nam'd, one wou'd think he had prevail'd with Nature to allow him a few Months longer than his Natural Leaſe, on purpoſe that he might live to ſee the end of the
<pb facs="tcp:151495:7"/>
Century, and to perform all the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ceremonies of opening the year of <hi>Grace;</hi> that he himſelf might hammer down the Gates of Eternal life, to be ſent up to Heaven on the Wings of a Million <hi>Jubilee</hi> indulgences of his own granting: The good Old Man is now with the Conclave of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſhut up in the limbo of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting darkneſs, and bound up with the reſt of that gang to be try'd at the laſt day, as well as we. The other liv'd till he had loſt all hopes of an Heir, and when he found he cou'd raiſe no poſterity to take his mantle from him, he left it to be ſcrambled for by them that can catch it, juſt in ſuch a diſtracted manner, as a better Man did once before him, that is, to him that beſt deſerves it; and 'tis more than I expect if this late Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of <hi>Spain</hi> has not by his Will laid a Foundation for a War of as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacing
<pb facs="tcp:151495:7"/>
conſequences, as that <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> did, when he bequeath'd the World to him who had the longeſt Sword, and the beſt Army. This Saint of a King is now laid down in the regions of Night, and his Death has left all <hi>Europe</hi> as much in the dark, as he himſelf now lies in the Royal <hi>Pantheon.</hi> The amazement that the World now ſtands in, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he has Nam'd the Duke of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jou</hi> his ſucceſſor, who in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity will be inveſted with that Empire, and for ought I ſee, there's no oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made againſt him.</p>
            <p>I hope our Politicians who are of another Opinion will not be offended with me for ſaying ſo, eſpecially when they ſhall hear that I am, as much as they can be, againſt the Crown of <hi>Spains</hi> falling into the Houſe of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon;</hi> But ſince there's ſo little ſtir among thoſe Powers who are moſt
<pb facs="tcp:151495:8"/>
concern'd againſt it, I can't foreſee what interruption the young King can meet with.</p>
            <p>I wiſh with all my heart the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> wou'd look about 'em before it be too late, before the Scepter is put into his hands, and the Court of <hi>Madrid</hi> ſworn to their allegiance; for when once that is done, and the Duke upon the Throne, taking upon him the Name of the <hi>Catholick King,</hi> and the Adminiſtration of Publick Affairs, and making himſelf eſteem'd by his People, by Acts of bounty and inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating Declarations, it will be a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der matter than we imagine to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs him of it. There is not upon Earth a People more tenacious of what they have once reſolv'd than the <hi>Spaniards</hi> are, nor fonder in all the obſervations of their Duty to their Kings, whether Dead or Alive: And
<pb facs="tcp:151495:8"/>
if they can be perſwaded to think well of the preſent eſtabliſhment, I know their Nature to be ſuch, that they'll ſtand by him to the loſs of all that they are worth: And ſince this Book is ſo far concern'd in the Deſcription of that Country and People, it will be expected that ſomething ſhou'd be ſaid of the preſent poſture of affairs, tho whatever can be ſaid muſt be purely but matter of Opinion, and a blind conjecture of what may, or may not happen.</p>
            <p>And here it falls into our way to inquire whether the greateſt part of the Nobility and Populace of that Kingdom, are pleas'd to have upon their Throne a Son of that Family, that for many Ages has been in Arms againſt 'em, always the rivals of their fame, and the invaders of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces: One wou'd think it ſtrange if they ſhou'd, for ſeveral reaſons; Firſt,
<pb facs="tcp:151495:9"/>
becauſe of that invincible antipathy in their Natures; Secondly, becauſe he comes upon a wrong Foundation, he having renounc'd all right and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; and his breach of that vow de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noting him faithleſs and never to be truſted; not to mention the affront put upon the memory of their great Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>De Haro,</hi> by making ſuch a jeſt of that ſolemn League. Thirdly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in all their Hiſtories they have no Example of a <hi>French</hi> King, who was King of <hi>Spain;</hi> it being the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of their own State, as well as that of their Neighbours, to keep <hi>France</hi> on the outſide of their Fronti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: With many ſuch reaſons as might be produc'd: But to Anſwer <hi>E Contrario;</hi> we know that the <hi>Arch-Duke</hi> was pitcht upon for Succeſſor ſome conſiderable time before the Kings Death, and that the Succeſſion of the Crown was ſo intirely inveſted in
<pb facs="tcp:151495:9"/>
him, that there was no manner of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion made for the <hi>French</hi> Line: Of this ſettlement the Court was well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd, and there was no other intereſt made in Publick, nor any Heir talk'd of but He who was already Nam'd: Thus it continu'd a long time before the King dy'd, and might have done ſo ſtill, but for a zealous hot-headed Church Man, who by being ſo near the Kings Conſcience had opportunities of Cajoling him which way he wou'd.</p>
            <p>This Cardinal being by ſome means or other brought into the <hi>French</hi> faction, whiſpers the King with the injury that wou'd be done to <hi>France,</hi> if the ſucceſſion was given away from her, and that there was no right (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the treaty of Saint <hi>John de Luz</hi>) but what was abſolutely in the Children of that Marriage: The Pious King more afraid of doing a thing that hazarded the Health of his
<pb facs="tcp:151495:10"/>
Soul, than conſenting to a project that might undo all the Countries round him, liſten'd to the Cardinal and gave him hopes of ſucceeding.</p>
            <p>While this was depending at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> meaſures were concerted elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where for the ſafety of the reſt of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> by preventing the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> from falling into any one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, whether that of <hi>Germany</hi> or <hi>France.</hi> The Watchful Guardian of <hi>England,</hi> was at the head of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the States of <hi>Holland</hi> being every way guided by ſo good a Pilot, follow'd him into it; Then having agreed upon terms according to the moſt reaſonable way of ſecuring the Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> they propos'd thoſe terms to <hi>France</hi> and to the <hi>Emperor: France,</hi> doubtful of his ſucceſs at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> conſented to what was offer'd him, and ſeeing no probability of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all, he was glad to be content
<pb facs="tcp:151495:10"/>
with a part: The <hi>Emperor</hi> on the contrary, well aſſur'd of his right, and not doubting but his Son wou'd be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd Succeſſor, refuſed to ingage in that partition, which was the diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of an Empire one day actually to be his; and in this aſſurance he ſtood out to the laſt.</p>
            <p>But now comes the great turn, the unexpected Cataſtrophe of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Policy. The <hi>Cardinal Arch-Biſhop</hi> engages for the <hi>French,</hi> and being of great credit in the Court and with the Credulous King, he forms a Confederacy to help him to turn the ſtream into that Channel; and in the very moment of Death, when the King was given up to contemplations of another Life, and was willing to forget every thing that might bring back his mind to earth again, this <hi>Spiritual tempter</hi> came in with a Will of his own making, and told the King plainly, that he wou'd not ſend him to Heaven, till he had revok'd his
<pb facs="tcp:151495:11"/>
firſt Will, and Sign'd that: The good King now upon the Verge of Life, conſents to any thing, rather than not be abſolv'd; and ſo to releaſe himſelf, he has bound us all to more terrible circumſtances than thoſe he was to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in <hi>Purgatory.</hi> The Will was then ſign'd for the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and when he had done that, the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi> told him he might die when he wou'd; So he ſhut his eyes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
            <p>Now I wou'd fain know what this Gigantick <hi>Will</hi> is that looks ſo big, and Bullies the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> out of her Right and Title: Is there force enough in ſuch a piece of Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to put by the Heir from his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? Can the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Toledo</hi> make a King of <hi>Spain</hi> in defiance of Leagues and Inheritance? by his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he inveſts the King with the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galia,</hi> but what is that to the making of a King? Or is the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> ſo precarious, that the King himſelf
<pb facs="tcp:151495:11"/>
can give it away at his pleaſure to the right or the wrong, as he thinks fit? I don't remember any Hiſtory of a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Monarchy that can produce an Example like it. Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a little before her Death was very much preſt to Name her Heir, not that ſhe cou'd make him an Heir that was not ſo already, but becauſe there were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral pretenders that made their claims, and this was an expedient to prevent animoſities and parties among the People: Accordingly the King of <hi>Scots</hi> was declar'd the immediate Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, who afterwards came in, and all <hi>England</hi> were happy in him. This was another matter: Here was no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading the rights of others, here was no bequeſt made of the Crown, nor a Legacy that cou'd not be countenanc'd by Juſtice and the conſent of all the Laws: The King of <hi>Scotland</hi> was the invincible rightful Heir, and there has not been a Sovereign on the Throne of <hi>England</hi> of a fairer Title, and not
<pb facs="tcp:151495:12"/>
many of ſo fair, ſo that this Example gives this circumſtance no advantage; for tho' this <hi>Will</hi> had been conſidered, made and ſign'd in the time of the King's Health, 'tis beyond all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, that it cou'd do the D. of <hi>Anjou</hi> no Service, when he has no other Title to ſupport him.</p>
            <p>But there has been ſo much ſaid of this by others, that I ſhall mention it no more, and I ſhall ſay as little as I can of any thing that I have read elſewhere, tho' it is hard on ſuch a Subject to eſcape the ſame Arguments which have been uſed before.</p>
            <p>It concerns us now to reflect on the Eſtabliſhment of the Succeſſion, as it ſtands at this time, and to ſee what remedy we have left us to help our ſelves, if there be occaſion: We are all ſenſible it wou'd be a dreadful thing to ſee the Scepters of <hi>F.</hi> and <hi>S.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited into one Hand, and if ſo, why not into one Family? Have the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors of this preſent <hi>French</hi> King
<pb facs="tcp:151495:12"/>
been more faithful in keeping their Leagues than he? I believe not, and I remember formerly to have ſeen a Book, Call'd <hi>An Account of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traventions of France;</hi> that made out, that all the Leagues and Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whaſoever made with <hi>F.</hi> have been to all Intents and Purpoſes broke, when ſhe had opportunities of better<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf; and that it was a Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im there (as all particular Countries have particular Maxims) to make their <hi>Covenants</hi> with ſuch reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to themſelves, as to be at Liberty to evade 'em, when they cou'd get more by ſuch a breach, than the terms of the <hi>League</hi> came to: And if their Anceſtors have been ſo perfidious, why may not their Poſterity? For my part, I expect nothing but univerſal War in <hi>Europe,</hi> even in our Days, to ſet up an <hi>Univerſal Monarchy;</hi> and 'tis plain, we all have reaſon to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it, ſeeing the ballance of power now abſolutely broke; but whatever
<pb facs="tcp:151495:13"/>
becomes of us in the beginning of this Century, 'tis certain there will be moſt fatal Changes before the end of it: Perhaps he who now ſits upon the <hi>French</hi> Throne, may not live to do the World much more miſchief than he has already done, yet he who ſhall ſucceed him, may follow his Example, in his perfidy and contempt of Treaties, and as he ſees opportunity, work by eaſy degrees the intire inheritance of <hi>Spain,</hi> into their own line, never to be interrupted.</p>
            <p>But why may not this alteration be made in our Days? Whoever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders the weakneſs, the Effeminacy and Dejection of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> at this time, will think it no hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. They who have read the Story of the Erection of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire out of the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth, have found, that tho' that was a Republick, ſupported by the braveſt Spirits in the World, Compos'd of a People rigorouſly fond of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,
<pb facs="tcp:151495:13"/>
and had laſted in that form for <hi>6</hi> or <hi>700</hi> Years, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible abhorrence of all Kingly Government; yet 'twas all too little for <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who by one Step after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other brought it out of that form, and rais'd it into a Monarchy, and when he had done that, he made it hereditary to his own Family.</p>
            <p>The Deſign was very great, but nothing was too great for <hi>Caeſar;</hi> he had a powerful Army to back him, and an Exchequer to diſtribute to thoſe he found neceſſary to his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>F.</hi> will have to do with a People already Degenerated to the loweſt pitch of Infamy, and while he has ſo good an Army with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and ſo much Mony to give away within Doors, What may he not do when he ſets about it? And that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nobility will be Corrupted, is no hard matter to make out: Elſe why ſuch Zeal and Obſtinacy for a
<pb facs="tcp:151495:14"/>
Prince ſo far out of the way, as the D. of <hi>Anjou</hi> was? Why ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon the eaſy <hi>King,</hi> as the forcing a Will upon him, which he refus'd to Sign till he was threaten'd with Damnation? Why ſuch impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience for the bringing the Young King to <hi>Madrid?</hi> Why ſuch fulſom Hyperboles as <hi>De los Rios</hi> at <hi>Paris</hi> every Morning Salutes his New Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter with? Why ſuch Largeſſes to be ſcatter'd among the People? Not to mention any more, 'tis apparent that all the meaſures they take tend direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to create a Title, and not demand it: And indeed his Policy in this is very <hi>Machiavilian,</hi> for he knows the Title is a Foundation, upon which it were ridiculous to depend, and therefore what he wants in that, he'll make out in Oſtentation and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes: Then, when the Scepter is ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled as he wou'd have it, and the Genius of <hi>Spain,</hi> made conformable to that of <hi>France,</hi> then 'twill be too late
<pb facs="tcp:151495:14"/>
too look out; then, in good earneſt (as the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Embaſſador ſaid in a Compliment) <hi>The Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranees will be melted down, and the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers between the two Kingdoms utterly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away.</hi> And this carries me to conſider the only Objection of Force which can be admitted; namely, That the D. of <hi>Anjou</hi> will enter into the Cuſtome and Manners of <hi>Spain,</hi> Rule all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by their Politicks, and forget that he was Born a <hi>Bourbon.</hi> But however probable this may ſeem, let us not deceive our ſelves; 'tis a dangerous Trial, and not to be truſted in the Hands of one deſcended from a Race of Kings, notorious for their Apoſtacy from all the bonds of Honour and Alliances.</p>
            <p>'Tis ill Policy to truſt a Pirate with our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, who has ſo often plunder'd us already; or not to make a Metaphor of ſo literal a Truth, it will be a Melancholy Reflection, to think, that all the Commerce of the World ſhall be at the pleaſure of two conſenting Monarchs, the Grand-Father and the Grand-Child.</p>
            <p>Here I ſhall be interrupted—But what harm can that cauſe us, if the D. of <hi>Anjou</hi> ſtands up for an intereſt of his own, and renounces the Ties of Blood to depend enteirly upon himſelf?</p>
            <p>Suppoſe he does ſo, which, for Arguments ſake we'll grant: But when he Dies, and it is again in the power of <hi>France</hi> to give a King to <hi>Spain,</hi> Why may it not be queſtion'd, whether he who then ſits upon the <hi>French</hi> Throne, won't as ſoon make himſelf King of <hi>Spain,</hi> as make the D. of <hi>Berry</hi> ſo,
<pb facs="tcp:151495:15"/>
conſidering the right was firſt in him, or in the Elder Blood? To me it does not at all ſeem un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable: for now it cou'd not be done, becauſe there is a Force in <hi>Europe</hi> to awe him, as long as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> ſtand together: But that ſuch a thing may happen hearafter is more than probable; for by that time there may be changes in other Governments; <hi>England</hi> may want ſuch a King as ſhe now has: <hi>Holland</hi> may want ſuch a <hi>Stateholder</hi> to head her Army, and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> King to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and Dutch powers, and make 'em act together: By theſe means the two Nations, moſt able to keep up the <hi>Ballance,</hi> may come to be divided between them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and who ſhall then oppoſe what violence may be offer'd to make <hi>F.</hi> and <hi>S.</hi> one? Nor is this a triffling Suppoſition. When the Lords and Commons of <hi>Denmark</hi> fell out among 'emſelves about Prerogatives, the King took advantage of their quarrels, and while they were rivalling each other, he ſtept over 'em both, and made himſelf Abſolute, and his Government inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent of 'em, which elſe he never cou'd ha' done. The parallel is good in t'other: For when the two Ballancing Nations come (as they oft have done) to claſh one with another, What Enemies will be able to confine <hi>France? Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> will not then be a Match for her; the <hi>Emperor</hi> has no Naval Force to contend for the Sea: The <hi>Northern</hi> Crowns have little to do with it: <hi>Italy</hi> can do nothing, 'twill be more than ſhe can do to ſave her ſelf, and in
<pb facs="tcp:151495:15"/>
this perplexity, what can be expected but abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute uncontroulable Dominion, not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd? And let not the diſtance of theſe Events make us negligent now; they may be certain, tho' they are remote; and the Children of the next Generation may have reaſon to Curſe us for ſuffering a <hi>Prince,</hi> whom we had ſo much Reaſon to miſtruſt, to get into his Hands and the Management of a <hi>Crown</hi> that ought never to be annext to that of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To what extremity was <hi>Europe</hi> reduc'd by <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th. till <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt ſtopt him! 'Twas well there was a <hi>Prince</hi> then in being, who had Strength and Courage to check his great Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, and to keep down his ſwelling Empire from ſuch a prodigious impoſtumation. Till then he had met with nothing that oppos'd him, or he Conquer'd all that did: And 'tis paſt diſpute, that he wou'd ha' made himſelf univerſal Emperor, if he had not been interrupted by this Rival King: There he found his good Fortune to fail him; there the God of War, that had given him ſo many Victories, held up the Standard of his Enemy, againſt him, and overthrew that Favourites he had ſo long eſpous'd; ſo that, from that time; to his abdication of the <hi>Imper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ial</hi> Diadem, he found every thing go backward with him; and leſt he ſhou'd live to ſee himſelf ſtript of all that he had got, he withdrew from the World, before the glory of his Arms was quite departed from him, and in a humour, left the Empire to his Son, who loſt it faſt enough.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:151495:16"/>But if we turn to the compariſon upon <hi>France,</hi> the Event will not be the ſame: for if <hi>France</hi> be ſo formidable of her ſelf, what will ſhe be, when the Sea Ports of the Bay of <hi>Biſcay,</hi> the <hi>Atlantick,</hi> and the <hi>Mediterranean;</hi> when the Mines of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> and the richeſt Iſlands of the World, ſhall be added to her? Nor can the <hi>Emperor</hi> do much to hinder him. The <hi>Turk</hi> is ready to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him, whenever <hi>France</hi> has a mind to put 'em by the Ears; <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in Emulations of their own; and if theſe ſhall not be at leiſure to oppoſe him, where is that Power in <hi>Europe,</hi> that can Face him in the Field, much leſs upon the Ocean? I hope this needs no proving; every one can Propheſy the Miſery of ſuch a Reign, if ever it comes to paſs. Nor can it be ſuppos'd, that when a King of <hi>France</hi> is got to ſuch a height of Power, he will deſcend from it, as <hi>Charles</hi> did; for as long as the Poſterity of this Houſe will be in being (and that may be to the end of the World, for they are a numerous Iſſue) ther's too much Ambition in their Natures to give away their Lawrel while they are able to to keep it.</p>
            <p>But perhaps this may never happen; perhaps, as we ſaid before, the D. of <hi>Anjou</hi> will prove more a <hi>Spaniard</hi> than a <hi>French Man:</hi> Well, be it ſo; I wiſh it may: But will not the King, whether it be his <hi>Grand Father,</hi> or his <hi>Father,</hi> reſent ſuch a Defection? Moſt certainly they will, and if in his New Government he acts any
<pb facs="tcp:151495:16"/>
thing in contrariety to the intereſt of that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was Born, How eaſy will it be to ſet up the Elder Brother againſt him, eſpecialy ſince Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciations go for nothing, and ſo take him down from that precarious Throne, which he holds but by their Favour.</p>
            <p>Or on the other hand, ſuppoſe the D. becomes a good <hi>Spaniard.</hi> The time may come when He or his Heirs may have a right to the Succeſſion of <hi>France:</hi> Can it then be thought, that he who is in poſſeſſion of ſo wealthy, ſo vaſt an Empire, will ſurrender it to another, becauſe the <hi>Will</hi> has ſo ordain'd it? 'Tis abſurd to think it; and he'll be ſo far from quitting ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious So'vrain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themſelves will help him to recover his Right, and be proud of the occaſion of aggrandizing themſelves, by having the reputation of giving their <hi>Monarch</hi> another Empire.</p>
            <p>This Article muſt be eaſyly granted, for the D. has left a Declaration behind him to ſecure his turn in the Succeſſion of <hi>France,</hi> as one of his Anceſtors did before him, who was made King of <hi>Poland:</hi> The Story is eminent in the <hi>French</hi> Chronicle, which ſaies, That when <hi>Henry</hi> the Third was elected King of <hi>Poland,</hi> he left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him a Specification of his Title; and when the Crown devolved upon him, he ſtole out of <hi>Poland,</hi> and came to <hi>France</hi> to claim it, which was allowed him, and he was thereupon King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:151495:17"/>Be how it will, as near as we can gueſs at the uncertain dependances of futurity, the reſult of this preſent Eſtabliſhment, muſt be unhappy one time or other: And by how much the longer the D. of <hi>A.</hi> is in poſſeſſion, ſo much the greater will be, either his Power, or the Power of <hi>France,</hi> according as he acts, either for his <hi>own,</hi> or the intereſt of the other.</p>
            <p>What then is to be done? There the wiſeſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians are at a loſs: Our cautious King fell upon the only Method to prevent the Calamities we are to dread: And he had ſo far Eſtabliſht t, that if he had to do with a Man of any Faith or Honour, we had been ſecure by thoſe Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures he had form'd. But as the King of <hi>France</hi> has broke thro' all ties of Treaties and Leagues, there is nothing hereafter to be truſted to his Word, and <hi>that</hi> being forfeited, we muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be always in Arms to watch him.</p>
            <p>I wou'd be far from adviſing the People of <hi>England</hi> to a War, who are but lately come out of one, which coſt 'em ſo much: But ſurely there is ſomething to be conſider'd for our own ſecurity, if <hi>France</hi> be now intriguing for an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the two <hi>Crowns.</hi> I muſt confeſs, 'tis more the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi>'s buſineſs than ours to call him to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, for he is poſitively affronted by having the <hi>Arch Duke</hi> Poſt pon'd of his Right; but let it be his never ſo much, 'tis ours ſo far as to oppoſe the conjunction of <hi>F.</hi> and <hi>S.</hi> with all our Vigour; that's undeniable.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:151495:17"/>But beſides that, What can the <hi>Emperor</hi> do of himſelf? His Country is ſo unhappily ſcituated, that nothing can be like it: For <hi>Spain</hi> is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great way from him, but <hi>France</hi> interpoſes ſo directly between 'em, that it is impoſſible to come at any part of <hi>Spain,</hi> but thro <hi>F.</hi> And one wou'd think, that as Nature has contriv'd the <hi>Pyrenees</hi> to keep <hi>Spain</hi> out of the power of <hi>France,</hi> ſo ſhe had, giv'n to the <hi>French</hi> the power of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out every Body elſe: By this unfortunate ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, it will be hard for the <hi>Emperor</hi> to do much in <hi>Spain,</hi> or, indeed in <hi>Italy,,</hi> unleſs he can out-bid the K. of <hi>F.</hi> for marching of his Men thro' the <hi>Griſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to make amends for this Miſfortune, the <hi>Emperor</hi> has an Army not inferior to that of <hi>France;</hi> ſome of his Veteranes being the beſt and eldeſt ſtanding Force in <hi>Europe;</hi> and if he had Ships to Tranſport 'em thro' our Channel, and a good Fleet to ſecond him, he might bid fair for the Bay of <hi>Biſcay,</hi> and the <hi>Straits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this will be practicable at no time, but at this very juncture: For if the Young <hi>King,</hi> who is going to his Throne, has leiſure to ingratiate himſelf with his People, and to buy up the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence and Hearts of the <hi>Nobility;</hi> his <hi>Grand-Father,</hi> who has been uſed to that ſort of Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick, can put him in away how to do it, and help him to Mony into the bargin. To prevent this, it ought to be the conſideration of all <hi>Europe,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Emperors</hi> Duty, and the <hi>Princes</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:151495:18"/>
               <hi>Italy,</hi> and next Ours, and <hi>Hollands</hi> to look about us.</p>
            <p>That there ſhou'd be always a ſtrong Fleet at Sea, every way ſuperior to the <hi>French,</hi> is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary; and that to be under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Renowned <hi>Orford,</hi> ſo ſucceſsful in our own Channel, and ſo belov'd in <hi>Spain:</hi> If this be not done, and by ſuch a neglect, we give <hi>France</hi> the opportunity of Triumphing every where over us, How diſmal will it be, to have theſe things iſſue in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of theſe two <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies</hi> and to ſo forma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble a Power as <hi>France</hi> already has; to ſee a Dominion of Thirty Eight Thouſand Miles in circumference in all parts of the Globe Allied, if not added to it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151495:18"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF SPAIN, In ſeveral Letters.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>LETTER I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Dear <hi>Brunet.</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NOthing cou'd give me greater ſatisfaction than the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands you honour'd me with at parting: My own curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity agrees ſo well with yours, that I find double pleaſure in obeying you; for while I am contriving to gratifie your Deſires, I am indulging my own. And when I write to the generous <hi>Brunet,</hi> I do't with the greater complacency in my ſelf, becauſe I know I am to ſtand before a Judge, who will not too ſeverely cenſure my imperfections: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main indebted to your Clemency, for ſeveral favours which are yet unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd; and I conſider that I am running into a new Score before the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151495:19"/>
old be paid off, like a Bankrupt who has nothing to afford for his Diſabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but Thanks and Gratitude: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I'll venture a little further on your good Nature, and with the ſame aſſurance that I rely'd upon't in our former Correſpondences, I begin my Narration.</p>
               <p>When I left St. <hi>Maloes,</hi> I embark't on a Daniſh Ship that was bound for <hi>England:</hi> The Port where we Anchor'd was the ſame where the Royal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mado of that Country then Rode. It fell out very opportunely for my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, that I ſhould come there at that juncture; for the Day after our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, there was an order for all the Squadrons to Sail, and immediately the Signal was made by halling home the foretop-Sail Sheets. As ſoon as I came a ſhore I ſhifted my Cloaths, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving furniſhed my ſelf with the habit which their Sailors wore, I chang'd the form of my dreſs, and disguis'd my ſelf as like one of them as I cou'd: You may remember that I had been Maſter of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue a great while, for I had formerly been in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> where I reſided four Years, and had in that time acquir'd ſo much of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151495:19"/>
it, that I cou'd expreſs my ſelf per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly in whatever I had occaſion to ſay: This was of great uſe to me af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards; and even at firſt I might have met with ſome difficulty if I had given them any jealouſy of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo lately out of <hi>France,</hi> by being deſtitute of it. But I was now provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt all ſuſpicion; for feigning my ſelf a <hi>Hugonot,</hi> (which is a ſufficient paſs for a <hi>French</hi> Man among theſe credulous People) I got admittance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to company of ſome of the Seamen; and having eaſily perſuaded them, that I had been a ſufferer for my Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and that I fled from the rage of the Perſecution, they become fond of me to ſuch a degree that it had almoſt prov'd a quarrel among the ſeveral Competitors who courted me to ſhip my ſelf among them, which of them ſhould enjoy my company. Theſe ſort of People are ſtubborn and quarrelſome, apt for all manner of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, turbulent and hard to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du'd, and highly jealous of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted Honour, for they have a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſomething which they take to to be a point of Honour, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to no more than this, That
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151495:20"/>
every one thinks himſelf a better Man than his fellow. The diſpute which they had about me was of this kind, every Man courted me to himſelf, and each oppos'd the other.</p>
               <p>I who was not yet well enough ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the nature of theſe fierce Iſlanders, was at a loſs how to behave my ſelf among them on this nice occaſion: I ſaw plainly if I ſhou'd determine in favour, or in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of any of their Perſons, by ſeeming to prefer one to another, Civil Wars wou'd have enſu'd. But after ſome conſideration, I believ'd the only way wou'd be to let them know that I had already reſolv'd how to diſpoſe of my ſelf, to give them every one thanks for their kindneſs, and to unite all their differences by concluding in favour of none of them, but to aſſure them, that I had long ago intended to ſhip my ſelf upon the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral (of which I had heard great Fame) and was then come to enter my ſelf Aboard. The Speech which I made to to this purpoſe had like to have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done me; for I forgot to change my ſtile, and they began to find out that I did not talk like a Sailor. This
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151495:20"/>
bred a Mutiny, and I was going to have a Council of War call'd upon me, when an Officer paſſing our Room, heard the noiſe and came in, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the cauſe of this uproar, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſtood up and wou'd under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to tell him the Adventure; then from one end of the Room to to'ther there was ſuch a general din, that I verily thought I had been in one of <hi>Quevedo</hi>'s Viſions, and that I ſaw the Devils going again to macerate the poor damn'd Traitor <hi>Judas.</hi> The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Officer put at laſt an end to their Fury, and away they march't.</p>
               <p>This Gentleman was a Lieutenant, of the very Ship I look't for, who inquiring whence and what I was, I gave him the ſame account I had done to my Companions, only adding, that I had formerly liv'd in a better Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, but was now reduc'd to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of great neceſſity; and having ſome inſight into Navigation, I cou'd not diſpoſe of my ſelf better than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſervice of a Prince, who had fill'd all the World with the Fame of his Arms.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151495:21"/>The Gentleman might perceive by the manner in which I ſpoke, that I had not always been ſo wretched as I now ſeem'd to be, for I did it on purpoſe to prevail with him for good quarter, and he very civilly aſſur'd me, he wou'd diſtinguiſh me from the reſt of the Crew. Then he took me with him, and appointed me conveniences better than I cou'd in reaſon expect.</p>
               <p>One might think, that he who had ſeen the lofty Navy of <hi>France,</hi> could not be much tranſported with what he ſaw in any other Country; But I can't forbear acquainting my Dear Friend with what amazement I beheld this glorious Show. Never was the Boſom of the Sea inſulted by ſuch a Fleet, never was ſo Magnificent a Pomp. Oh <hi>Brunet!</hi> 'Tis inconceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and above deſcription: Let it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that all the Kingdoms of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe come infinitely ſhort of <hi>England</hi> for the Strength, Number and Beauty of their Shipping. 'Tis true, our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent glorious Monarch has done won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that way, but truſt me Friend, 'tis all but Pageantry to this.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151495:21"/>Soon after my Embarkment, I gave my ſelf up to conſider of every thing I ſaw round me: To ſpeak of all that pleas'd me, wou'd run me into ſuch confuſion, that I ſhou'd not clear my ſelf a great while. I beheld every where matter of ſufficient contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but that which ſtruck me with moſt wonder, was the ſuprizing <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tania,</hi> the Ship wherein I entred my ſelf, and the Capital of the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy. To deſcribe this noble Structure, wou'd be a Task of immenſe difficulty; In all the fabrications I had ſeen, I never met with any thing came near her. I know what Opinion you at home have of your own Power, but be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd from one who was well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Naval Force of <hi>France,</hi> That ſhe bears no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this, neither in Number, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, Ornament, nor Diſcipline, tho' I confeſs, it may be ſaid with ſome juſtice, That the <hi>Riſing Sun</hi> (which was once the glory of the Gallick Fleet) had many excellencies to make Her remarkable; but when She ſtands in compariſon with the <hi>Bratannia,</hi> it may be ſaid the Kite is compar'd to the Eagle: Not that I want Ceremony for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151495:22"/>
my own Country; but that my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion in this, and every other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular may be impartial, I ſhall all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long ſpeak my mind as if I had no intereſt in the one ſide or the other.</p>
               <p>The Signal for Sailing being made, one might behold in this Ship a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Hands at work in an inſtant; ſuch a multitude loaded her Decks, that her ſtrong Floors groan'd with the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing Weight, and ſeem'd to bend beneath it: There appeared in every Face ſuch an alacrity, and in their Hands ſuch readineſs, that I cou'd not chuſe but be delighted with it.</p>
               <p>Our Anchors being up, we made Sail, ſtretching over to the Coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> and ſtanding towards <hi>Breſt.</hi> Here it was that I began to feel ſome reluctance for what I had undertaken, for I found there was a deſign of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting ſomething againſt that Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and it griev'd me to the Soul, that I ſhou'd be conſtrain'd to take up arms againſt my native Country. I had not been long in this apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ere I perceiv'd the Squadrons to part ſeveral ways: That wherein I was, and two more ſtood back again to Sea, and the remainder ſtay'd behind
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151495:22"/>
and ply'd upon the Coaſt. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd me from my Fears of Fighting againſt my Country, but I was not a little mortify'd, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhou'd thus Lord it in the Channel, and drive us under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of our Harbours. It was now rumour'd that their Deſign was againſt <hi>Breſt,</hi> both by the Courſe they Steer'd, and by the great preparation which was made for a Deſcent; They on the other Side had early Intelligence of the Deſign, and were ſo well prepar'd to receive 'em, that when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, expecting little or no Oppoſition, they ſoon ſaw their fatal Miſtake, and that they had now beſides all the Caſtles and Forts, a huge Army to Encounter. This was the moſt deplorable Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe that ever the <hi>Engliſh</hi> undertook, and it was almoſt a pity to ſee ſo many miſerable Souls run headlong to their Deſtruction, which they themſelves now eaſily ſaw, but had not power to avoid. This memorable Exploit is known by the Name of <hi>Cameret-Bay-Fight,</hi> and will be Famous to all Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the bloody Execution, and for the Death of the moſt Renowned Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Talmaſh,</hi> who was one of the firſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151495:23"/>
who fell. Our Squadrons, which now made up a Fleet of about 40 <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and 20 <hi>Dutch,</hi> beſides ſmall Frigats not in the Line of Battel, Fireſhips, Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Tenders, chang'd their Courſe as ſoon as they were out of Sight, and ſtood out for the Main, and we all jump'd right in our Opinions that we were going to the Straits.</p>
               <p>At this time our <hi>Toulon</hi> Fleet had been Bombarding the Coaſts of <hi>Spain</hi> in the <hi>Meditteranean. Malaga</hi> and <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant</hi> and ſome other Places had already felt the fury of their Bombs, and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celona</hi> was to be the laſt Scene of their Hoſtility; and by the way I can't chuſe but admire the wonderful Intelligence our Maſter keeps in theſe Foreign Courts; for he had long known of this intended Voyage, and not caring to hazard his weaker Fleet againſt the beſt of his Enemies, he ſent Orders to his Admiral before <hi>Barcelona</hi> to diſlodge. And what is very remarkable, the <hi>French</hi> withdrew from thence the very ſame Day the <hi>Engliſh</hi> hoiſt'd Sail in the Channel: 'Twas a Maſterpiece of Care ſo ſoon to foreſee this Storm, and to prevent it; for had they ſurpriz'd them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151495:23"/>
at Sea, the Conſequences might have been fatal.</p>
               <p>Our Voyage (I ſpeak of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi>) went proſperouſly on, without encountring any extraordinary Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Some Prizes the Cruiſers brought in, but I think our Country-men made ſufficient Reprizals on 'em in all parts of the World. In twenty Days, or thereabouts, we came within ſight of <hi>Cales,</hi> and there another Squadron, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by a Rear-Admiral, join'd us: This laſt Squadron was the remainder of that commanded by Sir <hi>Francis Whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> who was Drown'd at the back of <hi>Gibralter,</hi> by that terrible <hi>Levant</hi> which caſt away His and Thirteen other Ships, and daſht 'em into Pieces: This Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was of great Reputation for his Skill and Courage; but I don't know what can be ſaid for the Firſt, after ſo notorious a Miſtake as he made of the Land; for at the cloſe of the Evening he perfectly ſaw the Shoar, but he mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtook his Marks, and thought he had been to Leeward of the Hill, when he was to Windward; and that coſt him his Life, and the loſs of many good Ships, both Men of War and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:151495:24"/>We were now 70 Men of War in the Line of Battle compleat, beſides innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable other Veſſels of inferior Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which made in all a glorious Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> were alarm'd at this ſtupendious Navy, becauſe they had never, in their Opinions, ſeen any thing much better than their own.</p>
               <p>We had not been long cruiſing off the Iſland, e're the <hi>Spaniards</hi> got ready what little force they had, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in all but of Ten Ships of War and Two Fire Ships: With theſe they joyn'd us, and a great many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements we receiv'd from their Guns, which our General Anſwer'd.</p>
               <p>Of theſe Ten there were but Three or Four that were fit for Company, the reſt were ſuch Hoſpitals that they were a ſcandal to the Navy: And though they had been Five Years in fitting out theſe, and boaſted to the World what a power they would bring; yet after Six days ſail, moſt of 'em were diſabled, and they could hardly crawl under their Crutches up to <hi>Barcelona:</hi> However, at their Return, they fail'd not to give out, that it was for fear of them that the <hi>French</hi> ran away,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151495:24"/>
and the ignorant People, who have a high Conceit of their own power, believ'd all that was ſaid. 'Tis a ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Story to tell, how they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted with this Summers Expedition, they verily thought the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy of <hi>France</hi> was not able to Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Ten Ships; and though they came home Cripl'd and Maim'd, becauſe indeed they went out ſo, yet nothing could undeceive 'em, but that it was the bare appearance of their Ten Ships that ſet the Enemy a running, and ſcour'd the Sea. When we came up to <hi>Barcelona,</hi> we found the Rode clear, and no Marks of an Enemy but what they left with their Mortars. We Anchor'd, and it was ſome ſatisfaction to us to ſee that we were now in a part of <hi>Spain,</hi> that cou'd acknowledge the benefit they receiv'd by us, and that we were welcom'd a-ſhore as the Friends and Protectors of <hi>Catalonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There being nothing to be done here, we ſtay'd a-while to water and divert our ſelves, and then prepar'd for our Return; and by the way we put in at <hi>Alicant,</hi> to ſee what deva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation the <hi>French</hi> had made, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps every one but I was mortify'd
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151495:25"/>
at the ſight. <hi>Malaga</hi> fared not much better; but becauſe I intend not this as a Journal, I ſhall make haſte to <hi>Cales,</hi> which was appointed for our Winter Quarters, and ſay nothing of <hi>Barcelona,</hi> and the other places we touch'd at, till next Voyage.</p>
               <p>After ſome time of Abode and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> grew more familiar: Our General and the Governor had interviews of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and every thing tended to a good Underſtanding. Our Ships were laid up, and every man began to be idle.</p>
               <p>In this Interval of Eaſe, when all the world was at quiet, and War ſet aſide till the Return of the Spring, pleaſure was all the ſtudy of the Fleet: Every Captain had now his Houſe and his Miſtreſs a-ſhore, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Seaman Surfeited with good Wine and freſh Proviſion, and his ſhort Allowance-money bought him a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Whore and a Clap: Above all, our Noble General liv'd in great Royalty at his Houſe, which a Don beſtow'd on him for his uſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, as long as he ſtay'd: He kept a plentiful Table, and began al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to amaze the thrifty <hi>Spaniards</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151495:25"/>
with that Exceſs and Profuſion which every day appear'd on the board. But when the Fourth of <hi>November</hi> was drawing near, which is the Birth-day of the King of <hi>England,</hi> there was ſuch an Entertainment talkt of, as hardly was outdone by any of the Gluttonous Emperors, who are Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicled for their Luxury. I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſo much on your inclination as to be a little particular in this deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for it made ſo great a noiſe all over the World, that you muſt needs hear on't, but perhaps not know any thing of it, but as you had it in groſs.</p>
               <p>On this great Holiday the General intended to Entertain all the <hi>Engliſh, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Officers with a Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and a Bowl of Punch, to Celebrate the Birth of his Maſter, and to keep up that Amity that was between them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: It was already rumour'd as an extraordinary thing; and believing there might be ſomething in't worth my Curioſity, I crowded in to ſee it, and I can aſſure you I was ſo ſtrict an obſerver of all that paſt, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing eſcap'd me, nor ſhall I relate any
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151495:26"/>
thing but what I really ſaw with my own Eyes.</p>
               <p>The Feaſt was in every reſpect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what I cou'd imagine; and if I had not been a Witneſs to every ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar tranſaction, you might perhaps doubt the truth of what I am going to tell you.</p>
               <p>There were Four Tables ſpread in all: At the Firſt ſate the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> General, and Vice-Admiral: The <hi>Dutch</hi> Admirals, and Two or Three men of Quality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; At another Table in the ſame Room ſate all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants of the Neighbouring Towns; At the Third which was without, were all the chief <hi>Engliſh</hi> Officers to the number of a Hundred or thereabouts, and in the adjoyning Room the inferior Officers. I never beheld greater plenty at any Feaſt I had ſeen at <hi>Paris,</hi> nor ſent in better order: There was ſuch variety of every thing that was in ſeaſon, that one might have ſaid, the Lakes had been drain'd of their Fiſh, the Air had been ſtript of its Fowls, and the Fields of their Cattel; That the Vines had been unloaded for Wine, and all the Gardens in the Province plunder'd for Fruit: The vaineſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151495:26"/>
cou'd hardly ha' nam'd that thing that was wanting; and in ſhort, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw a more beautiful Confuſion: Every Element had ſome ſhare in't, and I can ſay nothing greater of it, than that it was a Banquet fit for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Giver, and the auguſt Occaſion it Commemorated. When Dinner was over, the General roſe, and all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany after him, and the Scene was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd to the Garden. When they came there, they found the Punch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p>I don't know whether <hi>Brunet</hi> is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this ſort of Liquor, but he may gueſs, when he has heard what the Ingredients are, what an unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latable Drink it muſt be. That which they call'd the Bowl, was a large Fountain in the centre of the Garden, ſhaded with Lemmon Trees, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Four principal Walks that terminated at the end of the Garden; Now you'll ſay this ſeems a little Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick, but I do aſſure you I ſhall write nothing but what was literally true, at leaſt as well as I can remember. There were in this Fountain-Bowl firſt of all a Dozen <hi>Engliſh</hi> Barrels of Water, amounting to 432 Gallons: Of Brandy
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151495:27"/>
there was 188 Gallons: Of Sugar 400 weight, of Lemmons, which the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den it ſelf afforded, about Six Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand: A Pound of Nutmegs, and there was order'd a 100 weight of Biskets, but there was none put in. Thus this Giant-bowl was compounded, and they who were Criticks in this Sort of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, ſaid they never drunk better in their Lives; for the General had taken great Care to have it well made, and for that end had nam'd three Captains, whom he ſtil'd the Commiſſioners of the Punch, to ſee it duly prepar'd: The Fountain was brim full, and for the Merriment of the Frolick, there was a ſmall Boat built on purpoſe to float about this Lake of Sulphur, with Oars and a Boy to Row, and to Skink to the Company in Silver Pints that lay thick about the brim of the Fountain: Now the Healths went plentifully round; The Princes of the Confederacy were firſt huzzaed in Pint Brimmers, as the Emperor, Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Britain,</hi> then the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> and laſt of all the Generals with an univerſal Huz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za, which echoed to the Skies. This fearful Noiſe put me in Mind of the Ottoman way of Warring, for when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151495:27"/>
they begin the Charge, every one Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows as loud as ever he can, and tears his Throat for the ſhrilleſt Voice, and then with a general Shout they fall to: Juſt ſo 'twas here; The Punch was the Enemy they were to ingage, they fell to Work with a moſt outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Dinn, and their Ingagement had ſo much of a real Battle in't, that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral were Kill'd and Wounded in the Aſſault. Round the Bowl were ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Tables ſpread with Hams, Tongues, Pickles, and all ſorts of dry'd Meats in great variety; and behind 'em, in the Walks, were Conſorts of Muſick, ſo far from one another that they were juſt heard, and diſtinguiſh'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Confuſion. Now tell me (my Friend) was ever any thing more Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent? Was ever any thing more Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick?</p>
               <p>This Noble Company (tho' moſt of 'em had more than they cou'd carry off) ſunk not the Bowl above an Inch, but when they withdrew to let in the Sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors to't, there was ſuch a Torrent of theſe Drunken Rogues, that in half an Hours time there was not one Drop left, for with their Hats and Buckets they lav'd it as dry, as an honeſt Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151495:28"/>
does his Glaſs when he Drinks to a Supernaculum; and well the Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons might, for they were now thirſty after having fed upon a whole Ox that was roaſted for 'em, which they cut off the Spit, and ſwallow'd down burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hot: So ended this ſumptuous Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</p>
               <p>The Winter being our long Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I had nothing elſe to do but to make my remarks of the Diſpoſition of the People I was ingaged with. 'Twere a needleſs Trouble to tell the well Read <hi>Brunet</hi> what a Temper the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are of, the Neighbourhood of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries has always afforded great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with 'em, and there is hardly a <hi>French</hi> Man of any Curioſity, but is perfectly acquainted with their Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. As for the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> there is ſuch an Antipathy between us and them, that we ſeldom ſpeak well of 'em, but tho' I were diveſted of all my Country prejudices, yet I cou'd hardly ſay any thing to their Advantage, and to tell thee the Truth, I hate 'em hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily: But the preſent bent of my Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation lying another way, I ſhan't ſpend my Time in giving Characters, but conſidering that <hi>Brunet</hi> is at this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151495:28"/>
time a Lover, I wou'd fain entertain him with ſome amorous Adventure that's more ſuitable to his Genius: This idle Time furniſh'd us with variety of Intrigues, but as I am no good Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an at ſuch Novelties, ſo I wou'd not render your Time heavy t'ye by relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'em in my own Stile, but I'll make you amends with a Manuſcript, which with much difficulty I purchaſt of a Traveller who was concern'd in the Ship which was the Scene of the Amour, and which I have tranſcrib'd and ſent inclos'd: But I ſend it t'ye with ſuch Caution, that I wou'd have you value the Gift, as you wou'd a fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Treaſure, which (they ſay) is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to reveal. The Author has ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd his Lovers with imaginary Names, to darken a little ſo late an Adventure, becauſe the Matter of Fact is true, and of ſo great Importance. The Story runs thus.</p>
               <div type="story">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:151495:29"/>
                  <head>THE STORY.</head>
                  <p>THE Monarchy of <hi>Philippia</hi> had been long govern'd by a Race of warlike Kings, no Chronicle can produce a Series of greater Heroes, nor Actions more aſtoniſhing than what we find in the Hiſtories of that Empire: For from the firſt Prince <hi>Pelagius,</hi> who for his great Exploits againſt the firſt barbarous Invaders was choſen King, down to the preſent Soveraign <hi>Catolinus,</hi> there was hardly one who inlarg'd not the Bounds of his Soveraignty, and planted not his Arms in ſome far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Region. A Thouſand Ages they were reputed the firſt Monarchs of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and their ſpacious Dominions reach'd from one end of the Globe to the other.</p>
                  <p>In this Poſture ſtood the Kingdom, when from an Infant <hi>Catolinus</hi> was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151495:29"/>
King: Never was a People in greater Expectation than of this young Hero: They lookt in him for all the gallant Accompliſhments of his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and the Eyes of all the World were bent on him as the Succeſſor of ſuch an illuſtrious Progeny, and as a Prince of wondrous Promiſes. There wanted nothing to render his Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on compleat, Maſters of all Sciences were brought from the Academies to give him Diſcipline; the Sun ſhin'd with a double Force upon him, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing conſpir'd to animate him with all the Vigour that his Years cou'd bear: The Subjects which he was to Rule, were a People who had been very Famous in the Ages that are paſt, for their Courage and Succeſſes; but of later Years, ſince Religion has uſurp'd ſo much over the Temporal Power, and effeminated their Spirits, they have been inſlav'd to the Church, and chang'd beyond all belief from what they were. Yet in the midſt of this depravity they ſtill retain'd ſome Notions of Honour, and were now in Hopes of a King that ſhou'd reſtore 'em to their Courage and their Glory: His firſt Minority gave 'em all the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151495:30"/>
Incouragement they cou'd wiſh for, and they hoped to find him one Day ſuch as they had form'd him in their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and for many Years he bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom'd ſo beautifully, that they doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not but he would prove the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer's Bleſſing. Thus every thing flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht, and there ſeemed no want, but of a Maturity of Years to ripen the young Monarch, and to make 'em a happy People: But now behold what a turn, what a fatal Diſappointment of their exalted Hopes!</p>
                  <p>The Inhabitants of <hi>Philippia,</hi> are (as was ſaid) ridiculous Bigots to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: The Patriarch of all the Eaſtern Churches has not throughout the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his Jurisdiction, a People more devoted to his Intereſt, nor more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Defenders of his Uſurpation: This is the Reaſon that this Country ſwarms with an ignorant and ſuperſtitious Clergy, Zealous of the Intereſt of the Church, and abſolute in their Power: The Laity ſtands in profound Awe of their Frowns, and when any Affair of Importance is to be controverted, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there may be a Party made for the advantage of the Church, they ride up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151495:30"/>
the humility of the People, and get all things into their Government.</p>
                  <p>'Twas thus with this infatuated Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the tender <hi>Catolinus</hi> arriv'd to Years that made him fit for their Management, and the Patriarch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what benefit it wou'd be to him if this Young King was betimes made his Creature, prevail'd by his inſinuating Miniſters that he might be put into the hands of the Eccleſiaſticks, and Educated with a fond Affection to the Church, and a prejudice to all Secular Affairs. They proſpered ſo well in their deſign, that even in his Pupillage he became a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Lover of his Religion, and ſeem'd already to be wrapt up in it to ſuch a degree, that he took no notice of thoſe Exerciſes which were fitter for his Youth, but gave himſelf wholly up to Amuſement and Meditation. This unmanly weakneſs was the cauſe that afterwards he cou'd reliſh nothing of the Duty of ſo great a Monarch; but having neglected to accompliſh himſelf as a Prince, inſtead of becoming a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier as his Anceſtors had been, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated into a ſtupidity of Godlineſs, and Reign'd more like a Prieſt than a King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151495:31"/>'Twas a melancholy Reflection to ſee ſuch a military People now dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht into the moſt ſordid ſlothful Wretches that ever liv'd: Arms were now forgot, their ruſty Swords lay idle, their Garriſons were unregarded, and their neglected Shipping, which for many Ages had been the wonder of all their Neighbours, now became their diſgrace. The King's Example cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted all the Youth, he became a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to the Church, and they became Bigots to him, not that they cou'd commend his Genius, but it indulg'd their idleneſs, and unmann'd their Souls: Never was ſo hideous a ſight of Corruption and Apoſtacy, their Friends pity'd 'em, their Enemies derided 'em, and the diſtant parts of the World could hardly believe it. Near Thirty years he held the Scepter without doing any Action fit for ſo ſublime a Monarch, he ſaw himſelf invaded on all ſides, whole Provinces were ſnatch'd from his Crown; and he who had no diſpoſition for War, ſaw all with little or no oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſate down at laſt contented with the loſs. At length his miſerable Subjects became ſenſible of their Shame; and as they found it too late to hope
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151495:31"/>
for redreſs from the preſent King, they concerted means to furniſh the Kingdom with an Heir who might in time redeem their proſtituted Honour, and awake 'em from their inglorious Lethargy. In order to this, it was adviſed that the King ſhou'd marry, his Councellors lookt around the World for a Lady fit for ſo high a Dignity; and at laſt, they caſt their Eyes on a Daughter to one of the Chief Princes that Compoſe the great Body of the Firſt Empire of <hi>Aſia,</hi> the Celebrated beautiful <hi>Nuberia</hi> now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the tutelar Goddeſs of this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Empire.</p>
                  <p>This charming Princeſs was the Idol of the Country where ſhe liv'd, a Lady of ſuch excelling Beauty, and ſuch uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon accompliſhments of mind, that 'tis hard to ſay, whether her Virtue or her Beauty was moſt admirable: Fame had long ago filled the Univerſe with the Acclamation of her Perfections, and Princes from the remoteſt parts of the Earth languiſh'd for her. Every ſighing Lover, when he wou'd ſay any thing extraordinary of his Divine Miſtreſs, cou'd ſay nothing finer of her, than by comparing her to the Princeſs <hi>Nuberia;</hi> for in that all the glory of the Sex was
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151495:32"/>
determin'd, and there cou'd be nothing more ſaid than what they copy'd from her. Soon as they had concluded on this illuſtrious Lady, Embaſſadors were ſent to her Father's Court to treat of a Marriage. But tho' the incurious <hi>Cato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> had given his conſent to this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy; yet he found in himſelf but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle inclination to the Alliance, having intoxicated his Brain with other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and made himſelf utterly inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Gallantry, or the ſofter Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Love: The Embaſſadors being diſpatcht, came in few days to the Court where ſhe reſided; The grateful <hi>Arſaces</hi> her Father read their Meſſage with great Acknowledgments of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and though he had already matcht his other Daughters to the beſt Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies in <hi>Aſia;</hi> yet he eſteem'd this the greateſt honour he had receiv'd, and no wonder then he ſhow'd his readineſs to conſent to the propoſal.</p>
                  <p>The diſconſolate <hi>Nuberia</hi> had quite another opinion of this Match; ſhe had heard no advantageous Character of <hi>Catolinus;</hi> and the firſt emotions ſhe felt at the propoſal, were reſentment and reluctancy. But 'twas in vain to contend with her Father's Authority;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151495:32"/>
Ambition was his God, tho' Love was hers: At length his frequent ſollicit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings made her deſcend to't whether ſhe wou'd or no; and ſhe who had never diſobey'd him, at laſt conſented. The Embaſſadors return'd with their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions proſperouſly diſcharg'd; and the next thing to be conſider'd was her Tranſportation to <hi>Philippia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It happen'd at this time that the Crown of <hi>Philippia</hi> was in Confederacy with the King of the famous Iſland <hi>Neptunia,</hi> againſt the common Enemy the Tyrant of <hi>Aſia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This King of <hi>Neptunia</hi> had above all his Anceſtors in that Monarchy ſo great a Force every Summer at Sea, that he was lookt upon as the entire ſupport of the War; and by being himſelf preſent with the Ally'd Armies in the Field, he had acquir'd immortal Renown by his great Conduct and Gallantry. And on the Ocean he triumph'd ſo ſecurely, that ſince the fatal Defeat which he gave the Tyrants Ships even upon their own Coaſt, the Dominion of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riental Seas became entirely his. <hi>Cato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> having the opportunity of ſo good a Friend, and being ill provided of Shipping himſelf, bethought himſelf of ſending to his Embaſſador who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151495:33"/>
reſides at that Court, to beg that a Squadron of Men of War might be detatcht out of ſo numerous a Fleet, and ſent on this important Errand. This being immediately granted, it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, that his Chief General <hi>Saladine,</hi> famous for a Thouſand glories, ſhou'd Sail with the Capital Squadron to the Imperial Shore, and wait for her Arrival.</p>
                  <p>This General, whom we ſhall deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe becauſe of his importance in this Story, was a Gentleman of one of the firſt Houſes in the Kingdom of <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunia;</hi> his Anceſtors had been for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages famous in the Records of that Country; and though he himſelf was but a younger Branch of that illuſtrious Stock, yet at this time his Family boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of one of the beſt Eſtates, and the beſt Titles in the Land, and even he himſelf enjoy'd an honourable Report, and a Spacious Fortune, beſides what he held by his Noble Employments, and was all along one of the leading Subjects of the Nation: He had been Educated with all the advantages the Court cou'd give him; and beſides thoſe outward Accompliſhments, he was of a graceful perſon, and exceeding ſuavity of Manners. When he received his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151495:33"/>
he made what haſte he cou'd to get ready, and with much celerity he furniſh'd himſelf with all things fitting ſo high a truſt. As he was a man of great Addreſs, he ſpar'd for nothing that was proper for the Entertainment of ſo Royal a Gueſt, and his liberality was on this occaſion ſo particular, that he put himſelf and all his Retinue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to magnificent Garbs, and loaded his Ship with profuſion of all manner of Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and adorn'd the Royal Apartment with all the beauty he cou'd purchaſe for it, inſomuch that after her Embark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it may be admitted a Queſtion if ever the Princeſs had been more mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificently regal'd in her Father's, or any of the Courts of the Empire, tho' all the Treaſures of the Province were laid upon the Board.</p>
                  <p>'Twas in this manner the gallant <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladine</hi> waited for the coming of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated Dame, and after ſome few days expectation, the Bruit of her approach gave him notice to prepare, and he now began to ſet all things in order for her Reception. In few Hours after he heard the Guns from the Shoar, proclaim'd her Entrance into the Port Town, and he anſwer'd 'em with his and all the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151495:34"/>
Ordnance of his Squadron: When ſhe firſt beheld the <hi>Neptunian</hi> Fleet, tho' at a diſtance, ſhe felt in her ſelf all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions of joy and terror: The firſt aroſe from the pleaſure ſhe had in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding ſuch a noble preparation for her, and the latter from the reluctance ſhe had to this unwelcome Voyage: But the Ceremonies of the place not giving her leiſure to reflect on any thing, ſhe muſt of neceſſity render her ſelf to the Civilities of thoſe Princes and other great Perſonages who came to pay her their Gratulations. When the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials were over, and ſhe no longer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd, ſhe withdrew to her Cloſet, to over-rule as much as ſhe cou'd her Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and to be at liberty to fortify her ſelf againſt the approaching Fate: But in vain was all her Philoſophy; for tho' ſhe had an entire reſignation to the Will of her Father in every thing, yet in this Circumſtance ſhe cou'd not chuſe but condemn him for diſpoſing of her without her own Approbation: Night drew on, and ſhe retir'd to her Repoſe, having firſt ſent to <hi>Saladine,</hi> that the next Morning ſhe wou'd come Aboard.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151495:34"/>When the Morning came, the Shore was crowded with infinite Numbers of People who preſt to ſee Her. The Cannon again founded her Triumph, and the Clamours of the Amaz'd Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators return'd it to the Skies. The Nobles who attended Her were now diſmiſt; and they who were part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Her, wholly reſign'd her to the care of the happier <hi>Saladine.</hi> 'Twas viſible in every Eye the grief they had to part with Her, but moſt of all in Her own, when She conſidered She was to take Her everlaſting leave of Her own Country, in exchange for another. She cou'd not think of without Tears: She bid 'em all adieu with exceeding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret; and having turn'd her Eyes to the Fleet, ſhe gave her ſelf up to her expected deſtiny. The haſty Oars car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd her off, and the laſt ſight ſhe took of the Shore, drew ſome ſighs which She had not ſtrength to ſtifle.</p>
                  <p>At length She came Aboard, and the Sumptuous <hi>Saladine</hi> receiv'd her at the ſide. But good Gods! the Aſtoniſhment he was in when he beheld the immortal Charmer! The Tongues of Angels tun'd to Celeſtial Muſick cannot utter his ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize; He thought he had receiv'd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151495:35"/>
ſomething immortal, and he was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a thought of proſtrating himſelf at her Feet, to ſhow how much he was inchanted: 'Tis inexpreſſible his Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Amaze; for tho' at another time he cou'd ha' plaid the Orator, now Exceſſive Splendor ſtruck him dumb. He gaz'd at the fair Divinity, as if he had never beheld any Human Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before; and notwithſtanding all his good breeding, he was ſtruck into ſilence and ſtupidity; juſt as a Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler who unawares is ſurpriz'd with ſome ſuperb Building, whoſe marvellous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of a ſudden ſtrikes him with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable Tranſports. At length he tries to ſpeak, but the power was wanting; for the Organs of his Voice were bound up in Rapture, and he remain'd like a Statue ſtiff and void of Motion. His Mind was agitated with a thouſand dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Labours; and in his Breaſt he already felt a Fire which ſcorcht him to the Heart: His Eyes were fixt not to be remov'd, his Countenance chang'd with the Anguiſh of his Paſſion, and he trembled as if an Earthquake had ſhook the Foundations of the World. At laſt he burſt out—Ye Gods! what can this be? Why do I gaze on this Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151495:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Creature, to whom 'tis even Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege to ſpeak? He ſtopt and gave his Senſes leave to renew their Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Still his Amazement continu'd; and tho' the Credit of his Character lay at ſtake for ſo profound ſtupidity, yet he was ſo loſt in wild Confuſion, that 'twas in vain to endeavour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
                  <p>The quickſighted Princeſs ſaw all his diſorder, and cou'd not chuſe but aſcribe it to ſome extraordinary Cauſe, his handſom appearance ſpoke him no Clown, and ſhe believ'd perhaps on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion he cou'd ha' carry'd himſelf another manner, yet far from divining the true reaſon, ſhe conſider'd him as a man under ſome diſſatisfaction, and gave her ſelf no Curioſity to examine it further.</p>
                  <p>Theſe were the firſt Impreſſions they had of each other, he was Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruck with the Figure of ſo excellent a Creature, and ſhe was pleas'd to have ſo Renowned a General to accompany her in her Voyage.</p>
                  <p>Upon her Embarking all the Ordnance was thrice diſcharg'd, Vollies of welcome were ſhouted by the Seamen, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151495:36"/>
was omitted to expreſs the Triumph of the day.</p>
                  <p>The beautiful <hi>Nuberia</hi> had among other Ladies, one whom ſhe admitted into all her Affairs. This Lady ſhe choſe for her Bedfellow, and for the Partner of her ſecrets: To her ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan now to reveal her diſpleaſure of this Marriage; and tho' ſhe had not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd her Heart in any Paſſion elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; yet ſhe found in her inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons no promptneſs to the Alliance. She fail'd not to tell her, that the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the <hi>Philippian</hi> Monarch wou'd by no means ſuit with hers, that ſhe had heard how his Government had run him into diſcredit with his own People, and that he was too much a Saint to be a good Lover.</p>
                  <p>The indulgent Maid agreed with her in what ſhe ſaid, and humour'd her Melancholy with more than an affected pity; for ſhe really lamented her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: The ingenious <hi>Fidelia</hi> had been brought up with her Miſtreſs in her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Court. In their Infancy they had been Companions, and from time to time as they grew up together, their Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and their Exerciſes had been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the ſame, and nothing happen'd
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151495:36"/>
to one, but the other ſhar'd in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction or diſtreſs: 'Twas thus that by a long Tryal of her Virtue the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Princeſs knew the value of her Friend, and ſhe never had than now more need of her Conſolation. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo well aſſur'd of her integrity, ſhe unboſom'd her ſelf of all thoſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which ſhe labour'd with.</p>
                  <p>By this time the amaz'd <hi>Saladine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to recover, he now ruminates on what he had ſeen, and the manner of his behaviour: He remembred he had been too remiſs in the Ceremony with which he ought to have receiv'd ſo il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious a Paſſenger, and torments him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the apprehenſion of having given her an ill Opinion of his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, he was afraid his ill behaviour wou'd be interpreted to proceed from want of Addreſs, or what was Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times worſe, from want of reſpect, and the dread of ſuch an impreſſion gave him unſpeakable trouble. In this diſtraction he cou'd hardly contain from running into the Cabbin, and proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf at her Feet: But that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance left him when he conſider'd he ſhou'd have opportunities ſufficient to clear himſelf of that imputation:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151495:37"/>
And immediately while it was unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to pay any further Civilities to the Princeſs, he call'd together his Captains and other Officers of his Ship, and gave 'em ſtrictly in charge to treat with moſt profound reſpect all ſuch of her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try who had the honour of attending her. This piece of Gallantry was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently reported to <hi>Nuberia,</hi> and ſhe ſeem'd extremely pleas'd to find her ſelf miſtaken in the Conduct of a man who knew how to regard her, and one that took ſuch early care to make himſelf obliging.</p>
                  <p>After ſhe had been Aboard a while, and contemplated the Magnificence of the Proviſion that was made for her, ſhe was highly delighted with it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that upon another occaſion ſhe cou'd ha' been well contented with ſuch an Abode; ſo ſhowing ſome inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to walk upon the Deck for a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the <hi>Neptunian</hi> Fleet, ſhe had no ſooner ſaid it, but the News was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd to <hi>Saladine,</hi> who haſten'd to the Cabbin-Door to receive her: She did not expect him there, but ſhe was not unpleaſantly ſurpriz'd to ſee him ſo obſequious, and to find him a little more complaiſant than he had been at
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151495:37"/>
her entrance: She then gave him her Hand, and walkt forwards with him: The confounded General trembled with the unexpected honour, he now felt her tender delicate Hand, and the joy which he conceiv'd at it threw him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into a Lethargy of Silence and Confuſion. Ye Heavens (he mutter'd to himſelf) what can this be? Whither will ye hurry the undone defenceleſs <hi>Saladine?</hi> If this I feel be love, firſt ſtrike me dead, rather than let me fear a Fire which muſt conſume me to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: How can a Wretch like I look up to ſo much brightneſs! 'tis Inſolence, 'tis Arrogance, 'tis Blaſphemy to ſpeak to her: Oh Charming Excellence! with that he ſunk his Eyes down to the Deck, and durſt not raiſe 'em up for fear of meeting hers.</p>
                  <p>The penetrating Princeſs, ſpite of all his Caution, ſaw his glances; but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever effect they had upon her, ſhe ſhow'd neither pleaſure nor reſentment; but paſſing on as if ſhe had not minded him, ſhe ſuffered him to lead her to the Balliſters, and there ſhe ſtopt: She thought ſhe had now given him an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of ſaying ſomething to her of the delightful proſpect they had; but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151495:38"/>
ſhe was quite out of her Aim; for even now again the poor ſufferer had no Language for her, but that of his Eyes. This gave her extreme impatience, and ſhe cou'd not conjecture the cauſe of his continu'd reſerv'dneſs; but being no longer able to hide her Curioſity, ſhe began the Converſation by asking him if that were the whole Navy of <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunia.</hi> Her Voice awak't him; but not being ſo much at leiſure to himſelf to conſider what ſhe ſaid, he Anſwer'd her in broken Accents very far from the purpoſe; this increaſt her Wonder and his Confuſion; and for an Hour toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he cou'd not recover from his Amazement. Never was the loſt <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine</hi> in ſuch a Labyrinth of Miſery, he ſaw himſelf entring into a Paſſion which might prove fatal to him, and he now began to loſe all hopes of arming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: Every ſight he had of her gave him leſs and leſs aſſurance of his Recovery, and ſtill plung'd him deeper. The cautious Princeſs was in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion as well as he, to ſee him thus; not that ſhe altogether believ'd ſhe had any intereſt in his diſorder; but 'tis very likely ſhe wiſht the happy <hi>Saladine</hi> ſo well, that ſhe cou'd ſuffer with him in all his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151495:38"/>
She began to condole and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty him, and tho' ſhe found no violent Inclination to Love him as yet, yet ſhe conceiv'd for him ſuch an ardent Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as was not many degrees from it. She believ'd ſhe might without an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to her high Quality conſider him as her Friend, and not making any further Reflections on the State of her preſent Diſpoſition, ſhe gave her Heart leave to act as it wou'd.</p>
                  <p>'Tis indeed to be allow'd, that bating that Melancholy which had overcaſt him, The gallant <hi>Saladine</hi> wanted no Ornament to recommend him, his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was exceeding Graceful, his Meen and Air had ſomething of uncommon agreableneſs, and beſides the advantage of his Perſon, he had a happy Genius in his Dreſs, which never fail'd of ſerving him to good purpoſe. <hi>Nuberia</hi> was a good Judge of theſe Things, ſhe had been always us'd to the beſt of both Sexs, and that in a Country ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much addicted to ſhow and Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; ſo that when ſhe beheld our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral attentively, ſhe perſwaded her ſelf ſhe had never ſeen any thing that pleas'd her better. After ſome ſtay, and a little Converſation, ſhe again gave
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151495:39"/>
him her Hand to lead her back, and having waited on her to the Cabbin Door, he made her a profound Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and withdrew. When ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Cabbin, ſhe found the Table covered with a magnificent Banquet prepar'd for her; She was pleas'd with the Surpriſe, and cou'd no longer think but her General knew in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to entertain her, and thinking it no breach of Order to deſire his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſhe ſent to him, and beg'd that he wou'd favour her with it. The well Bred <hi>Saladine</hi> wou'd have excus'd his ſitting in her Preſence, and deſir'd no greater Honour than to wait at her Chair, but no Excuſe wou'd be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, ſhe was reſolved to diſpenſe with all Ceremonies, and by beginning a more intimate Acquaintance to try if ſhe cou'd find out the Cauſe of his Perplexity; ſeeing it better became him to obey, than to refuſe a Civility from one ſo much above him, he took a little more aſſurance, and plac'd himſelf at the lower end of the Table. Soon as the Meal began the Muſick ſtruck up, and now every Sence was delighted; She had every Thing that was agreable to her Taſt, her Sight and her Ears, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151495:39"/>
ſhe ſeem'd at this time to be ſo preſent to her natural good Humour, that for a long while ſhe forgot her Afflictions, and gave her ſelf up to Eaſe and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
                  <p>There is not on Earth any Thing that ſoftens the Soul ſo much as Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, it muſt be a ſtubborn inflexible Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that can't be alarm'd at it, not ſuch as that of the generous <hi>Saladine,</hi> who was ſtrangely mov'd with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing Sounds, his Heart was toucht with the piercing Echo, and now languiſhing upon the Strings, grew ſo very Amorous, that his extaſy carry'd him almoſt beyond the Apprehenſion of his Sufferings: He cou'd not forbear Wiſhing it might have the ſame influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the Divine <hi>Nuberia,</hi> and he cou'd not wiſh for any thing more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, for the tender Princeſs had a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Breaſt, and being exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleas'd with the ſplendor of her En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, ſhe found in her ſelf an Inclination not much to his Diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: She cou'd ha' been ſatisfy'd to have had her intended Bridegroom juſt ſuch a Man as <hi>Saladine,</hi> and the more ſhe conſider'd him, the more ſhe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented her Misfortune that ſhe was to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151495:40"/>
be ſuddenly depriv'd of him, to be thrown into the Arms of one, for whom ſhe had an unconquerable Prejudice. In this adverſity of Thought, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded him with more Addreſs, and as her Indulgence increaſt, ſo did his Flame. His Faculties now regain'd their wonted Vigour, his Aſſiduities were doubled, and every thing he did and ſaid tended to her good liking. In a little time ſhe grew more familiar, and he more aſſur'd; their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation was now grown unreſerv'd, and diſtances were laid aſide: She began to conſider him with ſomething more than indifference, and he gaz'd on her as he wou'd devour her with his Eyes. 'Twas then the accompliſht General began to diſplay himſelf, he was no longer aw'd with Majeſty, nor fetter'd with the Terror of Offending her: His Diſcourſe was free and eloquent, and to whatever he utter'd, her Ears were open and attentive. Sometimes his ſtollen Glances met her Eyes, and ſometime he was reſolv'd to declare he knew not what, but as yet his Courage was not ſufficient when he conſider'd what he was going to do, but ſtifling his Temerity he forbore to be ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151495:40"/>
He knew very well the danger of the Deſign, and while he was in Temper to Reflect, he trembled for his Arrogance. She on her part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hav'd her ſelf with much Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but not ſo far as to incourage his Hopes, and when he conſider'd the Happineſs he had already receiv'd, he ſaw he had good reaſon to be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Condition,</p>
                  <p>The Time being come that it was ſeaſonable to depart, he remembred that it was not decent to take too much advantage of the Honour ſhe did him, and making a handſome Complement to that purpoſe, he left her with her belov'd <hi>Fidelia,</hi> well pleas'd with what had paſt.</p>
                  <p>The Apartment where this charming Princeſs lay was directly under that where <hi>Saladine</hi> took up his Lodgings, The Roof that parted them was but thin, ſo that it was not difficult for the wakeful Lover to hear what Diſcourſe paſt between her faithful Confident and her. His Pains kept his Eyes from Slumber, and he had not long laid down, ere he heard his lovely Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger addreſs her ſelf to <hi>Fidelia</hi> in theſe Terms. Oh my <hi>Fidelia!</hi> Whither has
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151495:41"/>
my Father's Ambition hurry'd me? Why muſt I be made the Sacrifice of his Glory, by becoming the Wife of one for whom I can have no Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Is there in a Crown any thing can make me happy? No my <hi>Fidelia,</hi> 'tis worth no more than the Riches that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn it, and I deſpiſe it as a Trifle not worth my Heart: Why am I then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlav'd to Greatneſs without the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of chooſing for my ſelf? Oh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy State of Women Born for ſuch Alliances! Were this <hi>Philippian</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch Generous, he wou'd releaſe me from my Fears, and not betray me to a Marriage in which I have not conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Eyes. Why muſt I Marry whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I Love or no? Am I not a Woman, Born with Paſſions like other Women? Have I not a Heart to give, and can I not Love? Oh Yes, my dear <hi>Fidelia!</hi> I have all the tenderneſs of my Sex, my Boſom is ſoft and gentle, my Heart is flexible and relenting, and I have a force of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in me, which tells me, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beloved, I never can be Happy.</p>
                  <p>The pitying confident heard her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſs with infinite Sorrow, ſhe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd not to perſwade her it was for her Glory, but conſented to every
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151495:41"/>
thing ſhe ſaid, and lamented with her the Severity of her Condition. On the contrary ſhe told her, the Court of <hi>Philippia</hi> was an abſolute Priſon to all the Queens who enter'd into 't, and the nature of the People was to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively jealous of their Wives. What then will become of me, ſhe cry'd? Can I endure to have my Honour ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to be guarded like a Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal? Oh wretched Fate! Unhappy loſt <hi>Nuberia!</hi> Theſe Words were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd aloud, and the attentive <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine</hi> echo'd her Sighs with his: He wiſht it were not ſo, but alaſs, how cou'd he oppoſe it? He ſaw ſhe was going to Execution, and that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was to carry her to the fatal Place. This Thought rackt him to Death, and made him Ten Thouſand times more uneaſy than the poor Sufferer below: He cou'd ha' dy'd to rid her of that tormenting Deſtiny, and a Thouſand times he reſolved, if ſhe wou'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, rather than to obey his Orders, to carry her into ſome far diſtant Country, where ſhe ſhou'd never hear more of that unfortunate Contract. But yet he had ſome Conſolation from her Averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to't, becauſe he hop'd it might
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151495:42"/>
make better way for him, not that he cou'd aſpire to make her his, for that was infinitely above his expectation, but yet he hop'd, ſhe wou'd not be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſenſible of his Paſſion, ſince her Heart was diſingag'd, and at liberty to pleaſe it ſelf. Thus this diſconſolate Company were condoling their ſeveral Misfortunes, when Word was brought to the General that the Wind was fair.</p>
                  <p>He who had taken no reſt, was now weary of his Pillow, and upon this Summons riſes. He found the Wind preſented, and that 'twas neceſſary to uſe it, ſo gave Orders for Sailing. Then were his Pains renew'd, when he conſider'd he was now advancing to his and the mourning <hi>Nuberia</hi>'s Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, every Wave his Ship cut carry'd 'em further on, but much happier wou'd he have thought it, if thoſe Waves had bury'd him. The Noiſe that is at ſuch a time reacht the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Princeſs; and when ſhe was told ſhe was on her Voyage, ſhe abandon'd her ſelf to Deſpair; and in her innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Torments invok'd the God of Tempeſts to end her unhappy Being: But in vain were all her Prayers, the uncertain Elements were never more certain, and the God of the Waters diſobey'd her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:151495:42"/>The Wind continu'd fair for many Days, fair for their Voyage, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to their Wiſhes, and 'twas not now long ere they expected to ſee the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome Shore. Then was it that all the Pangs and Agonies of Grief ſurrounded 'em, the drooping Fair ſunk under her approaching Calamity, the weeping <hi>Fidelia</hi> kept her beloved Princeſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in her Melancholy, but the Rage, the Torment, the Diſtraction of the loſt <hi>Saladine</hi> is not to be expreſt. He Curſt the proſperous Wind, he rail'd at Heaven, he Curſt himſelf, and only Bleſt <hi>Nuberia:</hi> He ſaw too late that he now lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d her, he ſaw her going to her Grave, he ſaw himſelf going to be depriv'd of her for ever, and all this confuſion of Miſery not to be ſhun'd. Thus was he fretting like a Lion in the Toil, champing the Chain that held him to his Fate, and calling for Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to daſh him into Pieces, when of a ſudden the Wind came about, and as it had been for four Days directy for 'em, it was now as directly againſt 'em.</p>
                  <p>Never was ſo ſucceſsful a Turn as this: Their Curſes were all chang'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Bleſſings, and the Deity which juſt before they had Blaſphem'd, was now
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151495:43"/>
the God of their Thankſgivings. The overjoy'd <hi>Saladine,</hi> ran in haſt to carry the News to the diſconſolate fair One, covering his Joy with as much Temper as he cou'd, not to give her any Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy that he knew of her Averſion to the Voyage, and ſhe receiv'd the News with wonderful Serenity, tho' her Heart was in no good Condition to diſguiſe her Satisfaction. Soon after this lucky turn it fell flat Calm, not a Breath of Wind ruffled the Face of the Deep, the Elements were in perfect Tranquility, the floating Palaces lay wantoning on the Boſom of the Ocean; the ſporting <hi>Nercids</hi> danc'd around 'em, wondring at this univerſal Stillneſs. Now they mov'd neither one way nor other, their Ships rode on the ſmooth Pacifick as they had been held by their Anchors, their Sails flatted againſt the Maſts, and the idle Sailors had nothing to employ em: The Face of Heaven had not one Cloud that threatned them, the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeem'd to be ſettled in this Halcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Morning and Evening Fogs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated no near approach of an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration. It ſeem'd indeed, as Fate had contriv'd it for the Wiſhes of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Saladine,</hi> who deſir'd nothing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151495:43"/>
more than to dwell for ever in the Company of his charming Princeſs.</p>
                  <p>The fair <hi>Nuberia</hi> too cou'd not hear of this revolution without warm emotions of Joy, as it delay'd a while her arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val to her Deſtiny, and gave her a longer injoyment of the noble Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, whom ſhe began to value with a more than ordinary Eſteem. She had been ſenſible in this part of her Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of his frequent Diligences, and a thouſand Turns of Gallantry with which he hop'd to pleaſe her, ſhe ſaw in all his Actions an Air of Nobility, and ſuch a profound Submiſſion, that even her exalted Quality cou'd hardly countenance it: But above all ſhe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſht that Deſire which ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd he had to pleaſe her, which with the reſt of his Tenders took ſuch root in her Heart, that ſhe cou'd not forbear ſhowing on all Occaſions the Satisfaction ſhe received in his Services. She now thought it no Crime to wiſh him well, and if a little Tenderneſs mixt with it, ſhe had not Power to controul it. 'Tis true, ſhe conſider'd ſhe was going to tie her ſelf for everlaſting to the Embraces of her contracted Husband, and that her Duty wou'd not warrant her Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151495:44"/>
for any other Perſon, but tho' ſhe was of an inviolable Vertue, and in all Things paid a ſolemn deference to her Honour, and to her Father's Will, yet the Image of the generous <hi>Saladine</hi> wou'd break in upon her moſt ſerious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, and make her whither ſhe wou'd or no regard him with ſome concern.</p>
                  <p>He on the other hand grew every Day more inflam'd, he found he lov'd in good earneſt, but the dread of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending her kept him from revealing it: This conſtraint he put upon his Paſſion ſerv'd but to increaſe it, and the more he ſtrove to conquer it, the more unconquerable it grew. This ſet him ſometimes on extravagant Projects; now he wou'd reſolve to let her ſee it, but preſently he apprehended the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery might be fatal, if ſhe ſhou'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it with Diſpleaſure: Sometimes he determin'd to prepare her by making an intereſt with <hi>Fidelia,</hi> but knowing the uncorrupted Duty that Lady paid her Princeſs, he was afraid it might miſcarry on that ſide too.</p>
                  <p>Never was a poor Lover agitated with ſo many different reſolutions; as he was, he felt intolerable Pains, yet if he ſhou'd attempt to eaſe 'em, it might add to his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151495:44"/>
Afflictions by ſeeing her offended. He found he now lov'd with all the fury of Diſtraction, his mind was never at reſt, but when his Eyes were on her, his Viſage chang'd, his Health left him, his Body ſicken'd, and all the Faculties of his Soul were at War one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He no longer took any Care of the Expedition, the Buſineſs of the Voyage was quite out of his Memory, and the charge of his Commiſſion lay buried in profound Oblivion. Theſe violent Convulſions threw him into a Fever, yet he choſe to ſuffer on with invincible Fortitude, rather than di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulge the Cauſe of his Pain. But tho' he ſtrove with his Paſſion, 'twas in vain to ſtrive with his Diſtemper, his Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs daily increaſt, and all his Phyſicians were in conſultation about his Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. They readily found out his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, but the Cauſe was beyond their Search, to no Purpoſe were their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications made, the Symptoms of Death had already markt him for another World, and they had nothing in their Art that cou'd remove 'em.</p>
                  <p>When the News of his Danger was carry'd to the Princeſs, ſhe was extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly griev'd, and the more, becauſe ſhe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151495:45"/>
doubted if it wou'd conſiſt with her Character to viſit him: She cou'd have been contented to have eas'd him of one half of his Illneſs, for ſhe lookt on him with the ſame tenderneſs, as if ſhe had a Brother in his Condition: But Maugre all Ceremonies, ſhe found ſhe cou'd contain her ſelf no longer, and ſending her dear Confident to know if a Viſit wou'd be agreeable to him, that Maid ran to his Apartment, and found him almoſt in the Arms of Death.</p>
                  <p>At the Name of the Princeſs he ſtarted from the Verge of Life, and looking up to ſee who ſounded that charming Name, he ſaw it was the Faithful <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delia:</hi> He held forth his Hand to let the welcome Meſſenger know nothing cou'd give him greater Comfort, and tho' his Tongue had not power to utter his Joy, his Eyes confeſt it. When the frighted Maid return'd to her Miſtriſs, ſhe related to her the deplorable Condition he was in, and the trembling Princeſs hearing her with infinite Pity, ſhe haſten'd with her to the Scene where the expiring Lover lay: At the firſt Sight of her, his Spirits forſook him, but ſtriving to recover, he wou'd have rais'd his Head to pay her his Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151495:45"/>
for ſo undeſerv'd an Honour; but ſhe approach'd his Bed time enough to prevent him, and took her Seat by the Bed-ſide. The poor unthinking fair here diſpenc'd with the <hi>Decorum</hi> of her Quality, as a Princeſs, and as a Wife, ſhe conſider'd the occaſion too preſſing to inſiſt upon Formalities, and ſhe choſe rather to deny for once her duty to her Honour, than to the Neceſſity of her Friendſhip for the dying Patient: She then beheld him in the Agonies of Death, chang'd from what he was, and ſhe thought it Charity to adminiſter all her good Offices for his recovery.</p>
                  <p>The Apprehenſion ſhe had of his danger made him now almoſt dear to her, who perhaps for want of ſuch an occaſion might have ſtill kept her Heart ſecure; but ſo it is, that we oftentimes begin to Love, when there is any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of loſing what before we only eſteem'd. Now it was that the Criſis of his Fate was at the higheſt, there was but one way of ſaving his Life, and that was guarded with innumerable Difficulties. He had the pleaſure of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding his Divine <hi>Nuberia;</hi> but where was that Tongue that cou'd reveal his Suff'rings? His Eyes languiſht on the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151495:46"/>
beloved Object as they were rivetted to't, but his Voice was ſhut up with Awe and Terror.</p>
                  <p>This moving ſight ſtruck our gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Princeſs with mortal Anguiſh, the compaſſionate <hi>Fidelia</hi> wept over him, and it was hard to ſay which of the Three bore the moſt ſignificant Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of Deſpair.</p>
                  <p>The Princeſs omitted nothing that cou'd expreſs her infinite ſorrow; nor to comfort him while there were any hopes he yet might do well: At laſt ſhe try'd by Queſtions to find out the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable Cauſe, but all her inquiries return'd without ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>If the gallant <hi>Saladine</hi> (ſaid ſhe) has ſo much confidence in my Friendſhip as to truſt me with the ſecret of his myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ilneſs, he ſhall find I ſhall concern my ſelf in his ſufferings as if they were my own: I Conjure you therefore, no longer to hide the cauſe of your indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; but if I have any prevalence over you, or you value the repoſe of one who has an intereſt in your welfare, declare what it is that burthens your Spirits, and preſſes down your noble Nature to ſuch an extremity.</p>
                  <p>Tho' there was a great deal of kindneſs
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151495:46"/>
in theſe words, yet the guilty Blood ſtole into his Cheeks, his Eyes were ſunk down, and a fatal ſhiv'ring ſhook the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the Bed: He ſtill had a check of ſhame on him, tho' ſhe ſeem'd ſo much intereſted in his Affliction, and to encourage the diſcovery: But at laſt aſſuming more reſolution, he rais'd his Eyes up to hers, and ſhe encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring 'em in the very minute of his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt langour, ſhe ſaw there was ſomething in his Heart which he fain wou'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal, but that he was withheld by ſome ſecret reluctance: He ſtruggled long between his pains and his fears, ſhe ſaw him in perplexity, and he ſaw her in trouble for him. This indeed ſeem'd a fair opportunity for him, he thought now to hazard all, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but he ſhou'd ſoon be out of a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of ſeeing her diſpleas'd with him, by the approach of that Hour which he had been impatlently expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but he was not long of that Opinion, his fears return'd upon him, and after all his ſtrugglings he was forc'd to reſolve rather to die than to tell her.</p>
                  <p>Juſt as he had thus determin'd, the Phyſicians came in, and cut off all farther Converſation for that time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:151495:47"/>The impatient Princeſs felt violent vexation at this croſs Adventure, and ſhe had rather have ſpar'd 'em that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, than have been ſo unſeaſonably inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: But not thinking it convenient to tarry longer; and being already a little reſented to be found in his Cabbin, ſhe quitted it, not without great regret to leave him in that condition.</p>
                  <p>But now behold what a turn of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune! for while the indulgent Princeſs had been converſing with him, <hi>Fidelia</hi> ſpying a Paper folded up in the Form of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeal'd, and carefully laid by his Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, ſhe took it up, and was amaz'd to find it inſcrib'd, <hi>to the Princeſs Nuberia.</hi> She made ſure of ſo happy an Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; and carrying it with her into the Princeſſes Apartment, ſhe gave it her to read, who open'd it with eager haſt and found it thus:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <p>When I am Dead and my torments at an end, let it be known to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Nuberia</hi> that for her I dye: I cou'd not live to ſee her anothers; and being unworthy to poſſeſs her, I choſe rather to end my Paſſion with my Life, than to live in perpetual Miſery: Let this be a Memorial of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151495:47"/>
my Love, and let me be pity'd by all ſucceeding Lovers.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Saladine.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis impoſſible to deſcribe the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent effects this Letter produc'd in the Breaſt of the Aſtoniſht Princeſs, ſhe cou'd not but look upon this diſcovery, as an injury to her Birth, and to the Circumſtances of her Condition, ſhe knew it was not fit for her to hear of Love from any perſon, at ſuch a criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal juncture when ſhe was juſt going to be the Wife of another: But then ſhe conſidered the deplorable ſtate of the dying <hi>Saladine,</hi> and how much he choſe to ſuffer rather than make it known; and then ſhe really wiſht him happier: A long time her duty and her inclination contended for poſſeſſion, and ſpite of all oppoſition at laſt her pity triumph'd. She his conſider'd her ſelf the cauſe of mortal dejection, ſhe conſider'd how full of reſpect his behaviour had all along been, and to what an extremity he was now reduc'd: And theſe Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions wrought upon her more than all the Rhetorick he cou'd have us'd: The tender hearted <hi>Fidelia</hi> was no leſs mov'd
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151495:48"/>
than ſhe, that faithful Maid had a high Opinion of his Vertues; and now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to confirm the Princeſs in thoſe kind Sentiments: She Adviſes her again to viſit him, and repreſented to her the neceſſity of ſaving ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a Life; to which the Princeſs reply'd, What can I do <hi>Fidelia?</hi> Thou know'ſt I'm not at liberty to hear of ſuch a paſſion, my cruel Father has ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crific'd me to his Ambition, and how ſhall I withſtand the force of my Deſtiny?</p>
                  <p>But Madam (ſhe was preſently inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted) you may ſee him, you may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him to be ſo far happy, as to let him ſee you pity him, if you can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him no more: You're not yet in the Court of <hi>Philippia,</hi> here are no Eyes to watch you, nor Tell-tales to publiſh any Breach of <hi>Decorum;</hi> you are not yet ſubjected to the Auſterity of thoſe Rules, that misfortune will come ſoon enough; In the mean time therefore ask your ſelf how neceſſary it is to ſave a Life which you confeſs is not indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent t' you, and reſolve over all Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to viſit him again.</p>
                  <p>The diſconſolate Princeſs was at a ſtand how to carry her ſelf in ſuch a perplexity, ſhe found but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151495:48"/>
little inclination to diſobey her, but ſhe cou'd not eaſily conſent to put her ſelf into the opportunity of an Amour which by no means conſiſted with her Honour. But when ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted her Heart, theſe Obſtacles were of little force, and after ſhe had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd what to do, ſhe prepar'd to ſee him again.</p>
                  <p>The dying deſponding <hi>Saladine</hi> knew nothing of this Accident; he every Hour expected Death; and had framed that Letter to let his beloved Princeſs know he dy'd for his inſolent Paſſion: While he was now muſing on the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of his fate, he was amaz'd to ſee them enter his Cabbin again. The Princeſs held in her Hand the guilty Paper, and he knowing it to be his, his Aſtoniſhment and Shame was beyond all Confinement: Then no longer doubting but that ſhe knew all, he was ready to yield up his Breath with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe and Confuſion. He cry'd out in an extaſy of penitence, Oh Heav'ns! what have I done? How has my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Hand betray'd me? Oh Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam! Let me not live to meet your Eyes: My guilty Flame has undone me, and I now deſerve to become your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151495:49"/>
The Queen lookt on him with ſome glances of Compaſſion; and tho' ſhe ſtill remembred this tenderneſs was not to be juſtify'd; yet ſhe cou'd not forbear ſaying, Here Unhappy <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladine,</hi> Take back your guilty Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and with it—My good wiſhes for your Health; and if you Value my ſatisfaction, preſerve your life. Theſe unexpected words were life it ſelf, he needed no other remedy to reſtore his Health, and already he felt his Heart reliev'd, and the powers of his Soul quickned up to Joy and Rapture: Then looking on her with Eyes divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Awe and Extaſy, he told her if he deſerv'd not to dye for what he had done, he wou'd live to make the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his Life the witneſs of her indulgent Goodneſs.</p>
                  <p>Then in a Moment his illneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to abate, his Fever left him, his Countenance reſum'd its uſual luſtre, and thro' all his Veins the vital Blood ran temperate and healthful: All Signs of dangers were remov'd, his Reaſon return'd, and his Senſes poſſeſt their former Occupations. No Marks of Deſperation appear'd any longer, nor any Raptures but what
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151495:49"/>
he utter'd in the admiration of her Mercy.</p>
                  <p>The Princeſs was much joy'd at this alteration; ſhe told him, That if the recovery of his Health depended ſo much on her power, ſhe was ſorry ſhe cou'd not always be his Phyſician; that ſhe had conſideration enough for the Merits of ſo generous a Man; but it was entirely againſt her Honour to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his Paſſion as it deſerv'd; but if he cou'd be ſatisfy'd with ſuch a place in her Heart as wou'd not invade her Duty, ſhe ſhou'd conceive for him the moſt tender Friendſhip; but that if ſhe were at liberty to chuſe a Lover that cou'd be moſt grateful to her, ſhe cou'd not fix better than on the <hi>Gallant Saladine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There needed no more to finiſh his recovery, he cou'd not hope to break off the Nuptials ſhe was going to Celebrate, and all the Ambition he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted, was but to ſee himſelf in her good Opinion, and in ſome poſſeſſion of her Heart: He heard her laſt words with tranſporting joy, and tho' there was a great deal due to the preſence of ſo illuſtrious a Princeſs, yet he broke out from all Conſtraints of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency into an extravagance of Paſſion.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151495:50"/>
Oh ye Celeſtial Powers (he cry'd) too happy, Happy <hi>Saladine!</hi> and can the generous Princeſs pardon me? Can ſhe forget my daring Inſolence, and forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me the Sentence of Death which was my due, raiſe me to Life? and bid me live for ever? Oh let me rave a while with boundleſs Extaſy, till I have utter'd this exceſs of joy that fills my grateful Soul: Yes, I will live, ſince you command me, and live a thouſand thouſand Ages, till I become immortal as my Love, and carry to the end of Nature the Triumph of your Eyes.</p>
                  <p>She wou'd have checkt his Tranſport, but he was in no condition to hear Reaſon; his Flight was too laviſh to be bound up to Rules, and he ſpar'd nothing that expreſs'd his Gratitude and her Generoſity. At length he ſtopt, and ſhe Anſwer'd in ſuch Terms as theſe.</p>
                  <p>I have already done more for the brave <hi>Saladine</hi> than I can juſtify to the preſent dependence of my Affairs; but I have conſider'd every thing, and I find all too weak for my Inclination: It becomes me not to ſay more, perhaps I have ſaid too much already. Only that if our Fortunes had ſo ordain'd it, I cou'd have been content without the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151495:50"/>
Temptation of a Crown, to have ſhar'd my happineſs with him. She bluſh'd for what ſhe had ſaid, and not able to look up, ſhe let fall her Eyes, and wiſh ſhe had not ſaid ſo much. As it gave her confuſion, ſo it increaſt his Happineſs; and now the reviv'd Lover, who a moment before wou'd have part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Life for an Expiation of his Guilt, liv'd to ſee himſelf forgiv'n, and what was infinitely more, belov'd: Now be undertook to talk with the freedom of a Lover; and while his Tongue was recounting the violence of his Flame, his Heart and his Sighs kept time with his paſſionate Relation: His languiſhing Looks pleaded powerfully for him, and he who knew to a ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the way to a Ladies Heart, made every geſture humour the diſtreſsful Tale: Now he play'd the Orator in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, his Tongue was Tipt with ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, his Eyes with Fire, his Breaſt beat to the Accents of his Voice, and every thing he utter'd was Muſick to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive Princeſs, 'Twou'd be very hard to deſcribe our General with all the advantages which he now poſſeſt; for notwithſtanding his Illneſs, he had an Air of ſweetneſs in his Face, and in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151495:51"/>
Action ſuch a perſuaſive Allurement, as was not to be reſiſted. The Princeſs receiv'd a ſenſible Impreſſion of all he ſaid and did, ſhe found her Heart al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready totter'd, and when ſhe wou'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain have conſulted her Reaſon, ſhe had no power to think. She repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her Fancy that ſhe had never ſeen any thing more worthy of her, and now ſhe was not determining whether ſhe ſhou'd love him or no; for that was already decided, and 'twas too far gone to be recalled: Her Heart became ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely his, and there wanted but the conſent of Fortune to make 'em the happieſt Couple in the World. Now the diſtances of their Quality and all reſervation was laid aſide, our Lover grew more aſſur'd by the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhe had giv'n him; and taking her fair Hand, he held it to his Lips with ſuch ardency as very much affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her: She grew leſs ſcrupulous as he grew more aſſur'd, and ſhe miſtruſted not thoſe innocent allowances in the poſſeſſion of one ſhe eſteem'd ſo much, and whom ſhe had found ſo worthy of her Confidence.</p>
                  <p>Thus were they highly ſatisfy'd with each other, ſhe was exceedingly pleas'd
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151495:51"/>
to ſee ſhe had ſuch power over him as to reſtore him to Life at her pleaſure; and he was in no ordinary degree of rapture, to ſee ſuch a change in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to be redeem'd from the jaws of Death and Deſpair, and to ſee himſelf rais'd from ſuch dejected Miſeries to a felicity infinitely above his hopes. But alas how ſhort were theſe ſtarts of joy! they preſently call'd to mind that they were not ordain'd for one another, that they were within few days of part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, never to behold each other more. Soon as that diſmal thought ſeiz'd 'em, they were both caſt down into mortal Affliction: All the Terrors of Deſpair ſate in their Faces, and they became the pity of the ſorrowful <hi>Fidelia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now to increaſe their Grief, the Weather grew Cloudy, the Calm was blown away with a boiſt'rous Eaſtern Gale, their Sails were all trimm'd for the purſuit of their Voyage, and they hurry'd on with ſuch precipitancy, that to their inſupportable ſorrow they ſaw the fatal Shore where they were to part for ever. Who can deſcribe the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of their ſuff'rings at the diſcovery of that infernal Coaſt? The Weeping Princeſs was paſt all Comfort, and the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151495:52"/>
furious <hi>Saladine</hi> ready to plunge into the bottomleſs deep to prevent the part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moment, which was but preventing one Death by another. But vain were their Complaints, the remorſeleſs Wind increas'd, and they fled before it with ſuch fury, that they plainly ſaw the Shore within few Hours Sail of 'em.</p>
                  <p>The nearer they approacht it, the more deplorable were their ſorrows, and they now macerated and tore 'em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the utmoſt apprehenſions of Deſpair, abandon'd to their Suff'rings and Diſtreſs. The Princeſs lay like one bereft of Reaſon, <hi>Fidelia</hi> ſympathiz'd with the Melancholy of her dear Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and the inconſolable <hi>Saladine</hi> had hers as well as his own Torments to afflict him. In that Frenzy he cou'd not forbear running into her Cabbin, where he found his Charmer over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd with trouble; and throwing himſelf at her Feet, beg'd to die in that poſture rather than to ſee her torn from him to an Everlaſting Separation. What did he not ſay to move her? But there needed no further Arguments to make her pity him, ſhe already found him ſo dear to her, that ſhe was within a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments conſideration of running the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151495:52"/>
of diſobeying her Father, and flying to ſome far diſtant ſafety with her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd <hi>Saladine.</hi> But theſe were only Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera's of a Diſtemper'd Brain, ſhe talkt of things impoſſible, and now there was no way to eſcape her Deſtiny.</p>
                  <p>The Storm began to ſing louder, and the faſter it blew, the nearer they drew to the unwelcome Scene: The Sea was now grown outragious, the Billows toſt 'em to the Skies, and the darken'd Heav'n (as if it mourn'd for their Calamity) was painted with the Viſage of horror and death. In this Tempeſt they hop'd for ſome unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed adventure, as being on an Element apt for Changes, at leaſt to delay a while their parting; but the Wind had no compaſſion of 'em, it Whiſtled ſtill louder, and drove 'em forwards with ſuch impetuoſity that now the Shore was juſt under their Bows, and ſpite of all their care, the Ships in hazard of periſhing. The alarm of this danger frighted all but the deſpairing Lovers; the Officers ran to the General for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in this extremity; but they might as well talk to the Clouds as to him: He was not at leiſure to regard the ſafety of his Fleet, being agitated with a greater Storm in his Breaſt, and whatever ſhou'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151495:53"/>
become of 'em, he was in no condition to prevent it: Immediately they dropt their Anchors, hoping to ride out the Storm; but all their caution was little enough to ſecure 'em. The Gulph of of <hi>Moco</hi> has always been notorious for Shipwrack, the Sea runs there with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible fury, and a thouſand Veſſels have found their deſtruction in its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable jaws. No Wonder therefore at this time the danger aſtoniſht all them who were tender of their ſafety; for throughout the whole Fleet there was not one who expected not Death, and who did not make it his buſineſs to ſhift for himſelf. All but the deſperate <hi>Saladine</hi> and his Princeſs were fearful of being ſtranded on the Shore, but they had ſo little taſte of Happineſs, that Death wou'd have been more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to 'em than Life, on any terms but of enjoying each other for ever. But ſeeing no hopes of ſuch a Fortune, they gave 'emſelves up with ready Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation to whatever ſhou'd befal 'em. In few Hours they cou'd behold ſeveral of their Ships caſt on the Shore, and the drowned Mariners toſt on the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentleſs Beach, as a Token of what they were now to expect.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:151495:53"/>This dreadful ſight gave all the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors unſpeakable horror, but to our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate Lovers it appear'd with a quite different Face: Not that they wanted pity for thoſe miſerable Wretches who were periſh'd; but it gave 'em hopes of ſuff'ring the ſame Death themſelves, and they were prepar'd to receive it with wonderful Alacrity.</p>
                  <p>The Princeſs felt not thoſe fears which were common to her Sex in ſuch Emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, her Courage was as much as was neceſſary, fortify'd with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of her <hi>Saladine,</hi> and in his Arms ſhe was reſolv'd to end her Life. He too who was grown careleſs of his own Life, neglected for a while even hers; and becauſe he ſaw he cou'd not be hers in Life, he rejoyc'd to think they ſhou'd die together. This indeed was grateful to him for a time; but at length he conſider'd, ſhe deſerv'd better Fortune than to periſh for want of the means of ſafety, and he now was of Opinion to prevail with her to have ſome regard to her ſelf. Accordingly he went to her, and Conjur'd her by all the happineſs ſhe wiſht him, not to remain longer Aboard, but to give him leave to get a pinnace ready to carry
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151495:54"/>
her a-ſhore, and to leave him to the Mercy of the Sea, who was willing to die if he cou'd ſecure her from the ruin which threatned her. He told her, there was leſs danger in venturing out than in remaining where ſhe was, that if ſhe wou'd conſent to go, he wou'd give in charge to his chief Officers to Pilot her a-ſhore, and to ſet her ſafe from the hazard of Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack: That indeed he wou'd attend her himſelf, but he cou'd by no means ſet his Feet on the Country where ſhe was to be for ever loſt to him; and that the torture which he ſhou'd feel to part with her, wou'd be too conſpicuous, and might give her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects occaſion of cenſuring that Relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctance, with which he was to ſee her torn from him.</p>
                  <p>Tho' there was a great deal of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in what he urg'd, ſhe cou'd not hear it without a Reſentment, which ſhow'd her violently offended; no Sir, ſhe cry'd, there is no ſafety for me where I have not the gallant <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine</hi> to bear me Company, and as we are now in the Moment of eternal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, I can rather conſent to periſh with you, than to indure the anguiſh
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151495:54"/>
of parting with you to ſuſtain a Crown which will prove a Torment to me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fatal Separation which it makes betwixt us. Then abandon'd to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, ſhe cry'd, Oh forgive my Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour! If I tranſgreſs the Bounds of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency to tell the faithful <hi>Saladine</hi> how much I Love him! Hence—away—with all Impediments of Duty, of ſtrict Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and contracted Vows, let me be Mad till I have rav'd enough, and told the generous Man how dearly I adore him! Oh take me to your Arms, and hide my Bluſhes, let me be wrapt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your faſt Embraces, and never wake but to behold you mine.</p>
                  <p>The Amorous <hi>Saladine</hi> was raviſht with this ſudden Tenderneſs, in all his Joys he never hop'd for ſuch a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but now his Soul was all on Fire. Ye bounteous Gods! (he cry'd) What Words are theſe? Oh let me hang upon your lovely Knees, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate on the Earth receive this Bleſſing! Then ſtarting from that Poſture, he flew out into a Tranſport, Let the Seas roar, and let Deſtruction reign, ſince I am made thus happy: Then running to her Arms, he added, Now—now— thou God of Whirlwinds ſtrike us
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151495:55"/>
down, ſink us together to the vaſt Abyſs, but let no Bolt of Thunder part our Arms! Oh Joy too great to bear!— here his Breath fail'd him, and the weeping Princeſs ready to expire with the moving Spectacle, ſunk down into his Arms, and they both remain'd as if they had been Dead. The diligent <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delia,</hi> who never left 'em, was in little better Condition, but knowing the Danger of calling for help, ſhe uſed all the Means ſhe cou'd to bring 'em to Life. <hi>Saladine</hi> firſt recover'd, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Princeſs entranc'd in his Arms, 'tis impoſſible to tell the various Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that poſſeſt him: He held her ſtill in his Embraces, and looking on her with Eyes that languiſht with the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs of his Heart, he was ready again to ſink to Death, but ſeeing her in that inſenſible Condition, he ventur'd to let down his Cheek to hers, and to touch thoſe Lips that now cou'd not be open'd to accuſe him: But 'twas with ſo much Awe, that if ſhe had awakt and felt him, ſhe cou'd not be offended with the Violence. His buſy Eyes ran over all her Perfections, and he gaz'd at her, as if indeed he never were to behold her more; and he cou'd have wiſht to Die
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151495:55"/>
that very Moment, without the deſire of any further Happineſs.</p>
                  <p>At length ſhe open'd her Eyes, and finding her ſelf in his Embraces, ſhe was a little ſtagger'd at her Weakneſs, and at another time cou'd not have pardon'd her ſelf ſuch a Confeſſion of her Love: But now 'twas too late to hide her Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhe was intirely reſign'd to her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and ſhe thought nothing too much for that charming Man, who knew how to uſe her Indulgence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out invading her Honour: Soon as ſhe collected her Spirits, ſhe lookt on him with ſuch Tenderneſs as cou'd proceed from nothing but her Excellency of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Generoſity, and he met thoſe Glances with ſuch a Languiſhment, that nothing cou'd be more moving than this dumb Converſation: He rais'd her up, and as well as he cou'd, deſir'd her to be compos'd, but her Trouble was too great to be comforted, and he was in no good State to give it her. <hi>Fidelia,</hi> who was leaſt concern'd, tho' not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her ſhare of their Miſery, prevail'd with her to retire, ſhe ſuffer'd her ſelf to be carry'd whither ſhe wou'd, and giving <hi>Saladine</hi> her Hand to ſupport her, ſhe was conducted to her Bed:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151495:56"/>
She ſtrove not to oppoſe 'em, but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in her tortur'd Breaſt no Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Reſt, ſhe laid her down, while the lamenting Maid did what ſhe cou'd to divert her. But in vain was all ſhe ſaid, her Heart was overcome with Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, and ſhe cou'd think of nothing but of the dreadful Hour that was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching. She now loſt all Hopes of periſhing in the Storm, for the Sky clear'd, and the Face of the Deep was grown ſmooth and calm; and every Minute ſhe expected the fatal Summons to debarque.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saladine</hi> being withdrawn to his own Apartment, begun to ruminate on his miſerable Condition, he ſaw nothing before him but Miſery, yet 'twas ſome comfort to him to think he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd; but how ſhort was that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort! For he ſoon concluded his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition the worſe, that being advanc'd to ſo great a Happineſs he was in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be depriv'd of it for ever. When he perceiv'd the Weather grow fair, his Torture was doubled; he now lookt for the Embaſſadors from Shore that were ſent to receive her, and every thing he heard, he thought was they. He was not long deceiv'd, for upon the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151495:56"/>
ceaſing of the Storm, they who were appointed to attend her to the Court came Aboard, and now Spite of all his Afflictions he was conſtrain'd to meet 'em, and to give 'em the Honours that were due to their Characters.</p>
                  <p>When the Dying <hi>Nuberia,</hi> ſaw the fatal Meſſengers, 'tis inexpreſſible her Anguiſh and Dejection; ſhe look'd on 'em as they had been her Executioners, and ſhe had hardly Fortitude enough to ſupport her ſelf to receive their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: She ſhow'd ſo little Complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for the Errand they came upon, that the quick ſighted <hi>Philippians</hi> were at a loſs how to behave themſelves; but not daring to preſs beyond her Pleaſure, they withdrew to give her Time to prepare for her ſolemn Departure.</p>
                  <p>Tho' ſhe had been a great while arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for this unavoidable Neceſſity, yet again her Grief return'd, when ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd her loſt <hi>Saladine:</hi> She had but another Moment to ſee him, and that was to be ſpent in utmoſt Sorrow: But being reſolv'd to have her eternal Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, ſhe ſent privately for him, and he was conducted by the faithful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident to the laſt Scene of their Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>views: This Meeting, as it was the laſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151495:57"/>
of their Lives, ſo it was attended with the moſt deplorable Circumſtances: She now omitted nothing that cou'd aſſure him of that indearing Eſteem ſhe had of him, and taking a Bracelet from her Arm, put it upon his, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring him never to part with it till ſome happier Occaſion ſhou'd make her capable of ſending to him again: She hop'd one Day to make him better Acknowledgments, if ſhe had Strength enough to Survive this doleful Parting, and ending her Diſcourſe with Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of her everlaſting Friendſhip; ſhe gave way to that torrent of Tears which burſt from her delug'd Eyes.</p>
                  <p>The unhappy Lover receiv'd her Preſent with ſuch a dejected Air, as if it were only to put him in Mind of his eternal Miſery; but the Aſſurances ſhe made him of being eternally his Friend, was yet ſome ſmall Mitigation: He yet hoped the varieties of War might give him an occaſion of ſeeing her Country again, that he might hear how ſhe liv'd in her new Majeſty, and what Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances ſhe ſtill preſerv'd of him: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, he wou'd have thrown himſelf at her Feet to take his final Adieu, but ſhe rais'd him by the Hand, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151495:57"/>
him to take her once more into his Arms, as being the only Happineſs ſhe had now remaining for him. He preſt her lovely Boſom cloſe to his, and with a Groan that brought up his very Soul, he cry'd—farewel: She had but juſt Strength enough to eccho him, and with a fainting Voice ſhe reply'd— eternally Adieu. He then let fall his Arms, and turning away his Eyes, he ſtrove to hide that Weakneſs which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd him of any further Speech; and ſtaggering to the Door, he went he knew not whither. All Things being got ready for her departure, ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for't without asking any Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and without any further Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny entred her Pinnace; ſtill keeping her Eyes fixt on the expiring <hi>Saladine;</hi> and as the Veſſel bore her away to the fatal Shore, the unfortunate Lover gaz'd at her till he cou'd behold her no more.</p>
                  <p>Thus (my dear <hi>Brunet</hi>) you have the Story of that unfortunate Princeſs, which ſome time ago made a great Noiſe in that part of the World where it was acted: The beſt thing that can be ſaid of it, is, that it is true, and our
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151495:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Author has omitted all flouriſhes, to keep to Reality: The Princeſs of this Story is ſtill alive, and I am told, the royal <hi>Catolinus</hi> prov'd juſt a Bridegroom, as ſhe prophecy'd of him; but the poor <hi>Philippians</hi> were diſappointed in their Hopes of an Heir, for Heav'n has not Bleſt that Crown with any Iſſue from that renowned Woman, tho' they were Daily in expectation of one, which they hop'd to obtain thro' the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of their Friends in Heav'n, which were conſtantly ply'd to for that Purpoſe. And now I ſhall ſhut up my long Letter, without troubling you with any other Adventures, but I hope in few Months more to find you ſome other Diverſion, for I have made an Acquaintance in this Place which will furniſh me with all Occurrences that are worth hearing: Till then I releaſe you from any further importunity, and remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your moſt Devoted Friend,</hi> R—</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Cadiz</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Dec.</hi> 4th, 1694.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:151495:58"/>
                  <head>POSTCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>IF you intend to Honour me with any of yours, let 'em be directed for me here: The Method of this Poſt-Office is very extraordinary, and I can't miſs of any of your Favours, if you write between this and <hi>May.</hi> There's ſuch a Number of Strangers in this City, that 'twou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d be impoſſible to know eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man by his Name, or almoſt by the Place of his Dwelling; therefore the Officers of the Poſtage order their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs thus. When the Mail arrives, the Clerks write down the Number up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every Letter, from One perhaps to 1000, as many as there are, and then the Copy of the Names as they are Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcrib'd, is writ down on a Table kept for that Purpoſe, putting oppoſite to the Name the Number that lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Letter, and this Table always hangs in the Paſſage, where every one, who comes to inquire, looks if there be one for him, and if he finds his Name in the Alphabet of the Table, he takes notice of the Number, and goes in to the Clerk, who always attends for that end, and reporting his Number, his Letter is preſently found.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:151495:59"/>
               <head>LETTER II.</head>
               <p>NOW again I have got ſomething to entertain my dear <hi>Brunet</hi> with, but how agreable it may be to him, I am not poſitive to determine, tho' I have taken ſome Pains to find him Matter of Diverſion, and if I give him half ſo much Entertainment as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in furniſhing my ſelf with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures to pleaſe him, I ſhall think my Time and my Toil amply reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>As I told you in my laſt, I had now leiſure enough to make my Obſervation of every thing I ſaw and heard, and when I got leave to go Aſhore to <hi>Cales,</hi> which I inform'd you, were our Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Quarters, I dreſt my ſelf in the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of my own Country, and went to ſee ſome French Merchants I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to, who were very glad to receive me: And I ſo well pleas'd them with the Relation of my Undertaking, that I made my ſelf many good Friends among 'em. There are great Numbers of <hi>French</hi> over all this Kingdom, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151495:59"/>
I have been told that in <hi>Madrid</hi> alone there are Forty Thouſand, who follow their ſeveral Vocations, generally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the diſguiſe of <hi>Flemings.</hi> When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I had any curioſity to ſee the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of this Town, one or other of my Friends always accompany'd me, to protect me from the inſults of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who are very Inhoſpitable to Strangers: And where ever we went, I found our Countrymen well eſteem'd, notwithſtanding their national Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, for being accounted, as indeed they generally are, Wealthy, the Fame of ſuch a Character draws ſome Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the People.</p>
               <p>The City of <hi>Cadiz</hi> is a very ancient City, the Foundation of it having been laid by the <hi>Phoenicians:</hi> It is Situate on the Skirt of the Iſland, famous here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore for being the Habitation of <hi>Geryon,</hi> the Antagoniſt of <hi>Hercules,</hi> who is ſaid to have carry'd away the Herds of Cattle which graz'd in this Fruitful Paſture; and at this Day the Paſture is ſo rich, that Cattle will die of Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs within 30 Days, unleſs they be let Blood; and, to ſay true, the whole Province is ſo exuberantly Rich, that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151495:60"/>
in the Time of the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt Punick War, it was a Temptation to thoſe warlike Invaders to make War againſt it, which they did ſo ſucceſsfully, that all that part of <hi>Spain</hi> was Conquer'd by 'em, tho' after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Romans</hi> ſent their Armies hither againſt the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> and in proceſs of Time the <hi>African Scipio</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd it, and made it an Appendix of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. This Iſland by <hi>Mariana</hi>'s Account was formerly 700 Paces from the Continent, and had 300 Leagues circumference: What he means by ſo extravagant a Meaſure, is beyond my Apprehenſion, for tho' I have often Pac d it round to examine if there were any Footſteps of ſo unlikely a Compaſs, I cou'd never find 'em, for at this Day it is no more than 3 Leagues about, and the River that parts it from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent is ſo narrow, that a Bridge of 6 Arches ſtrides it over. But as to the Situation of the Land, every School-Boy knows, <hi>Hercules</hi> concluded his Ramble here, and left his Name to thoſe Two great Hills <hi>Calpe</hi> and <hi>Abyla,</hi> which front each other from <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> which are to this Day, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151495:60"/>
will be to all Poſterity called his Pillars, as if he had erected 'em for the Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries of his Conqueſt. It was many Years afterwards the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs Gaditana</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and, one of their Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines for furniſhing their Tranſports in their Maritime Expeditions. The City is not extraordinary large, but ſo full of People, that no Habitation in the World can boaſt of greater Numbers, and for Magnificence of Churches, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents and private Houſes, neither <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> nor <hi>London, Germany</hi> or <hi>Italy</hi> can out go it: The Fortifications are not the beſt that I have ſeen, for all the backſide which fronts the Southward, is naked; but on the Angle they have built a ſmall Fort into the Sea, which they call St. <hi>Sebaſtians,</hi> and in time of War it may ſerve to prevent a deſcent on that Quarter: But the front which looks upon the Bay is well walled, and mounted with good ſtore of fine Braſs Cannon, and ſerves for the Evening Walk of the Merchants and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. Higher up towards the Bay is a Neck of Land which runs like an Iſthmus between the two Seas, lately Fortify'd, and indeed I think,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151495:61"/>
impregnable, and they have good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to guard that Place well, for it was on that Side the famous Deſcent was made by the Engliſh Generals, <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and <hi>Rawleigh,</hi> who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in one Day they Sackt this wealthy City, and laid it in Aſhes. A Mile without theſe Works ſtands the Caſtle of <hi>Puntal,</hi> a ſmall well built Garriſon, but ill Arm'd, and more negligently Guarded: For I don't know what uſe they make of it, but to lay up the Plate and Mony, which, contrary to the Statutes of their Country, they provide for the <hi>Genoeſes,</hi> and other Ships which come here for that Purpoſe; and from hence to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey it aboard. 'Tis true this Caſtle, and the other oppoſite to't on the other ſide of the Bay, made ſome reſiſtance when <hi>Eſſex</hi> invaded 'em, but it was ſo ſmall, that he was not twelve Hours in gaining 'em, and in beating the Garriſon out: The other that I nam'd is built on purpoſe to Countenance this, and to oppoſe the Paſſage of an Enemy into the Creeks, and not being above a Cannon Shot aſunder, it wou'd prove hard for a Man of War to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em, if they were well Mann'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:151495:61"/>Within the City I obſerv'd no regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Militia, only a Muſter of a few rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Rogues, which don't deſerve the Name of a Regiment, for neither Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment nor Diſcipline appears among 'em, yet theſe Raſcals are ſo Inſolent, that a Stranger wou'd be in danger of his Life if he ſhou'd refuſe to give the moſt beggarly among 'em the Wall and the Salute. They have three Gates, which are open'd and ſhut every Morning and Evening, each of 'em guarded with the Officers of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, and I think they make little uſe of 'em but to that purpoſe, nor that neither effectually, for nothing here is more common, than to run Goods aſhore, and carry Mony out, either by Stratagem, or the Connivance of the Officers: At the Sounding of the Orai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Bell theſe Gates are all ſhut, and the Keys carry'd to the Governor, and upon no Terms to be deliver'd out again, unleſs on very important Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities. The firſt and principal is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Puerta de la Sevilla,</hi> becauſe the Boats which Trade between <hi>Sevil</hi> and this City lie before it; the Second is called <hi>Puerta de la Mar,</hi> becauſe here
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151495:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Captains and Maſters of Ships ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally come a Shore; and the third <hi>Puerta de la Tierra,</hi> becauſe it is the Key which opens to the Iſland: But ſince I have mention'd the Oration, give me leave to acquaint you, That the cuſtom of the Evening Prayer is here perform'd with wonderful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; not but that I know 'tis in all Catholick Countries obſerv'd leſs or more; but here it is done with ſo much ſeverity, that not one Perſon, be who he will, who is at that time in the Streets, tho' the weather be never ſo dirty, but falls down on his Knees in the very place where he ſtood, and in that Poſture gives up his Thanksgivings for the Mercies of the Day: And ſurely there is in this cuſtom, an exceeding ſhow of Piety not to be met with among our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reformers, thoſe zealots who have elop'd from the Church, and now ſet up for Chriſtians more Spiritualiz'd than we. It was no ſmall pleaſure to me (My Dear <hi>Brunet</hi>) to ſee thoſe obſtinate Hereticks obey this cuſtom of falling down on their Knees at the call of a Catholick Signal, and bemire their
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151495:62"/>
lac'd Coats to conform with a Religion they ſo much rail againſt; but 'twas their Fear of being knockt on the Head, and not their Devotion, which made 'em comply, and they were ſo much in the right on't as to ſave their Bones, tho' they ventur'd at what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves call Idolatry, as indeed they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly call moſt of our Devotions. Soon as this is over, the City is on all Sides ſhut in, and 'tis then impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to get out, and this is the only Face of a Garriſon which I cou'd ſee among 'em.</p>
               <p>'Tis almoſt incredible the Opulence and Traffick of this City, there's ſcarce a Nation upon Earth that has not ſent ſome of its Natives to Trade here; and among theſe there's ſuch Diverſity and Confuſion of Habits and Languages, that at high Change, which is always at Eleven in the Morning, the Scene looks like an Opera, and the Eye is filled with Show and Figure. But 'tis a ſtrange Thing to conſider, that among ſuch Crowds of all Countries, there is hardly one <hi>Spaniard</hi> to be ſeen, theſe are ſo Lazy, or ſo Proud, that they give 'emſelves no manner of Exerciſe,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151495:63"/>
for they had rather Starve than Work: If they had not the beſt Country in the World, their Condition wou'd be very Miſerable, and as it is, they can but barely Live, for notwithſtanding their Oſtentation, there's the Curſe of Poverty in all their Families. At the time of Exchange one may ſee ſome of all the Kingdoms of the Earth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiating their private Affairs, which are moſtly levelled againſt the Intereſt of <hi>Spain;</hi> ſo that when I conſider'd this ſtrange Medley, I cou'd not chuſe but commend what I had once in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſeen of a Picture, which ſhow'd the King of <hi>Spain</hi> lolling on a Table cover'd with Pieces of Eight, with the King of <hi>England</hi> and the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> on each Hand, raking from under his Arms the ſhining Metal; the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noeſes</hi> behind his Chair making Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maces at him, and the King of <hi>France</hi> ſnatching it before his Face, whether he wou'd or no: And indeed 'tis lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally true, for all Nations prey upon him, and either by Wile or Force get moſt of his Treaſure out of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. How ſhou'd it elſe be? For there's not another Kingdom in <hi>Europe</hi> has any
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151495:63"/>
Mines of its own, and tho' the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> have a ſmall Trade with <hi>Guinea,</hi> and bring ſometimes Duſt from thence; yet that is ſo ſmall a Parcel of the Riches of both Countries, that it muſt be confeſt, the Body of their Treaſure muſt come from hence, and ſo be diſperſt thro' all Parts of the World, to the utter Subverſion of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Power: And were it not for their Poſſeſſions which they ſtill hold in <hi>America,</hi> they wou'd inevitably fall before every Prince that cou'd draw an Army againſt 'em, and be reduc'd to Nothing. But to return to <hi>Cadiz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Goverment of the City is in the Hands, firſt of the Government, and next to him of the Alcalde; the firſt is for the Regulation of the Military, as the latter of the Civil Affairs; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe Two are frequent Diſputes about Prerogatives, which are general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determin'd in Favour of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who has a Power (ſuch as it is) to awe and intimidate the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, who in ſo deprav'd a Reign may complain of the Uſurpation of his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val to no Purpoſe in the World: At our firſt Arrival <hi>Don Pedro de Velaſco</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:151495:64"/>
was Governour, who was afterwards preſented to the Viceroyate of <hi>Catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia;</hi> a Man ſuppos'd to be in the Intereſts of <hi>France,</hi> and ſupported by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Father, who is Conſtable of Caſtile, and one of the prime Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State: The Conduct of this Governour was highly Cenſur'd when Admiral <hi>Tourvile</hi> lay before this Place; for as it is reported, there was a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Correſpondence between 'em, and the Governor openly regal'd him with ſeveral great Preſents, to Bribe him from any Hoſtilities, and to gain the good Will of the <hi>French</hi> Merchants, who were not wanting to reward him.</p>
               <p>Here is an excellent Market for Fiſh and Fruit; but as for Meat, I have ſeen more on one Butchers Stall in <hi>London,</hi> than in all the Shambles here: All manner of tame and wild Fowl are ſcarce, tho' I have ſometimes ſeen of both Sorts exceeding good, but in no plentiful manner, for theſe are Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall'd before they come to Market, and they who can't go to the Price of 'em, muſt Feaſt on Herbs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or eat their Fiſh as their Daily Food, and thank God for Bleſſing 'em with the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151495:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the Sea. Their Pork indeed is the beſt in the World, but their Mutton, Beef and Veal the worſt; for whatever becomes of all their Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, there is little to be found of 'em in their Markets; and even that that is, is ſo ſtrangely mamockt in the cutting up, that with that, and the beating of the Sun all Day upon't, it looks like Carrion. To ſum up all in a word, nothing can ſhow more Sumptuous than the outſide of their Houſes; and nothing more Beggarly than their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty within.</p>
               <p>Some Months after our arrival, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Viſits were made between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> General, and the Governour, but if you were to ſee the gaudy Pomp of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> when he puts on all his gallantry for a Viſit, you wou'd think your ſelf in the Holiday Show of ſome overgrown Citizen, when the Pedler puts of his blue Apron to ſtrut along in Silks and Ribbons. Certainly nothing can be more Ridiculous than this Pageantry, and yet you may as well perſwade 'em that they're not the Ancieneſt People of the Creation, as that they're not the moſt accompliſht in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151495:65"/>
Breeding and Gallantry. The height of their Mode is but to mimick the <hi>French</hi> in their Garb; and you know they do this to ſuch a pitch of Deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it is become a Proverb, when we wou'd ſpeak of any Body very awkard, to ſay, <hi>He looks like a Spaniard in a French dreſs.</hi> To mention the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> tho' they are our Apes as well as they, yet they wear their Cloathes with a tolerable good grace, and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſullen Air which is inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from all Northern People, they come neareſt us of any of our Neighbours.</p>
               <p>Whenever the General made his Viſit, he went attended with the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his Officers, as there are many among 'em fine Gentlemen. Once there was a ſolemn Invitation, from his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency a Shore, to hls Excellency a Board, to an Entertainment at his Houſe; the chief Diverſion was to be a Comedy, and to this Invitation, the General went with the beſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance he cou'd make; and indeed the proceſſion was Magnificent beyond what is commonly ſeen here: For as the General Landed, the Governour in his own Perſon received him at the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151495:65"/>
ſide, and led him to his Houſe, between his Guards and the Soldiers (if I may ſo call them) of the Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, with ſuch Muſick as the place afforded, and a general diſcharge of Cannon: At his Houſe he was regal'd after a handſom manner, and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy Acted to the beſt advantage they cou'd, which yet was very mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable: When the General came away, he left a large Munificence behind him, which conſiſted of Sixty Piſtoles for the Comedians, and Sixty more for the Governours Servants. This libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the General, made a great noiſe, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ever after expreſt a high Opinion of his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, and began to treat the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with more reſpect.</p>
               <p>Without queſtion, their Comedies (as they call 'em, for they have hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any diſtinction between Comedy and Tragedy) are the vileſt things on Earth, and can be out done by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ſcandalous manner they Act 'em in, and the pitiful Decoration of their Stage: You who are a Critick in theſe Studies, may judge what they
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151495:66"/>
are, when I have told you, that in three Days time they can patch up a Play, even in verſe, for they are all in Rime, and get it Acted in three more, but after ſuch a barbarous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as wou'd ſooner raiſe your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt than your Diverſion: I have heard that the Famous <hi>Calderon</hi> ſeldom took more time; and tho' his are the moſt correct of any in the Language, yet if they were brought on the <hi>French</hi> Stage, the Audience wou'd think the Poet out of his Wits, and a Ballad Sung in a Country Market a better jeſt: As for their Scenes and Ornaments, a Mountebanks Scaffold is an illuſtrious contrivance to 'em: Two or three dirty Blankets pin'd acroſs the Stage, ſerves for the Curtain, that is, The flat Scene before which they Act, and when they have any thing to ſhow behind that, they draw the Wollen Scene, and then the Audience may ſuppoſe what they will: One wou'd think they ſhou'd be aſham'd of Day light, they Play in ſuch abominable Habits, and yet they never uſe Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, but ſtand in full view of the Sun, and defie the Devil and the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151495:66"/>
Critick. My Friend, Even in theſe trifles we may obſerve the diſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude between this Country and all others, for I think 'em altogether and in every thing the moſt contrary Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on Earth.</p>
               <p>And as if theſe People had contriv'd on purpoſe to be oppoſite to all the World beſide, they erect their Boxes juſt where our Galleries ſtand, and the Pit which with us is taken up only by the Gentry, is with them proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted to the Vulgar at the Price of about a Teſter: But with this remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able difference, That the Benches are lockt up, like the Pews in Proteſtant Churches, ſometimes purchaſed by particular Families, but generally to be open<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to every Scoundrel who ſtarves a Dinner to treat himſelf with Sixpeny worth of the Play. As to the Boxes, they are built on high from each ſide of the Stage to the end of the Houſe, not near ſo commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly as our Galleries; and the charge of one of them amounts to about Twelve Shillings, and that finds room for half a dozen: But for the moſt part, theſe boxes belong to ſuch and ſuch
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151495:67"/>
Houſes of Quality; and as we ſay, <hi>This is the King's Box,</hi> &amp;c. They ſay, <hi>This is ſuch a Ones, and this is ſuch a Ones</hi>— But when any of them are not taken up by the Owners, the Box-keepers make Money of them to others.</p>
               <p>Another Bar beſides the ſituation, to render theſe Boxes more inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, are, the Grates which they always put before 'em. This Cuſtom ariſes from the Care the Women take, or the Men for 'em, that they ſhan't be ſeen; and becauſe they muſt deprive others from ſeeing them, they deprive themſelves of ſeeing the Play.</p>
               <p>One of the Plays which I was at, invited me there by the curioſity of the Title; it was the Story of the <hi>Engliſh Earl of</hi> Eſſex, <hi>and Qneen</hi> Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth; which becauſe I had read both in <hi>French</hi> and in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to ſee what they made of it in <hi>Spaniſh;</hi> and to be ingenious, I cou'd not chuſe but be extreamly Scandaliz'd at the Character which they make of that Princeſs; for ſhe is there repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as the blackeſt and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Monſter in Nature, a Tyrant, Homicide, an Uſurper, Baſtard and a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151495:67"/>
Witch: And even out of the Play-Houſe, the People have the ſame Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Her; and which is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, I have heard a well read Gentleman, but hot and zealous, affirm, That ſhe was contracted to the Devil, and that ſhe was branded with a great black Beard, which made Her hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to behold.</p>
               <p>When I conſider'd this, I found theſe Impreſſions are convey'd to the Laity by the Artifices of the Prieſts, to give 'em an invincible abhorrence of thoſe they call Hereticks, and tho' nothing is more evident, than that this is as Lye, yet the common People are ſo tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of what the Church tells 'em. That they'll ſooner quarrel in defence of ſuch a falſhood, than admit of any Conviction. I ſaw ſeveral other of their Plays, but as they are crampt into ſhort Verſes, and the ſence very much pincht in for the ſake of the Rhimes, ſo I was ſometimes puzzled to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand 'em; in the main, I believe, there may be Wit in ſome of 'em, or elſe the People are eaſily provok'd to Laughter and Admiration; for their Applauſes are often expreſt by crying,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151495:68"/>
                  <hi>Vita, Vita,</hi> which is contracted out of <hi>Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> a Word that ſignifies their good Lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Satisfaction: I obſerv'd in moſt of their Plays that they are very happy in what we commonly fail, and that is, in the Oeconomy of the Fable: Their Plots are neither ſo intricate as to confound, nor ſo tranſparent as to be ſeen thro', but ſubſtantial, clear and ſurprizing: Their Verſe is every Firſt and Fourth, and Second and Third; and their Acts, which they call <hi>Jornadas,</hi> are never more than Three, only at the end of each, they bring in a ſcurrilous Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude of Farce and Nonſence, diſgrac'd with a Guittar and Harp, to make the Rabble Laugh.</p>
               <p>I ſhan't delay you with any more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks of this Place, I have already too far Tranſgreſt, for indeed there can be but little Pleaſure, either in Writing or Reading any Thing that can be ſaid on ſuch a wretched Subject. Give me leave only to add, that this Country is intolerably Hot, which makes good what one ſaid of Hell, that if he were to place it in <hi>Africa, Libya</hi> ſhou'd be his Choice, but if in <hi>Europe,</hi> no Place ſo fit as <hi>Spain</hi> for the burning Manſion.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151495:68"/>
This extremity of Heat is the Reaſon, that from Twelve to Four in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, every Body goes to what they call their <hi>Ceſto,</hi> that is, <hi>to Sleep,</hi> and the Streets for that time are as ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent as at Midnight, and no greater ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of a Trade than if it were the Sabboth; ſo that when the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who were not accuſtom'd to Sleep at ſuch Hours, wou'd be about the Streets, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> made a by-Word of 'em, and ſaid that at ſuch a time nothing but Engliſh-men and Dogs walkt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
               <p>But now I have been mortifying you with theſe heavy Complaints, let me try if I can lighten your Spleen a little with ſomething more reliſhing: As you are a Friend to a Bottle and an Intrigue, you can't chuſe but be pleas'd with the Converſation of ſome honeſt jolly Friars that are here: Thoſe of <hi>Spain</hi> are commonly more Temperate than the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> yet more than the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and indeed that's no Wonder, for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> can hardly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any Nation that excells 'em in all manner of Lewdneſs: Here are in this City of all Countrys ſome, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151495:69"/>
of all Orders, from the <hi>ſtately Caſtilian,</hi> down to the <hi>humble Iriſh-man,</hi> and from the proud <hi>Jeſuit</hi> to the lowſy <hi>Capuchin:</hi> The Clergy are ſo numerous and ſo Rich, that I have been faithfully told, near a third Part of this well Built City is in their Poſſeſſion, either given 'em by pious Legacies, or purchaſt with ready Mony: Beſides ſome fourteen Convents of Monks and Nuns, there's a Hoſpital called, St. <hi>Juan de Dios,</hi> which is maintained with the Profits of the Play-Houſe, the Stage being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicted, unleſs it pays (as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) about 2 thirds of their Daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt to its maintenance: The Occaſion of this heavy Tax on the Theatre, was the reſult of the Buſtle which the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Jeſuits made to get it ſuppreſt: The Story is very Famous under the Name of <hi>Pedro de Guzman,</hi> a zealous Churchman, who wrote a Book, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he vilifies the Stage, ſeeming to be much ſcandaliz'd at its Impiety, and giving it all the Opprobrious Terms he cou'd gather out of the diſcontented Fathers; and concludes, that it is equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Shameful to the Catholick Religion, to bear with this (which he calls) Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151495:69"/>
Lewdneſs, as to ſuffer the Bull-Feaſts, which gave it at all times ſuch infinite Scandal. The Latter is a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom which they derive from the Moors, who once Inhabited their Country, and was among other Sports, in mixture with a deal of groſs Superſtition, left to theſe <hi>Spaniards</hi> their Succeſſors after they were expelled <hi>Spain,</hi> and which are ſtill highly prevailing at this Day: I ſhan't go about to deſcribe this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Sport, it being already done by every Author who has writ any Thing of the Country; only I ſhall tell you, that once I had the Curioſity to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at one of 'em, ar which Time I ſaw 33 Bulls cut down, and macerated alive one by one, by theſe inhumane Butchers. Tho' I found much Cruelty in this kind of Paſtime, yet I cou'd not chuſe but be diverted with the Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in amuſing and ſhunning thoſe fierce Creatures: The Bulls which are deſign'd for the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice are all manag'd, for they are kept wild, and for ſome time before the Day of Sport, ſhut up in Darkneſs, to render 'em more Furious when they are let out into the Light and the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151495:70"/>
Crowd: The Combatants of this Day were ſome Gentlemen, whoſe Relations had been formerly Foil'd by the Bulls, and then lying under (what they call) an <hi>Impena,</hi> to revenge the Diſgrace, which is a Puntilio of Honour they never fail to obſerves: They came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Liſts, dreſt up like Morriſ-Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Riding upon Mules, as fine as themſelves; and one after another, they ran their Courſe: This <hi>Impena</hi> (if I call it right) is reckon'd a Diſgrace of the higheſt Degree, if any Cavalier comes off without Killing his Bull, tho' he himſelf be Wounded, or perhaps Kill'd, as it ſometimes happens, there lies an Infamy on that Family, till ſome other Branch of it takes off the Attainder, by Slaying one of the Sava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with his own Hand, which at laſt, tho' perhaps with the Sacrifice of moſt of the Family, they never fail to do. Theſe Gentlemen were reputed great Dabs at the Game, and ſo they prov'd, for by one Shift or other, they all came off unhurt, having redeem'd the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of their Friends, and acquir'd to themſelves univerſal Applauſe. But on theſe Holidays of Bull-Fighting, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151495:70"/>
Fellow gets ready his Dart or his Spear, and with that in one Hand, and his Cloak in t'other, he Wounds the Bull, and defends himſelf; for as ſoon as he ſtrikes, he throws his Cloak about his Eyes, which catching on his Horns, muffles him, and gives the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailant an opportunity of Eſcaping.</p>
               <p>This dexterity of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> makes all Strangers wonder: Among the reſt there was a drunken <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sailor, who was extremely pleas'd with the Sport, and was reſolv'd to take a run himſelf; he thought himſelf as good a Man as the beſt of 'em, and why ſhou'd not he ſhow his Courage as well as they? It happen'd immediately that there was a fierce Bull turn'd out, and now was the time to ſhew himſelf: Out then he ſteps into the Liſts, with nothing in his Hand but his little Hat, which was not much bigger than one of the Bulls Eyes, and in a daring manner waits for his running at him: Soon as the roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaſt ſaw him, he ran furiouſly towards him, and there being no Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy elſe in the Liſts, the Sailor muſt now make the beſt of a bad Market; the poor Fellow ſtill ſtood his Ground,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151495:71"/>
and when the Bull came near him, he try'd to amuſe him with his Hat, as he had ſeen the <hi>Spaniards</hi> do with their Cloaks, and throwing it between his Horns, it ſignify'd as much as if he had held his Hand againſt a Thunderbolt, for down he came upon his Back, with his Face to the Bulls, one of the Bulls Feet on his Stomach, and one of his Horns thro' his Cheek and out at his Mouth.</p>
               <p>One wou'd have thought theſe Braves that ſaw him, ſhou'd have run in to his Reſcue, but not one of 'em ſtirred, tho' the defeated Hero lay every Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment expecting Death; till of his own accord the generous Beaſt got out his Horn, and as if he had been ſenſible of his Conqueſt, left him on the Ground, and walkt on as if he were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd with his Victory. Soon as the Bull quitted him, then they run Races who ſhou'd firſt ſee if he were living, and finding no other hurt about him but that of his Cheek, he was carryed to the Hoſpital, and ſoon afterwards Cured.</p>
               <p>If you have the Curioſity to ask on what Occaſion theſe Bull-Feaſts are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151495:71"/>
made, take this Account which was given me of that which I was at. The Duke of <hi>Medina Sidonia,</hi> Captain General of <hi>Andaluzia,</hi> had a Son at the point of Death; his Life being given up by the Phyſicians, the Duke had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Prayers of the Church, as his laſt Remedy; and particularly addreſt a Monaſtery of <hi>Auguſtines</hi> in the Town where he Dwelt, to offer up their Interceſſion for him: In ſome Time after the Gentleman recover'd: and the glad Father, thinking his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery had been an effect of the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Convent, preſented it with theſe 33 Bulls, to be firſt Baited for publick Diverſion, and as a Token of his Gratitude, their Carcaſſes to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to the Holy Fathers.</p>
               <p>This is not always the Reaſon of 'em, for ſometimes the King, or ſome Grandee, entertains Embaſſadors with them, before the royal Palace at <hi>Madrid;</hi> or, for want of a better Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſometimes the Mob: When ever the latter happens, it is done to pacifie their Clamours, for they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Mutinous in a Time of Scarcity, and then the King appoints 'em a Bull-Feaſt,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151495:72"/>
which is both Sport and Supply to 'em. Tho' generally this is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd here with Circumſtances of great Oſtentation, yet in <hi>Barbary</hi> they have 'em in ten times more Splendour. Thoſe <hi>African</hi> People being lovers of all ſorts of Cruelty, and not to be pleas'd but with ſuch ſavage Diverſions. But ſo much for their publick Sports—I cou'd now make you merry with another kind of Gallantry very much in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice among theſe <hi>Spaniards;</hi> I mean that of Pimping and Intriguing: And tho' theſe two Excellencies are chiefly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing among the Laity, yet to give the Church its due, the Clergy are very dextrous at any thing wherein a Woman is concern'd.</p>
               <p>But ſince I have mention'd the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Clergy, let me not traduce 'em without entring their Convents and Chapels, and examine what ſort of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Devotion they practiſe; and I can aſſure my Friend whoever ſees 'em in their cells, tho' they are zealous pretenders, and carry to the World ſuch a Face of Auſterity, will find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than Mortification among 'em.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:151495:72"/>Conſider, My Friend, I am not ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all that are in Religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, God forbid I ſhou'd accuſe ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn a Life with general Prophannes: No <hi>Brunet,</hi> I have a profound Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for that Monaſtick Holineſs which inſpires the greateſt part of 'em; but yet as in all other Societies, there are even among theſe, ſome Corrupt Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers which ſhame the Sanctity of our moſt Holy Communion, and are Weeds that ought to be torn from the Earth, and Rooted out from the Churches of the Faithful: I am now ſpeaking of thoſe abandon'd Hypocrites, who have other ſecret Cauſes for their entring into holy Orders, than Contrition and Repentance. That there are ſuch, every Age hath inform'd us, and every Convent, or there wou'd be a little work for publick Scandal, or for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and ſuch ſevere Chaſtiſemenas as are often exerciſed in 'em. It was my Fortune to be acquainted with ſome of theſe we are now ſpeaking of, Brave Fellows, My Friend, Men who wou'd ſtick at nothing to gratifie their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, or to ſerve a Companion. If a Husband or a Brother be in the way,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151495:73"/>
they have devices to remove 'em, and ſuch ſubtil Stratagems as will hardly admit of Oppoſition: That what I ſay is true, every <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Officer that's here will bear me witneſs; for there's hardly a Gentleman in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy that loves an Intrigue, and can part with his Money, but has been helpt by one Friar or other of his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Tho' I am very much ſcandaliz'd at ſo great an infamy, which gives oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to our Adverſaries to reproach us; yet in ſpite of all ſhame 'tis an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute truth, and ſo much the more deplorable.</p>
               <p>It may well be anſwer'd, if it ſhou'd be ask'd how theſe Vermin have a knack at Pimping above any other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that by the power they have when they receive the confeſſions, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover who are Corrupt; and having known that the reſt is eaſy. And that theſe Villains are ſometimes as ſucceſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Debauching innocent Maids, as they are in continuing the pollutions of others already Defil'd, has been no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly prov'd by Examples, that have occur'd to my particular knowledge; and the reaſon is plain, why the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151495:73"/>
is more miſcheivious that way, becauſe the doors of every Family lie open to them, and that reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which Parents uſe in guarding their Children from all the World beſide, is put by at the approaches of a Prieſt, who, wherever he comes, is as familiar as if he were one of the Domeſticks. The liberty which they thus aſſume, as it is the particular priviledge of the Church, ſo it is very ſerviceable to 'em in their Deſigns of every kind, but principally to inſinuate for Alms and Benevolences, in which they are ſo dextrous, that 'tis a hard matter to avoid 'em: For beſides the Artifices they uſe by fair means, they have always the neceſſities of the Church to pretend, and when good words won't do, they have a Purgatory and Damnation to awe the unknowing Vulgar. I wou'd not ſay this of the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy if I did not know it to be litterally true; for as I wou'd be thought impartial in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks of every thing I undertake to Relate; ſo in this particular I woud ſhun all detraction, and cover as much as I cou'd the nudities of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Communion; but to deal plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151495:74"/>
with a Friend, I found within theſe holy Societies very much Corruption and Degeneracy; I found Abſtinence and Chaſtity, which are their Principal vows, no more than nominal Vertues, but I ſaw every where an egregious abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Slothfulneſs and Luxury, with a diſguiſe of Hypocriſy to cover it, and to keep up the reputation of the Cloyſter. I ſay not this univerſally of Religious Orders, it were pity if this ſhou'd be generally true of theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſes; without queſtion, there are multitudes of Saints among 'em; but granting that, yet 'tis beyond all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy true, that they have extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly degenerated from their firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and inſtead of giving themſelves up to Works of Piety, and the ſtudy of the ſacred Scriptures, as their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Fathers did, they are ſunk down into a Lethargy of Ignorance and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity.</p>
               <p>I believe, my Friend, it wou'd not be very difficult to find a reaſon for this Apoſtacy, when we conſider, how eaſily they give admiſſion to every lazy indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Wretch that can give little or no Account of his Faith, taking the ſacred
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151495:74"/>
Habit only to skreen him againſt the Gripes of Poverty, and the injuries of Fortune. But one wou'd think, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, that among ſo many idle People, who have nothing to mind but their Prayers and their Study, that there ſhou'd not be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhow of Learning, not to mention any thing elſe; but let <hi>Brunet</hi> believe what I now tell him, that in all the Converſation I have had with 'em, I ſcarce met with one in twenty, that had any other Language than that he was born with; or at the beſt, if his Practice at the Altar had furniſh't him with ſome looſe Fragments of Latin, it was commonly no more than wou'd ſerve to ask me what Country-Man I was, or to tell me how many Maſſes are ſaid in a Day: Not but that there are ſome of 'em great Maſters, but theſe are ſo few, that a Traveller may weary out his Patience, before he can meet with one who can ſatisfie his Curioſity in any queſtion of importance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:151495:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>The Jeſuits are the only Order by whom the more polite Studies are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd; of theſe indeed there are many great Criticks in all manner of Sciences, and 'tis with which Wiſdom, that they are appointed the Miſſionaries to go Abroad, for the firſt thing they ſtudy, is Humanity, and that in the chief place fits 'em for theſe wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Expeditions which they are ſent upon into the parts of the World. Beſides this, they are perfect Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in all the parts of the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, than which nothing can be more neceſſary for the converſion of the Eaſtern Nations, who are extreamly bigotted to Augury and the ſtudy of the Stars.</p>
               <p>The Method which theſe cunning People have to recruite their Order with a ſucceſſion of ingenious Men, is very remarkable; for in all Countries where they are, they ingroſs to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Education of all the Youth, and when they find a Boy of a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpritely wit, as it's eaſy out of ſometimes a Thouſand, as I have known
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151495:75"/>
in one School, they ſecure him to themſelves, and bring him up to their Order. By theſe means they never want a ſupply of able Men to carry on their Deſigns, and to preſerve their Superiority over every other fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>At this time I was recommended to make a Journey to a Monaſtery of Carthuſians, diſtant ſome four Leagues from hence: My company was a <hi>French</hi> Merchant and a Religious of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance; ſo croſſing the Bay, we rid it in two Hours, but after ſuch a barbarous manner, that as bad as I love walking, it had been much for the advantage of my Bones, if I had footed it thro' all the bad ways.</p>
               <p>Our Mules (for here are rarely any Horſes) were ſome of them which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ply at the landing Place, cover'd with Packſaddles inſtead of Padſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and Rein'd with Halters inſtead of Bridles. The ſeats of theſe Saddles are as flat as a Cuſhion, but not half ſo ſoft; and the fall on each ſide
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151495:76"/>
ſtretcht out ſo wide, that 'tis as bad as the rack to ſit on 'em: And to all this the ſawcy Muleteer, tho' there be but the Tail to ride on, will be ſure to be up behind you, if you don't out gallop him, or threaten him with more than bare words. In this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we went, and when we came with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſight of the Monaſtery, we diſmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, giving our Mules in charge to the Owners, who footed it as faſt as we rid. Here we took out a Bottle, and ſome Proviſion, and what was remaining after we had done, we ſent to our Jockeys; but the proud <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> tho' they were ready to ſtarve for Victuals, refus'd our leavings, and ſent us back in anſwer, That if we thought 'em not good enough to ſit down with us, they thought 'emſelves too good to take up with our Orts.</p>
               <p>This was Demonſtration beyond whatever I had heard of the Pride of theſe raſcally Peaſants; but indeed in every thing elſe that we had to do with 'em, we found 'em always the ſame</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:151495:76"/>We entred the Monaſtery, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I was mightily ſmitten with this ſuperb Building, I can hardly forbear you giving its Deſcription. I was ſo delighted with every thing I ſaw, that tho' I had ſeen that in <hi>Lyons</hi> which is juſtly counted the fineſt in <hi>France,</hi> I cou'd not ſuffer any compariſon between this and that, neither in the Archite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture nor Decoration.</p>
               <p>Thro'out the World the Houſes of this order are the moſt Magnificent of any and as much as they out-do all others, ſo much does this exceed all that I had ſeen of the ſame Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The reaſon of this grandeur is evident, for they admit none into their Habit, but Perſons of the higheſt Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who generally bring all, or the beſt part of their Eſtates in along with 'em, and dedicate 'em to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery. This which we now ſpeak of has ſuch prodigious Revenues, that in a Year of ſcarcity, in the City of <hi>Cales,</hi> they undertook to ſupply that populous place with Proviſion of all kinds for Twelve Months out of their
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151495:77"/>
own Magazines. The number of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Houſe was Originally li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to Thirty Three, but at this time, there were no more than Eighteen; and we were inform'd, there ſeldom are more, becauſe of the rigid and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable ſeverities of their Vows. We were likewiſe told, that when it was firſt Erected, the reputation of the Houſe brought from all parts of the Kingdom, ſuch as offered 'emſelves to it; but when they had a while groan'd under the rigours they were forc't to obſerve, they were no longer able to indure 'em; and becauſe there was no returning to the World, they ſent 'emſelves down to Hell by deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and violent Deaths.</p>
               <p>For five Days of the Week they are deny'd all Converſation, or ſo much as the ſight of one another, only Tueſdays and Thurſdays in the Afternoon they enjoy for their Relaxation, and 'tis upon theſe Days the Houſe is open for Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to ſee: When we went in, we met with ſome of the Fathers coming out, they ſurpriz'd us e're we expected 'em, and I confeſs, I was never ſo terrify'd
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151495:77"/>
with the ſight of human Creatures before. In their Faces they bear ſuch marks of Auſterity, and ſuch Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that to them who are affected with Solitude and Contemplation noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cou'd be more moving. We were carry'd by our Guide to the apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Procurador,</hi> and he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd us very curteouſly with Wine, Oranges and Citrons, which grew in his own Garden. He had two Rooms to himſelf, as they all have, one for his Study and Refection, the other for his Dormitory. They eat nothing but Fiſh, but of that they have ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety, that they never want change ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of what they are to eat, or the manner of dreſſing it: In the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Garden we ſaw a Fountain full of tame Carps, which at the call of the Feeder, wou'd put their Mouths above Water, and take their food from his Hand. The Duke of <hi>Medina Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> has a little Houſe Built within the Walls, where he lies when he comes to his Devotion, tho he lives a good way off; invited here, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151495:78"/>
by the Healthfulneſs of the Air, and the Beauty of the Monaſtery.</p>
               <p>I cou'd ſay much more of this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Structure, for on ſuch a pleaſant Subject, 'tis harder to ſay little than a great deal; but I conſider, that I have been already too prolix, and becauſe here I found the beſt retirement, I took an afternoon to my ſelf, to peice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether my Prayers, and to fit 'em up to what you ſee they are. Therefore i'le ſhut up this Letter, only putting you in mind, that you are indebted now two to me, who am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours, <hi>R. R.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>January,</hi> 12th. 94.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:151495:78"/>
               <head>LETTER III.</head>
               <p>I Make haſt to back my Second Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with a miſcellany of Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which I made after my return from <hi>Xeres,</hi> becauſe I wou'd not be thought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> idle, or forgetful of my Duty. And the firſt remark that occur'd, was that of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> manner of Eating, and dreſſing their Meat: And certainly no People upon Earth enjoy 'emſelves ſo little in their Appetites. Whether their Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance be the cauſe of their ill Cookery, or their ill Cookery the cauſe of their Temperance, is a Queſtion; for as the firſt is a Quality they value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon, ſo the latter is a ſhameful Truth, for in all my Life, I never ſaw ſuch Mammock and Sluttery. Not that what they eat is in it ſelf offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, but between the Butcher and the Cook 'tis ſo miſerably handled, that our Priſons wou'd hardly receive it: And yet 'tis a thing impoſible to perſwade a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that they are not
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151495:79"/>
the only Nation in the World that knows how to eat well; if you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him his Safron, he tells you, 'tis Savory; if you find fault with his Oyl, he anſwers you, That Oyl was one of the Bleſſings of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but when you come to touch his Sacred Garlick, he bruſhes up his Whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, flies into a Rage, and wonders at your folly.</p>
               <p>When the Table is cover'd, your Meal is ſerv'd up in Plates, or very ſmall Diſhes, and hewn into ſo many Diminitive Pieces, that your Knife may lye by till it grows into a Sword before you have occaſion to uſe it: and if you ſhou'd dare to call for a Fork, the good Man will ſtare at you as if your Temples were forked with a pair of Horns. I my ſelf have been at an Entertainment, of no mean Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, where we had all the ſervices in Plate, but not a Fork to be ſeen, where above half the Company had not Knives, and of Twenty Diſhes of Lenten Diet, Red Herring was the chief. The beſt on't is, the Wine is good,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151495:79"/>
and the deſert is excellent, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much ado an honeſt Drunkard may make a plentiful Meal among 'em. That which, at the end of the Entertainment gave me the greateſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, was, to ſee a large Silver Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon brought in, that almoſt cover'd the Table, for every Body to waſh together: And as with us 'tis counted rude to dip into anothers Glaſs; ſo here they count it rude not to dip altogether: when we waſht, a Servant that ſtood at the end of the Table, threw a large Diaper Napkin among us, and every one took a part to wipe him.</p>
               <p>I, who yet had an inclination for the fair Sex, was very uneaſy that the good Woman of the Houſe did not ſit with us, and bring two Daughters ſhe had, which were reported to be very pretty: My impatience to ſee thoſe hidden Charmers, made me im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate with Don <hi>Franciſca Caſtiliano</hi> to ſpeak to the Man of the Houſe to ſend for 'em; but he told me, ſuch a requeſt wou'd offend him, and he wou'd not by any means as'k him;
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151495:80"/>
then I turned to an <hi>Italian</hi> Gentleman who ſat next me, and he aſſur'd me, 'twas to no purpoſe; for he had lodg'd in the Houſe two Years, and never had ſeen the Daughters, I was heartily vext at this nicety, and thought it a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle uncourteous to diſappoint a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger's Curioſity.</p>
               <p>And now I am upon the Subject of Women, give me leave to make you what Deſcription I can of them.</p>
               <p>The better ſort are very Beautiful, fair of Complexion, if compar'd with the Vulgar, for which there can be no better Reaſon, than that they ſtay altogether within Doors, and eſcape the injuries of the Sun and Weather: Of ſhape they are exceeding fine, and indeed that may be generally ſaid of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> both Men and Women for to my remembrance, I never ſaw any there either Deform'd or ill Made.</p>
               <p>There is but one Day in the Year when they are allow'd their Liberty: and then 'tis ſo abſolute, that a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may Cuckold her Husband to his,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151495:80"/>
Face, and defy every thing but his Dagger. On this Day (which is <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Chriſti</hi>) the Churches are all open, and a deal of fine Pageantry ſpread without the Houſes to Solemnize the Feſtival. The Women walk the round of their Devotion to all the Churches and under, the umbrage of that, commit thoſe things which at another Seaſon they have not the freedom to do: And I have been told, that they'll intrigue the Year round to finiſh it at that time, while their Husbands and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are buſy in the general Proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that takes up all their Leiſure; nor are the <hi>Duegna's</hi> ſo dreaded for their watchfulneſs, able to prevent 'em. Beſides the Beauty of their Perſons.</p>
               <p>Their dreſs is ſo ſingular, that a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger muſt needs be pleas'd with it: Their Heads are not embaraſt with Commodes, nor their Waſts with Stayes. On their Shoulders they ware lac'd Hankerchiefs, inſtead of Nightrails, and their Hair, which is the fineſt in the World, is richly pleated with Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons, and falls down to their Seats. The outſide is yet far inferiour to what
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151495:81"/>
is underneath, (for they affect an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhow of gravity) but under their Waſtcoats and Petticoats, they wear the moſt ſumptuous Ornaments they can can purchaſe. But the moſt ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar fancy they have, is that of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring little Feet, and to this end, they cramp their Children when they are Young, and as their Feet are ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, their Legs are inlarg'd, which is likewiſe accounted graceful: I was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at this Cuſtom, and when at the Play-Houſe I ſaw a Woman Act a Man's part, who had large Carman's Legs, I complain'd of it to my Friend, who told me, that was the only Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Part about her. But tho' they take ſuch pains to Beautifie their Feet they are extreamly ſhy of ſhowing 'em, and 'tis held a Favour as great as any thing can be afforded, when one of 'em uncovers her Feet to ſhow 'em; after this and a Kiſs nothing is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd, for he who has theſe two, is Maſter of the reſt of her Perſon.</p>
               <p>The Men of <hi>Spain</hi> are not ſo fair as the Women, they are well in Shape
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151495:81"/>
and Stature, Active, but unwilling to ſhow it: I need not ſay much of 'em, every Hiſtory being particular in this, and every thing elſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the general Diſcription of the Country. Their Habit is for the moſt part the <hi>Caſtilian,</hi> tho' I obſerve, of later Years, they begin to affect the <hi>French,</hi> eſpecially they in the <hi>Maritime</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, diſtant from the Court; or ſuch as have been abroad; and as this dreſs is plain and cheap, ſo it is the moſt advantagious in the World to diſplay the Elegancy of their Shapes, for every thing from the ſhoulders down ſits to the Skin as cloſe as the Skin does to the Fleſh: But about the Neck they're always looſe: One Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that, is, to ſhow their Linnen, for tho' that is not very fine, yet 'tis of an excellent Colour, and the work which they beſtow about the Neck and Hands is ſo amazing, that I really knew a Butcher in <hi>Cales</hi> that gave Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pieces of Eight only for making of his wedding Shirt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:151495:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>Their Beds are the worſt that can be, ſtuft only with Wooll, and quilted down; their Sheets no larger than Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, but alwaies clean and white; the Frames of the Beds are made to fold up like an Old Woman's Stoole and to be remov'd from place to place: Of theſe, I have ſeen Twenty in a Room, ſet cloſe one to another, which tho' it makes the Chamber look like an Hoſpital, yet we found it very ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable.</p>
               <p>Next to their Beds, the greaeſt plague was that of the <hi>Musketoes,</hi> theſe are a ſmall kind of Flies, which in the Night buzzes about your Face, and ſtings moſt intolerably: Strangers never fail of being markt with 'em the firſt Night they lie a Shore, which makes 'em in the Morning look as if the ſmall Pox was broke out upon 'em: Some have fine Gawze Netts to keep 'em off, but that's very rare.</p>
               <p>Curtains here are as ſcarce as a ſhade about <hi>Madrid</hi> on a Sunſhiny Day, hardly any to be heard of: And all the while I lay a Shore, I met but
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151495:82"/>
with one Bed ſo provided: The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides of their Houſes are unhung, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be with Pictures, bare Walls being cooler, and the colour of theſe Walls is whiter than a Ladies Skin: They uſe no Chimneys, and rarely have their windows glaz'd; the two Reaſons are, Glaſs is very dear, and very hot. The ſecurity of their Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows lies in the Iron Bars, before which they have a Lattice, which does as well as Glaſs.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> are very Idle, and conſequently much giv'n to Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: They know the uſe of Dice very well, but their chief Diverſion is in Cards. <hi>Ombre</hi> is a Game as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with them as <hi>Triumph</hi> is with us, but the difference that is in every thing between them and others, is even in this moſt provoking, that as all People upon Earth deal the Cards to the left, they deal to the right, and handle 'em a quite contrary way to us and every Body. And now we are upon this Subject, I have a fair occaſion of reckoning up the differences
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151495:83"/>
of particular Humours between them and us.</p>
               <p>And firſt in general, tho' we are parted but by a ridge of paſſable Hills; yet it wou'd ſeem, we live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſtrange diverſity of Conſtellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for even in the Actions of the Soul we are quite different, as well as in thoſe of the Body: for the <hi>French</hi> Man is Active and Mercurial, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> Speculative and Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine; the one Sociable and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſive, the other reſerv'd, and full of Thought; the one ſo open, that you cannot hire him to keep a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; the other ſo ſecret, that the Rack cannot force him to diſcover: Next in their Faſhion and Apparel: The <hi>French</hi> go thin and open, as if there were continual Summer; the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſo Wrapt and Cloakt, as if it were always Winter: The <hi>French</hi> Button downward, the other up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: The laſt conſtant to their Mode, the firſt more wavering than a Silk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm: The <hi>French</hi> walk as faſt as if they were running from an Arreſt;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151495:83"/>
the <hi>Spaniards</hi> as ſlowly, as if they were newly come out of quartan Agues: The <hi>French</hi> Parade in cluſters; the <hi>Spaniards</hi> never walk above two: The <hi>French</hi> as Airy, as if they were galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardizing in the Street; the other as ſolemn, as if they were marching in a Proceſſion. Whence this prodigious diſcord ſhou'd ariſe is very unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, whether by Antipathy, by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, of Deriſion, or whatever it is, there's not ſuch another inſtance upon the Face of the Globe. I might have added, That the <hi>French</hi> walk with Swords no longer than Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Bodkins, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> wear 'em ſo long, that their Rumps ſeem as if they were Spitted. I was alarm'd at this exceſſive length, and it was told me, That the ſtandard for a Blade was four Feet, but the Cutler always adds another Foot, and then they're about as long again as ours: And becauſe this great length makes 'em awkard and hard to be drawn, they have contriv'd for the better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of Execution, to have their Scabbards open from the Hilt to the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151495:84"/>
Chape, as if it were no more than a Caſe, and the upper end is lock'd with a ſpring, which opens with a touch, and the too ſides of the Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard parting, the Inſtrument of Death comes forth. To this uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable meaſure of their Swords, they have likewiſe great skill in Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, but after another manner than ours, for as we keep a Guard even with our Breaſts, they keep their's even with their Eyes, and the Arm a little bent at the Elbow, as ours is alwaies ſtrait; and yet I ſeldom heard of Duels among 'em, but of Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations without number.</p>
               <p>I am afraid, My Dear <hi>Brunet,</hi> of being too particular, leſt I grow te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, or elſe I cou'd ſit up a whole Winter's Night upon this one To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick of Aſſaſſinating: Let it ſuffice inſtead of more, that there hardly paſſes a Day here when we don't here of ſome new Murder committed the Night before, and yet the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors are never inquir'd after, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver puniſht: This Scandalous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151495:84"/>
of the Law ariſes from the implacable deſire they have of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging their injuries with their own Hands, and many times when a Court of Juſtice wou'd redreſs 'em, they Laugh at ſuch a Propoſal, and ſcorn to give away the opportunity of doing 'emſelves right.</p>
               <p>As to the Laws of <hi>Spain,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they are very well Executed, where the Churches claim does not interfere with it; they have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Courts of Judicature, and the method of Proſecuting Buſineſs is eaſier than any where elſe, for often a Trial is call'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd before the parties know any thing of the matter. I take the Rule to be thus: The Merits of both ſides are got ready, and enter'd into ſome inferior Office, deputed by the Chief, where Officers wait for ſuch purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and there being all that can be ſaid by both Parties made out plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and what ever they can bring material, by their Witneſſes, or any other Teſtimony ſumm'd up in order.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151495:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The depoſitions are packt up in two Bags among a Thouſand more, and ſo ſent to <hi>Toledo, Sevil,</hi> or ſome other Court, where they are carefully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd, and afterwards diſpatch'd to their reſpective Countries, without ſending for, or ſeeing the Parties or Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>In every Houſe in <hi>Spain</hi> is the King's Picture, almoſt in equal vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with the Virgin's and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's, tho' certainly he makes the worſt Picture that ever I ſaw. His Face is Fair, Long, Lean, ſunk in the Cheeks, ſharp Chin, turning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Noſe; his Noſe Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd, great Ears, and his Hair moſt frightfully tuck'd behind 'em: His Eyes are good, his Body ſmall, and his Legs every where alike: I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd of his Diſpoſition, and it was Anſwer'd, That he is infirm and apt to be diſorder'd, That he is of an exceeding ſweetneſs of Nature, fond of his People, Mild and a great Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Jeſting: No correct Politician, nor very ſtudious of Politicks, chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151495:85"/>
rather to rule by the indulgence of Nature, than the Maxims of Art: His Diverſions are Comedies and Bull baitings; his Exerciſes, the great Horſe and the Prayer Book, and his Dreſs the plaineſt in the Court: He Loves the Queen fondly, and She him, nor do the prejudices of their different Countries ever divide 'em, tho' ſometimes the Factions of both ſides are Clamorous. But the greateſt unhappineſs is, the want of an Heir, which tho' every Day Pray'd for, comes to nothing. This is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Misfortune, and Ages yet to come may feel the Conſequences of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spain</hi> is crowded with as great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Men of Quality as any King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Europe, excepting <hi>Poland,</hi> and with a Clergy of the beſt indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the World. And tho' the ordinary ſtanding force of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not ſo great as that of <hi>France,</hi> yet without queſtion the King can raiſe incredible numbers when he is heartily put to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:151495:86"/>And becauſe I wou'd not ſay any thing without a Reaſon, I believe it may be eaſy to prove that this King can produce as numerous Armies as the King of <hi>France,</hi> if he wou'd pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the ſame Courſe. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Spain</hi> abounds with a great many idle fellows, who had rather Starve than Work, and being all fond of wearing Swords, they wou'd glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take the Title of Souldiers, if the King gave 'em incouragement.</p>
               <p>In the next Place: They are ſo well affected to their King, that if his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs requir'd their Lives, they wou'd ſtick at nothing to ſerve him; and ſo fond of their own Liberties, that if there were danger of loſing them, no conſtraint of Eſtates or Families cou'd keep 'em from their Arms: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, His Provinces (tho' not ſo well peopled as thoſe of <hi>France</hi>) are infinitely more, and larger, and if as the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> does, he were to Levy ſo many Men out of every Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage by the proportion of Eſtates,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151495:86"/>
the amount wou'd be prodigious; but as he never had occaſion to make ſo great a Muſter, ſo to eaſe his People, he ſits at as little charge as he can; his frontiers being Man'd with few Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the inner parts of his Empire requiring none. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, was the anſwer of a Courtier to a Stranger, who ſeem'd to wonder at ſo ſmall a Guard as the King kept about him, for when the Stranger de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, If that were all his Guard? The Anſwer was, Are not we all his Defenders? What need is there of more?</p>
               <p>But the principal Augmentation of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Force, will ariſe from the aſſiſtance of the nobleſs, and the vaſt numbers they can bring of their Vaſſals and Dependants: And as this Auguſt Body Subſiſts entirely on the Crown by tenures of one kind or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo it is at the pleaſure of the Crown to command 'em to ſervice, when any urgency preſſes it; and their territories and revenues being ſo ſpatious, it is thought, the leaſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:151495:87"/>
Muſter they can produce wou'd be a Hundred Thouſand. Add to this, That the Clergy too, being for the moſt part feud a tory to the Crown, and bound (though not perſonally) to aſſiſt in the defence of the Realm, their produce muſt be very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But as to the Noble Men, their Services are the more certain, becauſe their Honours deſcend not <hi>de jure</hi> from Father to Son, unleſs confirm'd to the Son by the King's Acknowledgment and Compellation, which makes them more obſervant of him, than in <hi>France</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> where it is demanded as a Birth-Right; and becauſe out of the groſs Body of theſe Noble Men, the King honours ſome with the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Grandees,</hi> privileged to ſtand covered before him, which being the higheſt pitch of Grandeur the State can give, it keeps thoſe great Ones in readineſs to Obey his Pleaſure, in hopes of being ſometime call'd to it.</p>
               <p>Here it muſt be confeſt, that the People of <hi>France</hi> are more Military, and that the King of <hi>France</hi> has a
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151495:87"/>
better Exchequer, and conſequently his Armies are fuller; but conſider, The King of <hi>Spain</hi> of late makes no Conqueſts abroad, and therefore is not neceſſitated to be always in Arms; and if his Exchequer be low, it is becauſe he ſeldom Taxes, but ſlides on in Tranquility with his ordinary <hi>Intrado,</hi> and as well as he can, bears up, without oppreſſing his People: but if an unavoidable neceſſity threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens him, and he be forced to Arm as many as he can, 'tis beyond Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, That he can fill a <hi>Campaign</hi> to as great an extent as <hi>France,</hi> and ſaying That, I have comprehended any Kingdom in Europe. It may be ſubjoyn'd here, that his Country is naturally Strong, defended on one ſide by the <hi>Pyrenes,</hi> his ſhore every where guarded with good Forts, and the other ſide ſecur'd with difficult Approaches, good Garriſons, and the Warlike Nation of the <hi>Catalauns:</hi> So that upon the whole, his charge is very eaſy, which is a happineſs to himſelf and his Subjects.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:151495:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>Of the Language of <hi>Spain,</hi> 'tis a comely Sonorous Majeſtick kind of ſpeaking; 'tis generally the ſame all over the Kingdom, except in <hi>Biſcay,</hi> where they ſtill uſe their own Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Original: but every where elſe 'tis the ſame, only diſtinguiſht in ſome remote Provinces, by idioms particular to every place; tho' in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talonia</hi> and the contiguous Towns it is Corrupted into a ſort of <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock.</hi> It has a very near affinity with the Latin, the <hi>Roman</hi> Conquerors having here more than any where elſe, left their Language behind 'em. 'Tis not very hard to be learn'd, for foreſeeing the uſefulneſs of knowing it, I gave my ſelf up to it, and in three Months I became ſo good a Proficient, that I underſtood every thing that was ſaid.</p>
               <p>But before I end this Miſcellane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Letter, take as near as I can Collect, all the vaſt Kingdoms and Dominions that make up the Body of this Magnificent Empire. In <hi>Europe,</hi> there is <hi>Spain</hi> it ſelf, of two Thouſand
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151495:88"/>
five Hundred Miles Circumference: <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talonia, Naples, Millain</hi> and <hi>Flanders.</hi> In the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> the Iſlands of <hi>Sicily, Sardinia, Corſica, Majorca, Minorca, Yvica,</hi> and <hi>Fermentera.</hi> In the <hi>Atlantick,</hi> the <hi>Canaries, Madera, Cape Verde,</hi> and ſome other ſmall Poſſeſſions. In the <hi>Oriental Seas,</hi> the <hi>Ladrones, Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines</hi> and innumerable leſſer Iſles in <hi>America,</hi> almoſt the whole Continent, with the great Iſland of <hi>California;</hi> in <hi>Africa, Ceuta, Maragan,</hi> and ſeveral ſmall Plantations in all the parts of the World; but there having been no Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count publiſht of 'em ſince the defection of <hi>Portugal,</hi> the Liſt is not ſo exact as I cou'd wiſh it, but enough has been ſaid to prove that the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> has a larger tract of Land than any Monarchy in the World, amounting to more than Thirty Seven Thouſand Miles in circuit: and as his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on Land are of ſo great extent, ſo on the Coaſts he has Harbours of the greateſt ſecurity from Storms, and Forts of invincible Defence againſt an Enemy. And certainly nothing can be more delightful than to Sail up
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151495:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> almoſt every where in ſight of Land; the Country of <hi>Spain</hi> yielding the fineſt Proſpect of any upon the Face of Nature, which appears charming to the Ships that go by becauſe of the colour of the Soil, the numbers of the Towns, and the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Buildings, the Houſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Built of a white Stone, and ſo raiſed one above another, that every diſtinct Houſe may be perceiv'd at a great diſtance; but this is not the Beauty of <hi>Spain</hi> alone, for all the Towns of <hi>Barbary</hi> are built in the ſame manner; above all, the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Town of <hi>Algier,</hi> which without doubt for the bigneſs, is the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable Fabrick upon the Ocean.</p>
               <p>I might here inlarge my Letter, by reviving the old Records, which talk ſo oſtentatiouſly of the great Actions that have been perform'd in this Country by the <hi>Romans,</hi> but I have been too tedious already, and as I intend this but as a Poſtſcript to my laſt, and have all along ſaid very little of the Hiſtory of the Country, 'tis time I ſhou'd pay my Compliment and bid you adieu.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:151495:89"/>But before I ſhut up, and while it is in my Head, let me eaſe my Spleen againſt two things which I abominate here; one is the moſt odoriferous Cuſtom of Watring and Dunging the Streets with what comes out of their Cloſe-Stools; and this they do in ſuch an outragious manner, that I have ſeen the high Streets of ſeveral Towns pav'd in a Morning with that ſoft matter, and a Tide of Urine rolling down the Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels: But what is moſt wonderful, by Noon all this is all gone, and not the leaſt appearance of all that Filth that we ſaw when we roſe: The Air is ſo incredibly fine, that it rarifies whatever it meets with to prey upon; and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> hold it a Phyſical prevention thus to furniſh the ſtreet with Matter for that voracious Planet, leſt it ſhou'd prey upon their own Carcaſſes.</p>
               <p>The other Offence, is the univerſal uſe of Oyl in every thing they dreſs, which is ſo venomouſly bad that it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the Air around: and this is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the Sawce the ordinary People have; ſo that for a whole Streets length you ſhall ſee no sky for the thick Fog
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151495:90"/>
that comes out of their Frying-Pans; and that makes ſuch an intolerable ſtink that I don't know any thing more nauſeous.</p>
               <p>When I was diſcourſing of their Pride, I might ha' told you that I have ſeen a Smith at work upon a Horſeſhooe with a Sword at his Side, and a Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger behind him: His Man held the Shooe, and the Maſter (who never works but upon preſſing neceſſities) gave it the finiſhing Stroak. They hammer their Iron all cold, and that's the Reaſon that a Horſe need be ſhod but three or four times a Year.</p>
               <p>I might ha' ſaid ſomething of their Gravity, and by how many ridiculous Affectations they wou'd be thought reſerv'd and demure, but I have been as good as my word in making this a mad Miſcellany, and I hope you'll par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Confuſion,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I Remain Yours <hi>R.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="letter">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:151495:90"/>
               <head>LETTER IV.</head>
               <p>AT laſt I have the favour of yours, and the Account you ſend me, of the Great Exploits our Soveraign has Acted on the Continent, gave me Infinite Satisfaction. Certainly he's the greateſt <hi>Monarch</hi> that ever came after <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and if his Sea Expeditions had the ſame Succeſs, there wou'd be nothing want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chronicle him, the firſt, in all the Annals of Glory. But alas! When I Reflect on the Inſults theſe People his Enemies, have made on this ſide of his Dominions, I am ſtrangely Mortify'd; for without Complementing their Power, it muſt be acknowledged, that they have an Invincible <hi>Navy,</hi> and 'tis happy for us, that our Harbours Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected us from 'em, or there wou'd have been no ſafety from their Arms. The Fatal Defeat at <hi>La Hogue,</hi> is a bitter Evidence of this Truth, and I wiſh for the Glory of my King, we may never come ſo inopportunely into their Power again: What is there in the World but the Power of this Rival <hi>Engliſh Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:151495:91"/>
to Eclipſe him? The <hi>Genius</hi> of that Prince is a Check to the Career of his Ambition; and tho' it never ſhall be ſaid, that he can blot out the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of <hi>France,</hi> yet give me leave to ſay, his Emulous Gallantries Interpoſe a Cloud of Darkneſs before 'em, and make 'em leſs Viſible to Impartial Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: But to my Buſineſs.</p>
               <p>About the Latter End of <hi>April,</hi> we Sail'd from the Bay of <hi>Cales,</hi> and there being Occaſion to ſend a Scout a Cruiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the General Order'd, that ſome of the <hi>Britania's</hi> Crew, ſhou'd be Ship'd Aboard Her, of which Number, I had the good Fortune to be One. This un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected change pleas'd me, becauſe I thought I ſhou'd ſee ſomething more in a Cruizer, than by Remaining where I was; for the great Ships ſcarcely put in any where, while the Frigots are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Employment, and I was not miſtaken in my Opinion.</p>
               <p>Being now Shipt anew, I ſhew'd my ſelf very forward, in whatever was to be done, partly to get to my ſelf a good Character, but chiefly that I might be in the Opportunities of ſeeing all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures; we had not been long from the <hi>Fleet,</hi> e're we took a ſmall Bark, and
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:151495:91"/>
tho' this was no extraordinary Prize, yet it gave us occaſion to put into <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gier,</hi> the only thing in the World that ſuited with my Curioſity. There be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a War between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Moors,</hi> we durſt not come in near the Shore, but Anchoring about a League without, we ſaw a Pinnace making to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, under a White Flag; the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of Peace. Immediately the Captain order'd his Barge to be Mann'd, and putting White Flag to be Hoiſted; and putting a Lieutanant in Her, he Commanded him to meet the <hi>Tangerine,</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement him in Civil Terms. The Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant obey'd his Inſtructions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Met, he deliver'd by an Interpreter, the Buſineſs of his Errand, and after Mutual Civilities they parted.</p>
               <p>Soon after, a Gentleman from the Town, came aboard, with a Preſent to the Captain, of Mutton, Kid, and other Proviſions, which he Returned in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Glaſſes,</hi> Racking <hi>Bottles,</hi> and other Toyes, which were very acceptable to the Mahometans. They then Treated about the Prize, and ſhe was Bought and Sold, in half an Hour.</p>
               <p>The City of <hi>Tangier</hi> makes a fair Proſpect to the Sea; It was Aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:151495:92"/>
to <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> K. of <hi>Portugal,</hi> in the Year 1471, after his Succeſſes at <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zila,</hi> and has been ever ſince in their Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, till <hi>Katherine</hi> had it for part of her Dowry, and it now being in the hands of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the <hi>Moors</hi> thought it eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be recover'd, by being ſo far diſtant from it's Maſter; and accordingly they ſell to Work under the Conduct of that Tempeſtuous General <hi>Gaylan;</hi> who after ſeveral Defeats which he Received, and the loſs of his own Brother, at laſt Play'd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſo foul a Trick, that in an Ambuſcade, which he made for the <hi>L. Tiveott,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> General, he cut to Pieces moſt of the Garriſon, and the General himſelf. 'Tis Built on a Riſing Ground, of White Stone, and ſeems to be well Fortify'd: The Hills on both Sides are Guarded with Walls, and before it is a <hi>Peer,</hi> Rebuilt by the <hi>Moors,</hi> after it was Demoliſht by the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> You may remember this City was once in Poſſeſſion of <hi>England,</hi> being part of the Dowry of the Siſter of <hi>Portugal,</hi> who was Marryed to <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d, then King of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> but the continual Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the <hi>Moors,</hi> kept 'em always in Alarm, and after a Thouſand Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, it was found too Great a Charge,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:151495:92"/>
for that Remote Iſland to be every Year ſending Succours to releive it; and I am perſwaded, that it is Impoſſible for any <hi>European</hi> Nation to be long Maſter of it, ſince the Provinces under the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> of <hi>Morocco,</hi> are ſo much Improv'd in the Art of War, by thoſe Inſtructions they have receiv'd by the <hi>French,</hi> who are at this Day in all their Camps. I need not ſay what Advantage it wou'd be to him if our <hi>Monarch</hi> had it in his Hands; for 'tis a better Curb to the paſſage into the <hi>Mediteranean,</hi> than any on the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Shore; but I Prophecy, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever undertakes to Beſiege it, will be Loſers by more then their Coſt; and I doubt not but in time, thoſe <hi>Moors</hi> will Recover the reſt of their Country out of the Hands of the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> who are now Poſſeſt but of <hi>Ceuta,</hi> and Two more ſmall Towns, of all the Coaſt which was once theirs.</p>
               <p>And now I have mention'd <hi>Ceuta,</hi> let me ſay ſomething of that, more than <hi>Trojan</hi> Siege; which has already laſted Six Years, and is like to Laſt as many more. I know the World has Lookt upon this Siege, with ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, both of the Beſiegers, and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd; becauſe in ſo many Years time, there is neither One way nor other, any
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:151495:93"/>
Period put to't, neither the Town Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd by the <hi>Moors;</hi> nor the <hi>Moors</hi> beaten from before the Town: But let us ſee, if there may be an excuſe made, for the ſlow Progreſs of the <hi>Moors,</hi> or the weak Defence of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt place, the Camp of the <hi>Moors</hi> (according to what the Muſters amount in general) never conſiſts of more than 15000 Men, and they a Medley of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Nations, collected into that great <hi>Empire,</hi> who till of late knew nothing of the Modern way of Beſieging. 'Tis true, the <hi>Engineers</hi> are moſtly <hi>French,</hi> and whatever little Succeſs they have already had, muſt be aſcrib'd to them: I don't know if it be worth your Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what the Current Opinion is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Undertaking; but I have heard that the General, who has the Command of the Siege, had formerly committed ſome Unpardonable Crime, and it was given him in Choice, either to enlarge the City of <hi>Macchaneſs,</hi> the 2d <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the <hi>Empire,</hi> to Redeem <hi>Ceuta</hi> out of the Hands of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> or in the 3d place, to Forfeit his Head: Tho' I believe this to be a Fable, yet ſo much of it is True, that if the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral miſcarries in his Deſign, his Head
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:151495:93"/>
will be in good earneſt Forfeited, to the <hi>Emperor's</hi> implacable Reſentment: For he rarely Pardons any who fail of what they Undertake.</p>
               <p>In the 2d place, the Kingdom of <hi>Moroc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> is but very ill ſupply'd with Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition: We all know they wou'd be Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring with all the Courts in Europe, for Arms, and other Neceſſaries of War; but 'tis not the Intereſt of any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, to put into their Hands the Power of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring their Trade, and making Inſults on their Coaſts: So that they have little of Warlike Proviſion, but what they get from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who will Traffick with any People for their own private Intereſts, tho' all their Neighbours are to Suffer for their Avarice. By this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digency of Military Stores, it follows, that their Attempts in War muſt be leſs Vigorous. Beſides this, the Garriſon is ſtrongly Fortify'd towards their Camp, and it being open at Sea, for Succours to be continually pour'd in, their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Garriſon muſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently be great, and their Sallies fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and Numerous. To add to all this, <hi>Morocco</hi> is perpetually in War with the Re-publick of <hi>Algiers,</hi> and being a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Preſt in that, they are leſs at leiſure to regard this.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:151495:94"/>On the other Hand, if it be Objected to <hi>Spain,</hi> that they are too remiſs, now they have little elſe to do, that they don't drive their Enemies from before their VValls, and Diſlodge ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Vagabonds, it may be anſwer'd, That, as they are but on the defenſive, they have no more to do, but to prevent 'em from making any conſiderable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs; and tho' it wou'd be highly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for their Honour and Intereſt, to Raiſe the Siege; yet the <hi>Exchequer</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> is always kept ſo low, that they have hardly Mony to Pay their Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; and of courſe, the Work muſt go on with little Reſolution: Beſides, they who are ſent thither, are for the moſt part ſuch who are taken out of the Streets, and ſent into the Service, and who muſt needs be a great while Train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, and Diſciplining, before they can be made fit for a Sally. The Governour is a Grandee of <hi>Spain,</hi> and a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Gallantry, but wanting a Force of Men and Mony to anſwer the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of ſo long a Siege, he is able to do little: His Lady is an Engliſh Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Siſter to the preſent Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi> the firſt Peer of that Kingdom; and when our Ship came before the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:151495:94"/>
Town, the Captain went aſhore, and was entertain'd with a hearty welcome by her and her Lord. When the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment was over, the Governour took all the Engliſh Gentlemen, and ſhew'd 'em the Mooriſh Camp, &amp; to do the K. of <hi>England</hi> Honour, in the Perſons of thoſe his Subjects, he cauſed to be planted on the walls the Royal Standard of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> which when the <hi>Moors</hi> ſaw, they wonder'd what it meant. The French could preſently inform 'em what it was, and by that Signal, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing there were Engliſh Strangers in the Garriſon, they fell to Firing and Bombarding, as if now they were in a humour of taking the City by Storm, and ſoon made the Ramparts too hot for the Curioſity of the Beholders. Then they fell to't Pell-mell, both from the Garriſon and Camp, and this Fury laſted on both ſides, all that Night, and part of the next day, and for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral hours ſailing we heard 'em ſtill at it. <hi>Ceuta</hi> was taken by the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> in the year 1415, and was annex'd with the reſt of the Dominions of the Crown of <hi>Portugal,</hi> to the Monarchy of <hi>Philip</hi> the Second of <hi>Spain;</hi> but
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:151495:95"/>
when <hi>Portugal</hi> recover'd her ſelf out of her Uſurper's Power, moſt of her <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> abroad deſerted the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Yoke, except this Garriſon, and ſome Iſlands in the <hi>Atlantick</hi> and <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Seas.</p>
               <p>Next morning we join'd the Fleet, and we who had been remov'd, were now reſtor'd to our own Ship.</p>
               <p>After ſome days Sailing, we came up to <hi>Barcelona,</hi> where we all Anchored; And now the <hi>Catalauns</hi> began to treat us like Friends; for as ſoon as we ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd before the City, we were ſaluted with all the Guns, and they were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with as many of ours. The Vice-roy, who was the <hi>Marqueſs de Leganez,</hi> came Aboard us, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Pomp of Barges and Equipage, and the General receiv'd him with great ſatisfaction: At his debarquing, he was complemented with all the Guns of the Engliſh Fleet, except of one Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, who (for ſome private Reaſon) did not fire: The next day he viſited the <hi>Dutch</hi> Admiral, and at his Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was ſaluted with all their Guns.</p>
               <p>The City of <hi>Barcelona</hi> is the Capital of the Kingdom of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent City, it being formerly called <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſino,</hi> and then a Roman Colony, inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:151495:95"/>
by a more induſtrious People than the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> for here they are all em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in one Occupation or other; and though the King favours 'em with lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Privileges than any other of his Dominions, yet 'tis with much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty they are kept in their Allegiance: The Reaſon of this is, becauſe the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of <hi>Spain</hi> can't preſerve 'em from the Invaſions of the <hi>French,</hi> who are their near Neighbours, and upon every opportunity, moleſt 'em in their Trade. This Country has at all times been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry apt for Mutinies, and Popular Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, being as nearly related to the <hi>French,</hi> by the diſpoſition of their Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, as they are by their Scituation; and to prevent 'em from revolting, the King careſſes 'em with great Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and when that fails, he has a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Force to awe 'em into Subjection.</p>
               <p>In this City, there are (as near as I can remember) about 30 Monaſteries of both Sexes, well endow'd beſides ſome Churches, and a Cathedral of great Oſtentation. The Vice-king's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace is a large plain Structure, neither well built, nor well furniſh'd, tho' the Spaniſh Hiſtorian <hi>Mariana</hi> commends it highly, tho' he never ſaw it; it ſtands
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:151495:96"/>
at the ſide of a great Square, which is the <hi>Parade</hi> of the <hi>Militia:</hi> The other Buildings are high and fair, and the Shops of the Citizens diſplay a great deal of Wealth. 'Tis here, that the Gallies of <hi>Spain</hi> are laid up, there being an excellent Mole to ſhelter 'em from ill Weather, and convenient Houſes to lay 'em up in the Winter. At this time all the Galleys, as well of <hi>Scicily</hi> as <hi>Spain,</hi> were together; and it muſt be confeſt, ſpite of all Detraction, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> is well provided with ſuch ſort of Navigation: Theſe Galleys are ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly deck'd, and carry one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother between 50 and 60 Oars, mann'd with four Slaves each, who are chain'd to their Seats, and ſtript to the Skin. I believe there might be about 30 in all, which being together, ſide by ſide, made a fine ſhew, and ſurpriz'd us with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, when we turn'd ſhort into the Mole to go aſhore. The Command of theſe Veſſels is held ſuperior to the Command of Men of War, and the Captain of each is a Man of Quality, and the General, a Duke.</p>
               <p>On the Shore, before the Mole, the Nobility and Gentry of the City (which are very numerous) take the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:151495:96"/>
Air every Evening, where one may ſee at one time a 100 Coaches lin'd with the Beauty of the Country, whom the Cavaliers wait upon on Horſe-back, and gallant with more than <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. The City is wall'd round, and mounted with braſs Canon, formerly in ſuch a Number, that there were rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon'd above 300 round the Works, but there are not half ſo many now, the reſt having been taken down by ſome of the former Vice-roys, who repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the King, that they were diſabled and unfit for Uſe, tho' in reality they were very good, and ſo converted 'em to their own Advantage. The <hi>M. de L—</hi> has been a Notorious Offender this way, and when he was depos'd from his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, he feign'd himſelf mad, to elude the Examination they were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make, and ſo eſcap'd an Account.</p>
               <p>There is not in the world better Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery than is in the Dominions of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and this is ſo ſtrong a Temptation to the covetous Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, that they are every year dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd under one Pretence or other, and put into their Pockets. What can be a greater Demonſtration of the Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Government?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:151495:97"/>After ſome little ſtay here, the Fleet weigh'd, and ſtood to the Eaſt-ward, their deſign being to Bombard <hi>Toulon,</hi> or <hi>Marſelles,</hi> and to burn the Ships: It was (my Friend) good ſport to me, to ſee 'em go about a Project which was like to coſt 'em ſo much trouble to ſo little purpoſe. I knew it would be in vain to attempt any thing againſt either of thoſe Harbours; and I was well pleas'd to find they had contriv'd an Expedition, which wou'd turn to their own Diſgrace. Soon as we reacht the Latitude of <hi>Toulon,</hi> there was an Order for all the Long Boats, and Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, to be Arm'd, and the Rear Flag of <hi>Red,</hi> was Hoiſted Aboard a 3d Rate, to Conduct this <hi>Diminutive Armado,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Iſles of <hi>Hieres;</hi> but before this was put in Execution, a ſmall Frigot was ſent in to Spie the Condition of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, who made a quick Return, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with much ado, eſcaped the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, who were ſent after Her, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the General, that it was Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable to Attempt any thing there, the Harbour being Lin'd with invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Forts, and a Stout Reſiſtance provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded round the Shore: This Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Gall'd 'em ſhrewdly, but then
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:151495:97"/>
turning their Deſign towards <hi>Marſelles,</hi> the General Detacht other Frigots, to Diſcover where it was moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to Enter, who came back with the ſame Account they had done from <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> adding, that they were every where ſo Impregnable, that twou'd be but to Sacrifice their Ships, and their Lives to Aſſault 'em.</p>
               <p>Thus being on all ſides prevented, we with-drew further off, and Cruiz'd off the Iſles; when a Furious North-Weſt Blew us quite out of Sight of Land, and put us to a Neceſſity of Shifting for our Safety. This Storm continu'd for a Fortnight, and was ſo Violent, that the Birds were blown from Shore, and came to Reſt their Weary Wings, on the Decks, and Rigging of our Ships. Theſe Poor Creatures were Grown ſo Tame, with Famine, and Fateigue, that it was an eaſy matter to take 'em with our Hands; and there was hardly a Ship that had not Quails, and Turtle-Doves, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on their Yards. The Tempeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſtill Obſtinate, and the Sea Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning High, as it always does in the Gulph of <hi>Lyons,</hi> at length it was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd to ſtand before it, and Steer for the Iſland of <hi>Sardinia;</hi> there was a
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:151495:98"/>
Neceſſity for this, for we began to want Water extreamly; and in few daies Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving there, we Anchor'd in an open Road, within four Leagues of <hi>Cagliari.</hi> Here we found a Freſh Stream, that Supply'd us immediately; and when we had been a while at an Anchor, the Country <hi>Peaſants</hi> brought down Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in ſuch Plenty, that now all the <hi>Marriners</hi> Fed upon Freſh Meat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sardinia,</hi> is an Iſland near adjoining to <hi>Corſica,</hi> oppoſite to the Re-publick of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and the Dukedom of <hi>Tuſcany;</hi> the People of both Iſlands are Account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Barbarous, but we found 'em quite otherwiſe, unleſs we Value their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities by the Good Bargains we made, and count 'em Fools becauſe they Sold us Good Penny-worths: They are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Notoriouſly Ignorant, and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, but far from being ſuch Savages as they are Accounted in Hiſtory; and unleſs the Character belongs to the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> who Riffled and Pillag'd the Poor Wretches, I don't know of any Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity I ſaw while I was abroad. The <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to give 'em their Due, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite at that ſort of Miſchief; for when they had any of thoſe Poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in their Power, they made no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:151495:98"/>
of Plundering them of what they had and turning 'em looſe to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs and Beggarly. I'le give you one Inſtance of this Kind, becauſe I wou'd not fix a Scandal on a People without good Reaſon; and that is thus.</p>
               <p>Two Souldiers having got Leave to go a Shore, under pretence of Buying Freſh Proviſion, bethought 'em ſelves of a Cheaper way of being Supply'd, than by their Mony, and Marching up into the Country, came to a Poor Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant's Houſe, who Liv'd Far from Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, an Honeſt, Simple VVretch, who Fed and Clothed himſelf with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of his own Induſtry, and kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his Houſe all that he was worth in the VVorld: It was this Poor Man's Unhappineſs to be at Home, when thoſe Stroalers entred his Houſe without any Ceremony, who ſeeing a ſtrange People within his Doors, Imagin'd 'em to be ſome of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who, he had heard, were come into their Country, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning to Treat 'em with what he had, he offer'd 'em the Bounty of his Houſe, ſparing nor Meat, nor Wine, nor any thing that cou'd expreſs his Satisfaction of ſeeing 'em there: After he had given them of what he had, and they had Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:151495:99"/>
with all ſorts of Plenty, he loaded 'em with Fruits and other Good things, and Offer'd 'em what Accommodation he cou'd make for their Lodging, if they wou'd be ſo kind as to ſtay with him that Night: They likeing well their Entertainment, thought this was a good Opportunity to Enrich themſelves, and making their way up ſtairs in a Riotous manner, they amazed the unwary Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, who cou'd not gueſs what they meant by Running up and down, in ſuch Tumultuous Haſt: But The Poor amazed fellow, who ſaw himſelf going to be Undone by theſe Rogues, made what Oppoſition he cou'd to hinder 'em, and as he Struggled, and Pray'd, that they wou'd offer him no Violence, one of the Villains with his Dagger, Stabb'd him to the Heart, and laid him Dead at his Feet; and when they had committed that Execrable Deed, they Stripp'd the Houſe bare, and marcht away with the Spoils of their Villany. This Bloody Action was afterwards made known to the <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> who Demanded Juſtice of the General; the General making inquiry after the Criminals, found 'em out, and Sentenc'd the Principal to Death: When this was Reported to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:151495:99"/>
the <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> he Deſir'd no greater Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction than to ſee 'em Condemn'd; and being a Man of Generoſity, himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceded for their lives, only deſiring they might be made ſenſible of their Crimes, but that they might not be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted. The General with ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, granted his Requeſt, but wou'd not let the Murderers yet know what had been determin'd; ſo appointing a day for the Execution of the Principal, and the Puniſhment of the other after the Military manner, they were drawn out under a Strong Guard, and a Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion was Commanded aſhore to attend the Execution: And now behold a turn, and the Juſtice of Providence on the Guilty Malefactor. The Ruffian who gave the Fatal Blow, was pinnion'd, and upon his Knees ready for Death, which he was to receive from a File of Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, drawn out for that Purpoſe; and his Companion plac'd cloſe by him to Suffer the Terror of his Execution: He who Headed the Battalion, and carry'd the Pardon in his Pocket, gave Orders that the Musketeers ſhou'd not Fire, till he made the Signal; but that all the Ceremony ſhou'd be made to Terrifie him a while with the Proſpect of his
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:151495:100"/>
Death; the Lieutenant who had charge of the File, knew nothing of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, but ſuppoſing he was to be Shot, according to his Sentence, gave the Signal for Firing, without asking any further Direction; and in a Moment the Murderer was Torn to Pieces. Judge now my Friend of the Precipitancy of theſe <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but chiefly of the Divine Juſtice, that wou'd not let ſuch a Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Offender Eſcape the Puniſhment of his Blood-ſhed. The other Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent was Puniſht at the ſame time, tho' not by Death, and the Blood of the Murder'd Peaſant ſo far atton'd: The Officer who Commanded the File, was Broke for his Raſhneſs, and the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel that ſhou'd have taken more care, was made Priſoner, but ſoon afterwards Releas'd.</p>
               <p>The City of <hi>Cagliari</hi> is the chief of the Iſland, exceeding ſtrong, and the Seat of the <hi>Vice-Roy;</hi> this formerly was accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo Noble a City, when <hi>Gracchus</hi> took it for the Uſe of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that <hi>Florus,</hi> by way of Excellency, call'd it <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium,</hi> tho' afterwards it was demoliſht by the ſame <hi>Gracchus,</hi> to diſable the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; but in more ſettl'd times it was Re-built, and a ſecond time Taken by
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:151495:100"/>
the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and at laſt reſtor'd by the <hi>Piſans</hi> to it's Primitive Luſtre. I never in all my Life, ſaw ſo plentiful a Market as here, nor every thing Sold at ſo cheap a Rate; a dozen Chickens might be bought for a Shilling, a Kid for 2, a Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton for 4, and a Beef for a Pound, all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in their kind. It was evident, this proceeded from the Scarcity of Mony among 'em, as well as from the plenty of the Market; for the ordinary People were ſo little converſant in Money, that they hardly knew the different Species of Coyn. Yet here, as well as in <hi>Spain,</hi> 'twas eaſy to diſcover the Natural Pride that is in all, who have any Relation to the Crown; and one unanſwerable ſign of it, is, that notwithſtanding their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous Simplicity, their Poverty, and abject Condition, they eſteem 'emſelves beyond the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in Riches and Power: and as in <hi>Spain,</hi> the Natives of <hi>Galicia,</hi> value 'emſelves above all the provinces of the Kingdom; ſo here, they triumph over the <hi>Galicians,</hi> in the ſame degree of ſelf-deſtinction. But certainly nothing can be more ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous than this Vanity; for there's not the leaſt pretence for ſuch a Compariſon, not even in the Fruitfulneſs of their
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:151495:101"/>
Country, which is their chief Glory; for tho' their Corn Harveſts are very ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful, and they ſwarm with variety of all Living Food, yet they are ſo unlearn'd and ignorant in Commerce, that their Neighbours on all ſides fetch away their Commodities for half the Value, &amp; leave the inhabitants, nothing but the diſgrace of being cheated, and ready to Starve in the midſt of Plenty.</p>
               <p>One thing I obſerv'd, from the top of a Steeple, which was very remarkable; 'twas a lake of about a mile in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, which the Sun ſeem'd to have diminiſht from twice that Compaſs, and to have candy'd all the edges round it into an excellent white Salt: I enquir'd of our Guide, if the City made uſe of the Salt, but he told me, that the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians held it to be unwholſome, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad the eating it, under the Penalties of Fluxes, and Feavers; but that indeed the better reaſon was, that there were ſeveral ſalt Works in the Town, and twou'd be a fatal diſappointment to the Proprietors of theſe Works, who paid dear for their Licences, if this were uſed, and that the Phyſicians were in Fee to Cry it down. I was ſatisfy'd with the latter Reaſon, knowing the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:151495:101"/>
firſt to be a fiction; for what cou'd there be of malignity in this Lake, more than in that Rock of Salt, a little to the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Barcelona,</hi> which was ſo Fine, and White, that the General himſelf uſed no other at his Table?</p>
               <p>The great Church here, is very Old, and very Stately; the outſide and Roof, ſeem'd to me like the <hi>Muſaeum</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and becauſe I had once ſeen that in my Ramble thro' <hi>England,</hi> I gaz'd at this with the greater delight. The reſt of the ſacred Buildings are leſs magnificent than in <hi>Spain;</hi> but beneath all, the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Palace is the moſt humble Piece of Grandeur (If you'll pardon the <hi>Soleciſm</hi>) that I ever ſaw. 'Twas Large, tis true, but in no other reſpect, ſuitable to the Pride of ſuch a People; for a private Gentleman of <hi>France,</hi> wou'd be aſham'd to have ſuch a Houſe, accounted the Seat of his abode, or indeed of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement. Some half a ſcore ragged tawdry fellows, are the <hi>Vice-Roy's</hi> Guard; and theſe ſo miſerable, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sailors made ſport of 'em, when they wou'd hinder 'em from Entering. But to make amends for our diſappointed Curioſity, we found the <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of ſo much Courteſy, that there
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:151495:102"/>
was not the leaſt appearance in him of that ſullen Pride, which is natural to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> tho' he was a <hi>Spaniard</hi> Born, and Educated in the Court, the Original of all Vanity. He liv'd in no manner of Majeſty, which for his ſake we Lamented, and thought it pity a Man of ſuch Merit, ſhou'd not enjoy all the Honours of his Place, and we heartily wiſh'd him better Fortune. I don't know how to urge it upon him, for a weakneſs that which he did out of an exceſs of affability, and good Nature: I muſt own I did think it beneath the dignity of ſo exalted a Station, to do what he did, but as he did not ſeem to want ſence to know his Diſtinction, and the quality of his Royal Office, ſo it muſt be underſtood the Effect of complacency to Gentlemen of a Forreign Nation which was in alliance with his Maſter. The thing I ſpeak of was this, That when ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Officers came aſhore, he ſent his Coaches to bring 'em up to his Palace, where He himſelf ſtood ready to receive 'em, I my ſelf was one of the retinue, and ſaw every thing that paſt. When they were within the Houſe, he accoſted 'em one by one, and the firſt civilities being over, he led 'em him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:151495:102"/>
from Room to Room, quite through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Palace, Naming, by parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, what every Apartment was, omitting only that, where his women were, which was not open. This, and other Condeſcenſions of the ſame Nature, was, what lookt very odly to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> But if we conſider the Satisfaction that muſt ariſe to him, by ſeeing ſtrangers in his Government, who were come to defend his Maſter's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and the few opportunities he had of converſing with any but his own People, we can't blame him for the Pleaſure he took in ſerving 'em.</p>
               <p>The Women here are in no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with them of <hi>Spain,</hi> they have indeed in their Converſation, a freedom more engaging than the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ladies have; but even in that they are ſo awkard, that a Man of ordinary Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, wou'd hardly find an inclination for an amour with 'em. The Women of <hi>Spain,</hi> tho' they are in Publick more Reſerv'd, have yet Infinite Charms, to make amends for the Toil of coming at 'em; and as they are very Beautiful (I mean the better ſort, for the reſt are all <hi>Gipſies</hi>) ſo they have ſuch an inſinuating Wit, that a Man of intriegue, may be
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:151495:103"/>
exceedingly delighted with 'em. But the <hi>Sardinians</hi> are the moſt ſtupid Jades in the World, not, I believe, that they want a Force of Inclination equal with others, but they want that addreſs to ſet off, and to engage the Hearts, as well as the Perſons of their Lovers, which the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ladies excel in.</p>
               <p>After the Fleet had Water'd, they prepar'd for their return Down: In the Night we paſt between the Iſles of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorca</hi> and <hi>Minorca,</hi> and before the ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in of the Evening, we made the Land, and it appear'd ſo like that of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> that we thought we had been upon the Continent ſooner than we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; but finding our ſelves here, ſome were of opinion, we had Steer'd a wrong courſe. Next Day we reacht <hi>Barcelona,</hi> and now it was talkt of, as if here we were to take up our Winter Quarters; at leaſt, that the Four Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which we brought from <hi>England,</hi> ſhou'd quarter here with the 7000 <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> we took in at <hi>Final.</hi> I had forgot to tell you, that it had been agreed by the Confederate Princes, to lay Siege to ſome <hi>French</hi> Garriſon in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and to that end, 7000 <hi>Germans</hi> were detacht from the Armies on the <hi>Rhine,</hi> under
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:151495:103"/>
the Command of the Prince of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> to joyn the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> who were already in the Field, in the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guer of ſome important place; which afterwards prov'd to be <hi>Palamos:</hi> The <hi>Germans</hi> being arriv'd at <hi>Final,</hi> ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Tranſports were ſent to take 'em in; and when they joyn'd the Fleet, the Galleys were order'd out of the Mole to attend us, and to carry aſhore ſuch who were to diſembark.</p>
               <p>At this time there was an Order for ſome of the great Ships to be ſent back to <hi>Cales,</hi> and there to Joyn others who were caſt for <hi>England,</hi> and together to make the beſt of their way home: The remaining part of the Fleet Steer'd for <hi>Palamos,</hi> and being come before it, the Army landed, and joyned the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who were about 18000 Horſe and Foot: The <hi>Germans</hi> being 7000, and the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> 4000, when they were together, they made up a Conſiderable Body. The <hi>French</hi> were about the ſame Number, and hearing that the Enemy intended to Beſiege <hi>Palamos,</hi> they marcht their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my within Sight of the Town, and of the Confederates. Both Armies now being in view of one another, ſeem'd to Watch each other for the Riſing Blow,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:151495:104"/>
but neither caring to Fight, the Town was inveſted, and the Siege begun. I need not acquaint you with the general Story of the Siege, without queſtion you have Read it in the Prints, but I can't for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear telling what a hideous ſight this <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army was: They had about 4000 Horſe, which was their only Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable Body; for the Foot was the moſt Miſerable rout of Vagabonds, that ever took the Field. They had neither Cloaths, Arms, nor Proviſion; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> out of Compaſſion ſupply'd 'em with what they wanted, but they made no uſe of any thing but the Food. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch a Number, there were not 1000 Tents in all, but the greateſt part of 'em lay on the parcht Earth without any Covering but the Heavens. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, with the <hi>Germans</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the Siege was carry'd on, and in 5 days, even in ſight of their own Army, the <hi>French</hi> quitted the Garriſon, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantled all the Works.</p>
               <p>There being nothing more to do, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> embarkt again with the loſs of half a Score Killed, and about 40 Wounded; tho' they Suſtain'd the Fire of the Garriſon, and were the principal cauſe of it's deſertion; when we returned
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:151495:104"/>
to <hi>Barcelona,</hi> we heard the Camp was broke up, not without a Battle which the <hi>French</hi> forc't upon the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in which, as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themſelves report, they had the better; and you may be ſure there was nothing wanting to Celebrate the pretended Victory with the greateſt Oſtentation. It was a Deplorable Spectacle, afterwards to ſee thoſe Naked Wretches come home, without Cloaths, or Arms, and almoſt Famiſht with Hunger: And tho' it may be ſuppos'd, the Infantry had but a ſmall Share in the Fight, yet they ſpar'd not to give out, that they alone had defeated the <hi>French,</hi> and overthrown all the Glory of <hi>France</hi> down to the Ground.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> at his entring <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celona,</hi> had all the Honours that were due to his Character and great Services; and afterwards for a Reward of his Signal Performances, was poſſeſt of the <hi>Vice-Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yalty</hi> of that Kingdom. But the <hi>Catalauns</hi> (who are an uneaſy People) grew Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his Power, and were buſy to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice him, in the Favour of the Court, and to miſ-repreſent him; which they did at laſt, with ſuch Succeſs, that he had much ado to preſerve his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that he had a Party at Court,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:151495:105"/>
and the Queens Inclination to ſupport him, and even with all his addreſs, he had much ado to keep himſelf upright, againſt the frequent Complaints of the <hi>Catalonians,</hi> and the Kings Indulgence to 'em.</p>
               <p>The Fleet now Steer'd for the <hi>Straits</hi> Mouth, and when they were oppoſite to <hi>Algier,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Squadron, which was alwaies to Wind-ward, ſaw two Ships of that Republick, which ſtood into the Fleet, to pay their Complement to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> General, his Country being at Peace with the Re-publick, but the <hi>Dutch</hi> at War: After they remain'd one Day and Night among us, they Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and were diſmiſt. The <hi>Dutch</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral ſeeing an opportunity of two ſuch conſiderable Prizes, made the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal for two of his Men of War to give 'em Chaſe; who with ſome difficulty came up with 'em, and brought 'em to their Fleet. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> General was highly exaſperated at his breach of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Hoſpitality; he knew that as the <hi>Dutch</hi> were abſolutely under his Command, that this was an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence he could not Pardon, and that the Admiral might know he reſented ſuch an Affront, he ſent an Officer to
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:151495:105"/>
order him to releaſe 'em, but the Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Churl refus'd, returning in anſwer, that they were the Enemies of his Country, and that he wou'd keep 'em. The General having more Conſideration than to uſe any means of Violence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came his humble petitioner, and in the Language of Humility, beſought him, that as they had put 'emſelves into his Protection, and came but with a deſign to pay their friendſhip to the King of <hi>England,</hi> that he wou'd ſuffer 'em to paſs unmoleſted, and that he wou'd anſwer it to the States, his Maſters: So after much Intreaty they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd.</p>
               <p>Almoſt ſuch another Punctilio of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was diſputed between the French Envoy at <hi>Algier,</hi> and the Captain of an Engliſh-man of War, who was ſent there to renew the Peace between <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and that Re-publick; for when the Man of War arriv'd, which was a Ship of 70 Guns, the Envoy told the <hi>Dey</hi> ſhe was but a Frigot, and that all the Ships of <hi>England</hi> were no better: The Captain hearing how the <hi>Dey</hi> had been abus'd, waited on him, and told him the Envoy had impoſed upon him; and for his ſatisfaction, begg'd that he
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:151495:106"/>
would do him the Honour of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence Aboard her: The <hi>Dey</hi> conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and after a ſplendid Entertainment, the Captain took him to view her all over, and the <hi>Dey</hi> in his own Perſon counted all her Guns one by one, and found 'em, as the Captain had told 'em, 70. When he ſaw the Deceit, he was enrag'd at the Envoy, and at his Return, ſent for him in the preſence of the Captain; and being come, the <hi>Dey,</hi> with his open Hand, hit him over the Face, ſpit at him (which are the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Marks of Infamy in theſe Countries) and turn'd him out of Doors. I had at firſt ſome Suſpition of the Truth of this Story, but when I heard, that it was carry'd to <hi>France,</hi> and that our King Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and threatned to Revenge it, it was no longer to be doubted. I was extreamly mortify'd at this pitiful ſhift of our Envoy's, and am heartily ſorry his Zeal made him ſo indiſcreet: Our Maſter has no need of ſuch impoſtures, and if he had puniſht his Miniſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of menacing the <hi>Dey,</hi> his Juſtice had been more commendable. Our Paſſage down was now a delight, we kept near the Shore, and had the Pleaſure of beholding the Country all the way we
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:151495:106"/>
Sail'd: From a wonderful diſtance, we perceiv'd the Hills of <hi>Granada,</hi> alwaies cover'd with Snow, tho' they lay in the Hotteſt Region of Europe.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Murcia,</hi> is the City of <hi>Cartagena,</hi> firſt Built by <hi>Aſdruball</hi> of <hi>Carthage,</hi> as a receptacle, for Men and Mony, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving from <hi>Africk;</hi> Scituate in a <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſula,</hi> but ſo impregnably Fortify'd in the time of <hi>Scipio,</hi> that but for a Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem he wou'd never have taken it: Memorable likewiſe for the Piety of that General, who wou'd not ſee thoſe <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Beauties, which were preſented to him, leaſt they ſhou'd betray him to Incontinency. By <hi>Conſtantine</hi> it was made the chief City of the Province, which took its Name from it; but this not being intended for a Hiſtory, I have done. 'Tis now a Populous and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful City, well Fortify'd, and has a good Harbour. I ſhou'd have mention'd <hi>Alicant</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Valentia,</hi> famous for the Wines it ſends to all Parts. Over this City is a Caſtle on the Top of a Prodigious High, and Steep Hill; 'tis a hard Journey to't, if you ſet out at Noon, as we did, and when you are in it, you meet with very little to reward your Labour: the only thing I
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:151495:107"/>
Remember worth Writing, is, that at our going in, our Company were ſtript of their Swords, but had them reſtor'd at their going away; this Caution may be neceſſary, for twou'd be no difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for half a Dozen Brisk fellows to roll the Garriſon down the Hill. At the bottom of this, ſtands that Celebrated Place, well known to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sailors, by the Name of <hi>Mount-Whoredom,</hi> and it well deſerves ſuch an Epithite; for there is not ſuch another ſpot of Ground in <hi>Europe,</hi> for all manner of Pollutions. Lower down, lies <hi>Malaga,</hi> and <hi>Velez Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laga,</hi> the firſt (not to mention the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory) is a Town of great Traffick for Almonds, Raiſins, and the Wines of that Name: 'Tis a Rich, Populous, and Strong Place, full of all Nations, but eſpecially of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> whoſe Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize is its chief Reputation: The latter is ſtill Famous, for being in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of thoſe Hills, where there is a ſmall remnant of the old <hi>Moors,</hi> who ſtill ſpeak the Arabick Language; from thoſe hills may be ſeen the whole courſe of the <hi>Straits</hi> of <hi>Gibralter,</hi> the Cities of <hi>Ceuta</hi> and <hi>Tangier</hi> in <hi>Africk.</hi> Next we come to <hi>Gibralter,</hi> formerly <hi>Heracela,</hi> Built by <hi>Hercules,</hi> at the very
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:151495:107"/>
entrance into the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> a ſmall Town, but very Strong, of little or no Commerce; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſul here being in Deputation from him of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laga:</hi> Here the Sea is ſo narrow, that 'tis a common thing for the <hi>Moors</hi> from <hi>Africk,</hi> to croſs and Land in the Night, and carry a way whole Villages into Slavery. On the point of the <hi>Calpe,</hi> one of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous Pillars of <hi>Hercules,</hi> ſtands a little Chappel, ſacred to all Catholicks who ſail by, who alwaies Salute it with their Guns, becauſe it is the moſt Weſterly in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I'll Cloſe this Letter with acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, That after a Pleaſant Voyage, we arriv'd at <hi>Cales,</hi> where we were Welcom'd after a more grateful manner than ever, and where nothing was to be heard, but Univerſal applauſe of the General, for the whole Series of this Summers Expedition; Health and long Life to him, and Proſperity to the Arms of <hi>England,</hi> remaining, in the Sincereſt manner,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your moſt Devoted Friend and Servant,</hi> R. —</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Cadiz,</hi>
                     <date>September 18th. 95.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="letter">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:151495:108"/>
               <head>LETTER V.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Dear Brunett,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THE Winter being again our long Vacation, I began to indulge my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elf in all the Pleaſures ſo much leiſure might afford me. The firſt undertaking I had, was to Ride to St. <hi>Lucar,</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with my old Friend, the <hi>French</hi> Merchant, who had an acquaintance in that place: But before I wou'd under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take my Journey, I wou'd make my Comrade promiſe, to Club for a Calaſh, having had enough of their Pack-ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and <hi>Mules,</hi> in my ramble to <hi>Xeres:</hi> I found no difficulty in perſwading him, I ſound much more to prevail with him, to let me bear half the Charge, in which I wou'd not be deny'd. I had not rid one of the 4 Leagues, we were to goe, but the dam'd Calaſh was ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy, that I cou'd not chuſe but think of the death of being broken on the Wheel: Certainly next to the Wheel, there is no Rack on Earth, like this ſort of Carriages; but tho' our Calaſh was the Devil, our Mules were ſwift,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:151495:108"/>
which in an Hour and a half, ran us to St. <hi>Lucar,</hi> which was four long Leagues, and the end of our Stage.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Lucar</hi> was the <hi>Templum Luciferi</hi> of the Ancients, from the Temple of <hi>Venus</hi> which ſtood there, that Star be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſometimes called <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and of later years very famous for being the Port belonging to <hi>Sevil,</hi> where that Wonder of Cities, loaded and unload<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all her Bullion which came to her from <hi>America.</hi> But ſince <hi>Cales</hi> has got the Aſcendant of <hi>Sevil</hi> in her Trade, ſhe is mightily decay'd, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Town, which ſits upon the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel that goes up to't, is proportionably leſſen'd: Not that 'tis now poor, or ill built, but as formerly ſhe was ſo large, that ſhe contended for the place of the Second City in <hi>Andaluzia,</hi> ſo we now wonder there ſhou'd be ſo little to ſhew for all that Boaſt which ſhe made in the fulneſs of her Glory. It is ſtill a good Town, and has daily Intercourſe with <hi>Cales</hi> and <hi>Sevil</hi> by its <hi>Barco Longo's,</hi> which paſs every Tide between the two great Cities, and is indifferently ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by this Second-hand Trade: The Governour has a ſtately Houſe ſcituate on a Hill, almoſt inacceſſible, that looks
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:151495:109"/>
all over the Town, the River, and the Country, almoſt as high as <hi>Sevil.</hi> Here are but few Monaſteries, but thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well built, and richly endow'd: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong 'em is a little College, erected for the Engliſh Refugees, and dedicated to St. <hi>George.</hi> The Foundation of this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, is juſt as Ancient as what the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh call the Reformation; that is, as their Apoſtacy from the Catholick Church, and was laid for the Recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe perſecuted Catholicks, who fled for their Religion in the Reign of that Scourge of the Catholick Faith, Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this time there were but three Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in't, but they live the better for their being ſo few, having all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues in their own diſpoſal. We ſaw but little here to pleaſe our Curioſity, unleſs you'll eſteem this one, that tho' the Fathers were Engliſhmen; born and bred in <hi>England,</hi> yet by ſo long a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe of their own Language, they had almoſt forgot to ſpeak it; and when I wou'd have talk'd to 'em in their own Tongue, they anſwer'd in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and were not to be got out of that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage into their own. In my many Converſations with theſe Religious, I
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:151495:109"/>
had more than once met with ſuch an Adventure before; particularly after I had ſeen the <hi>Carthuſian</hi> Monaſtery at <hi>Xeres,</hi> I went into the Town to viſit an Engliſh Nun, who had been much fam'd for her Beauty: She indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd that Character which was given her, for I never ſaw any thing more Charming. Her Name was <hi>Philippa Ward,</hi> Daughter to an eminent Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of that Name, who liv'd at <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erto deſancta Maria,</hi> and in her Infancy had put this Girl into this Convent: When I found this fair Creature ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, I devoted to her all my ſpare hours, while I remain'd in that Town, and at other times, when I cou'd be ſpar'd from my Attendance on Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board.</p>
               <p>I found her in every reſpect ſo Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that it was a Violence to take my ſelf from her: And to this very day, I feel ſuch a tenderneſs for her that I never think of her without Pleaſure. This Beautiful Maid had in her firſt prattling days, learnt the Engliſh Tongue perfectly well, her Father's Family had generally <hi>Engliſh</hi> Servants in't, and while ſhe was at home it was impoſſible for her to forget the Language of her
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:151495:110"/>
Parents, but ſhe no ſooner went into the <hi>Nunnery,</hi> and aſſociated with thoſe of another Tongue, but ſhe left off her own, and in ſome Years after, ſo intirely forgot it, that when I went to ſee her, ſhe hardly knew how to pronounce her own Name after the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Accent. And now I have mention'd this poor Creature, ſuffer me to digreſs a little, to eaſe my ſpleen of thoſe reſentments, which every generous Man ought to have againſt the uſage commonly practis'd in the dedication of theſe young Women to Monaſtick lives.</p>
               <p>If a family be over loaded with Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren beyond the Father's Capacity of preferring, the youngeſt are Sacrific'd to Cloyſters, at an age wherein they are not able to underſtand what they are to undergoe. This Lady was a deplorable inſtance of that ſort of Cruelty: Her Father dy'd when ſhe was young, and there being other Children elder than ſhe, the Eſtate was divided among them, and but a Competency for this to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce her into the Monaſtery, with ſome inconſiderable allowance for her Life, intruſted in the hands of her Uncle, her Father's Brother, who as ſhe told me her ſelf, lives now in <hi>London;</hi> but
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:151495:110"/>
the Condition of the Will ran thus, That if ſhe ſhou'd ſurvive her Brothers and Siſters, that then all their ſeveral Fortunes to deſcend upon her, and this Uncle to take it into his hands, and to ſee it paid: When ſhe firſt was put into the <hi>Nunnery,</hi> ſhe was but 5 Years of age, in her 6th her Father dy'd; and before ſhe was 12, ſhe was the only Survivor of of all his Family: She now having a Title to the whole, apply'd her ſelf to her Uncle for her ample fortune; but ſoon as the reſt were Dead, he ſeiz'd all into his own hands, and came away into <hi>England,</hi> and 'twas in vain to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the performance of her Father's Will, from one whoſe temper was not to do her Juſtice. In ſhort, he cajol'd the Abbeſs with bribes, to wheedle the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Girl to remain in the Convent, and while the Abbeſs on one ſide was inchanting her with Stories of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed kind of Life, the Uncle on the other ſide, trifled her out of her hopes of her due; ſo that at length, when it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd if ſhe wou'd profeſs for good and all, ſhe ſeeing no likelihood of receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Fortune, took the habit, and devoted her ſelf forever to the <hi>Monaſtery.</hi> After this, it was impoſſible to think of geting out, and he being now ſecure
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:151495:111"/>
that ſhe wou'd never trouble him more, enjoy'd her Eſtate, and lives upon't to this day. To ſuch an extreamity was ſhe at laſt reduc'd, that even her ſmall annuity was ſtopt, and ſhe liv'd with no other ſubſiſtence but that of the Houſe, and about 4 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling Yearly, allow'd her by one <hi>Malbrank</hi> a charitable <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant in <hi>Cales.</hi> In this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſhe was when I came acquainted with her, and when ſhe told me this Melancholy Story, I cou'd not chuſe but ſuffer with her in her misfortunes. So great was my concern for her, that tho' I knew the danger of taking her out of the Convent, yet a Thouſand times I importun'd her to truſt her ſelf with me, and I wou'd have run the hazard of my Life for her deliverance, if ſhe wou'd have conſented, but 'twas too bold an undertaking for her, and all my prayers were loſt.</p>
               <p>I expect it will here be objected, that no body is compell'd to take the habit: but when the time of profeſſion is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, the Perſon who is to profeſs, is at liberty to ſtay or goe; but of how little advantage is this liberty, when the poor Victims have been ſpoil'd of their Fortunes, and Nurs'd up in a ſuperſtitious Faith of the Sanctity of a Religious Life,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:151495:111"/>
which wants no allurements to make it grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful during the time of the Noviciate? Not but that I know ſeveral who have, after a long abode in a <hi>Nunnery,</hi> releas'd 'emſelves again, particularly a <hi>Dutch</hi> Woman in <hi>Cales,</hi> who liv'd 45 Years there, came out and was marry'd. But theſe are ſuch who have no Eſtates to Tempt their covetous Guardians to keep 'em in, and are of ſo little account, that the matter was not much what became of 'em. Thus far I have digreſt — but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to my company—</p>
               <p>From St. <hi>Lucar,</hi> I was perſwaded to take a tour to <hi>Sevil,</hi> the chief City, not only of this Province, but of all the Kingdom, for Beauty, buildings and antiquity. And here I found Entertainment for my Eyes, and every Sence I had; for in all my life I never ſaw any thing pleas'd me more. <hi>Paris, Lyons,</hi> and <hi>Roan,</hi> and 20 ſuch places afford not ſuch variety of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Not but that I had heard and Read much of its Fame, which did in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure prepare me for what I was to expect, but I found it all infinitely ſhort of the Truth, as much as they, who drawn by the great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of our Kings Palace at <hi>Verſailes,</hi> find it ſo prodigiouſly ſurpaſſing their expectation: As 'twill be impoſſible to give you particular deſcriptions of every thing I ſaw, ſo I am pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by ſeveral Books which are publiſht of it, to which I referr you. I ſhall only in groſs, acquaint you, that for the Elegancy of the publick and private Structures, the ſtrength and beauty of its Walls, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and opulence of its Monaſteries, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious revenues of their Endowments, and
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:151495:112"/>
the Pompous Furniture within 'em, its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſpatious ſtreets, its Antiquity and Reputation for the <hi>Mooriſh</hi> Wars, and other innumerable excellencies, there is not within the whole Compaſs of the Globe a finer City. I cou'd not for a whole week be drawn from this pleaſant contemplation, tho' my friend, who had leſs Curioſity than I, importun'd me every morning to be gone: But after I had remain'd here 7 days, I took my leave with as much reluctance as I ſhou'd have done with a Miſtreſs I had been ſo many years courting for her company, and was that moment to leave her forever.</p>
               <p>Our next deſign was to return to <hi>Cales,</hi> but becauſe I had been twice jaded on Land, firſt by their <hi>Mules,</hi> and now by their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſhes, I was reſolv'd, ill as I lov'd the Water, (for I never had a diſpoſition for't but for my Curioſity) to truſt that Element with my Body; ſo hiring Places in a <hi>Barco-longo,</hi> we ſhip'd in the Morning, and rouled down the ſtream with Pleaſure enough, till we came to St. <hi>Lucar,</hi> and there we entered on the Ocean again. Theſe <hi>Barco-longo's</hi> (if you'll pardon the ill Grammar) are excellent Sailers, and will lye nearer the Wind by two Points than any of our Ships. They are extremely ſharp before and behind, and that makes 'em fly when they are before the Wind, but when they come to be cloſe halled, then are lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and make but little way.</p>
               <p>There are ſeveral dangerous Rocks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween St. <hi>Lucar</hi> and <hi>Cales,</hi> and tho' the Pilots of theſe Boats are dextrous in avoiding 'em, yet for want of a fair Wind, they are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:151495:112" rendition="simple:additions"/>
put to their ſhifts; and when they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, as ſometimes they do, to go to wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of 'em, they hazard by their obſtinacy their own, and the lives of their paſſengers. It far'd juſt ſo with us, for the Wind taking us ſhort, juſt as we were abreaſt of <hi>Rota,</hi> where there runs a great Sea, our Pilot thought to weather the Rock, but was forc't in all haſt, to bear away and go to leeward of it. This was the devil again I thought, and now I was ready to Conclude there was no ſafety in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing this Country, neither by Land nor Water, and to aggravate my ill Humour, juſt as we enter'd the Bay, we we re again beſet with another Rock, call'd the <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> which we had much ado to ſhun. But at laſt the danger was paſt, and we got ſafe in to my great Satisfaction, who was heartily vext to think of being drown'd in a Bay, who had tempted the Main in ſo many Voyages.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not trouble you with any thing that paſt this winter, having met with no adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture worth relating, only ſuch as Regarded the Church, which I am a littte tender of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating, and wiſh with all my heart, I had no occaſion giv'n me of being Scandaliz'd at 'em. But I hope it will be no offence to ſay, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the preſent Clergy are exceedingly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and that the artifices, with which they delude the ignorant multitude are the higheſt reproach that any Communion can ſuſtain. Among many more, give me leave to name one, which is one of the moſt reigning ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals in our Churches, and that is, the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they give to every Rakehell and Villain, from the puniſhment of his Crimes. What
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:151495:113"/>
a defamation is it to the <hi>Altars</hi> of the holy Catholick Church, to defend Murderers and Aſſaſſins? And yet nothing is more frequent all over the <hi>Roman</hi> Chriſtendom, eſpecially in <hi>Spain, Portugal,</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi> In <hi>France,</hi> tho' our Churches have the ſame Sacredneſs, yet we allow no ſhelter but in caſes of great Oppreſſion; for there Juſtice can force its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, and this indulgence is not granted to Wretches, who for their evil deeds ſtand for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited to the Civil Power. I cou'd tell you ſurprizing ſtories of the Tranſactions of the inquiſition, which come to the purpoſe I am ſpeaking of, but 'tis a dangerous topick, and I ſhall forbear meddling with it. But that this evil is notoriouſly Eminent in <hi>Spain,</hi> let this ſtory inform you, which is directly true, and told me by one who was an Eye Witneſs. The <hi>Calla Nueva</hi> of <hi>Cales</hi> (as I told you) is the Exchange, where the Merchants meet in the Morning to Negotiate their affairs; this ſtreet at that time is extreamly crouded, and was ſo, when a Boy preſſing very rudely thro' the Croud, happen'd to tread on a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Toes, the Gentleman being hurt, turn'd round, and ſeeing the boy, who ſtood ſtaring at him as if he dar'd his anger, hit him over the Face, and put him away. The lad taking this for an affront, went away murmuring, and preſently after came back with a Stiletto, and finding the Gentleman ſtill there, got behind him, and with his Dagger Stab'd him into the Reins, and at that one ſtroak laid him flat: His fall drew the Eyes of all the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change that way, and when they ſaw the boy with his Stiletto bloody yet in his hand, every
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:151495:113"/>
body was inquiſitive to know the cauſe of ſuch an accident, the Gentleman's company knew how he had ſtruck the Boy, and now they had ſeen him Revenge the affront, they as well as the reſt open'd a way thro' the Croud, and made a lane for the young Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer to eſcape to the next Convent, which he immediately did, and was there protected by the Fryers, till ſome account cou'd be giv'n of the Wound. The Gentleman in three daies dyed, and ſtill the Boy remain'd in his Sanctuary, and was afterwards made a Servant to the Convent, and lives there to this day, unpuniſh't and unexamin'd. Now what can be more derogatory to the Sanctity of our Religion than thus to protect ſuch impieties? Believe me, my friend, it gives great occaſion of reproach for the Enemies of our Faith to lay upon us, and I can't well blame 'em for ſpeaking truth.</p>
               <p>The Winter being now far advanc't with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any memorable adventure, the General was called home, and another order'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him. He Sayl'd for <hi>England</hi> with the greateſt part of his Fleet, and a Numerous Convoy of Merchants, and I ſtill remain'd on board the ſame Ship I was firſt imbark't in. I can give you no further account of what the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did in thoſe Seas, but that I after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heard, they did all they cou'd to way-lay the <hi>Toulon</hi> Fleet which were now on their Voyage to <hi>Breſt,</hi> but that they miſcarry'd in their deſigns, and the Renowned <hi>Tourvile</hi> brought it home in ſafety to the great diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment and diſgrace of his Enemies.</p>
               <p>When I came to <hi>England</hi> I was diſcharg'd
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:151495:114" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with the reſt of the Ship's Company, and got Mony and my Liberty, and ſufficient Satisfaction in what I undertook, eſpecially if I have contributed to your Diverſion, and acquitted my ſelf of the Charge you laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me according to the deſires I had of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing you, which is the Summ of all my wiſhes and Happineſs. Adieu:</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours</hi> R —</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>London:</hi>
                     <date>January 15th, 95.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151495:114"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151495:115"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151495:115"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
